<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<page confidence="0.323289">
b&amp;apos;c
</page>
<note confidence="0.538396">
\x01 2002 Association for Computational Linguistics
</note>
<title confidence="0.780011">
Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
</title>
<author confidence="0.6999385">
Daniel Gildea
Daniel Jurafsky
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.95775">
University of California, Berkeley, and
International Computer Science Institute
University of Colorado, Boulder
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.99812795">
We present a system for identifying the semantic relationships, or semantic roles, filled by
constituents of a sentence within a semantic frame. Given an input sentence and a target word
and frame, the system labels constituents with either abstract semantic roles, such as Agent or
Patient, or more domain-specific semantic roles, such as Speaker, Message, and Topic.
The system is based on statistical classifiers trained on roughly 50,000 sentences that were
hand-annotated with semantic roles by the FrameNet semantic labeling project. We then parsed
each training sentence into a syntactic tree and extracted various lexical and syntactic features,
including the phrase type of each constituent, its grammatical function, and its position in the
sentence. These features were combined with knowledge of the predicate verb, noun, or adjective,
as well as information such as the prior probabilities of various combinations of semantic roles.
We used various lexical clustering algorithms to generalize across possible fillers of roles. Test
sentences were parsed, were annotated with these features, and were then passed through the
classifiers.
Our system achieves 82% accuracy in identifying the semantic role of presegmented con-
stituents. At the more difficult task of simultaneously segmenting constituents and identifying
their semantic role, the system achieved 65% precision and 61% recall.
Our study also allowed us to compare the usefulness of different features and feature combi-
nation methods in the semantic role labeling task. We also explore the integration of role labeling
with statistical syntactic parsing and attempt to generalize to predicates unseen in the training
data.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985072" genericHeader="abstract">
1. Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976124230769231">
Recent years have been exhilarating ones for natural language understanding. The
excitement and rapid advances that had characterized other language-processing tasks
such as speech recognition, part-of-speech tagging, and parsing have finally begun to
appear in tasks in which understanding and semantics play a greater role. For example,
there has been widespread commercial deployment of simple speech-based natural
language understanding systems that answer questions about flight arrival times, give
directions, report on bank balances, or perform simple financial transactions. More
sophisticated research systems generate concise summaries of news articles, answer
fact-based questions, and recognize complex semantic and dialogue structure.
But the challenges that lie ahead are still similar to the challenge that the field
has faced since Winograd (1972): moving away from carefully hand-crafted, domain-
dependent systems toward robustness and domain independence. This goal is not as
Currently at Institute for Research in Cognitive Science, University of Pennsylvania, 3401 Walnut
</bodyText>
<author confidence="0.351063">
Street, Suite 400A, Philadelphia, PA 19104. E-mail: dgildea@cis.upenn.edu
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.92048">
Departments of Linguistics and Computer Science, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309. E-mail:
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.965414">
jurafsky@colorado.edu
</email>
<page confidence="0.683405">
\x0c246
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984462157894737">
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
far away as it once was, thanks to the development of large semantic databases such
as WordNet (Fellbaum 1998) and progress in domain-independent machine learning
algorithms.
Current information extraction and dialogue understanding systems, however, are
still based on domain-specific frame-and-slot templates. Systems for booking airplane
information use domain-specific frames with slots like orig city, dest city, or de-
part time (Stallard 2000). Systems for studying mergers and acquisitions use slots
like products, relationship, joint venture company, and amount (Hobbs et al.
1997). For natural language understanding tasks to proceed beyond these specific do-
mains, we need semantic frames and semantic understanding systems that do not
require a new set of slots for each new application domain.
In this article we describe a shallow semantic interpreter based on semantic roles
that are less domain specific than to airport or joint venture company. These
roles are defined at the level of semantic frames of the type introduced by Fillmore
(1976), which describe abstract actions or relationships, along with their participants.
For example, the Judgement frame contains roles like judge, evaluee, and reason,
and the Statement frame contains roles like speaker, addressee, and message, as
the following examples show:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.991464333333333">
(1) [Judge She ] blames [Evaluee the Government ] [Reason for failing to do
enough to help ] .
(2) [Message Ill knock on your door at quarter to six ] [Speaker Susan] said.
These shallow semantic roles could play an important role in information extrac-
tion. For example, a semantic role parse would allow a system to realize that the ruling
that is the direct object of change in (3) plays the same Theme role as the ruling that
is the subject of change in (4):
(3) The canvassing board changed its ruling on Wednesday.
(4) The ruling changed because of the protests.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.639743">
The fact that semantic roles are defined at the frame level means, for example, that
the verbs send and receive would share the semantic roles (sender, recipient, goods,
etc.) defined with respect to a common Transfer frame. Such common frames might
allow a question-answering system to take a question like (5) and discover that (6) is
relevant in constructing an answer to the question:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9993125">
(5) Which party sent absentee ballots to voters?
(6) Both Democratic and Republican voters received absentee ballots from
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.977296756097561">
their party.
This shallow semantic level of interpretation has additional uses outside of gen-
eralizing information extraction, question answering, and semantic dialogue systems.
One such application is in word sense disambiguation, where the roles associated with
a word can be cues to its sense. For example, Lapata and Brew (1999) and others have
shown that the different syntactic subcategorization frames of a verb such as serve can
be used to help disambiguate a particular instance of the word. Adding semantic role
subcategorization information to this syntactic information could extend this idea to
\x0c247
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
use richer semantic knowledge. Semantic roles could also act as an important interme-
diate representation in statistical machine translation or automatic text summarization
and in the emerging field of text data mining (TDM) (Hearst 1999). Finally, incorpo-
rating semantic roles into probabilistic models of language may eventually yield more
accurate parsers and better language models for speech recognition.
This article describes an algorithm for identifying the semantic roles filled by con-
stituents in a sentence. We apply statistical techniques that have been successful for the
related problems of syntactic parsing, part-of-speech tagging, and word sense disam-
biguation, including probabilistic parsing and statistical classification. Our statistical
algorithms are trained on a hand-labeled data set: the FrameNet database (Baker, Fill-
more, and Lowe 1998; Johnson et al. 2001). The FrameNet database defines a tag set
of semantic roles called frame elements and included, at the time of our experiments,
roughly 50,000 sentences from the British National Corpus hand-labeled with these
frame elements.
This article presents our system in stages, beginning in Section 2 with a more de-
tailed description of the data and the set of frame elements or semantic roles used. We
then introduce (in Section 3) the statistical classification technique used and examine
in turn the knowledge sources of which our system makes use. Section 4 describes
the basic syntactic and lexical features used by our system, which are derived from
a Penn Treebankstyle parse of individual sentences to be analyzed. We break our
task into two subproblems: finding the relevant sentence constituents (deferred until
Section 5), and giving them the correct semantic labels (Sections 4.2 and 4.3). Section 6
adds higher-level semantic knowledge to the system, attempting to model the selec-
tional restrictions on role fillers not directly captured by lexical statistics. We compare
hand-built and automatically derived resources for providing this information. Sec-
tion 7 examines techniques for adding knowledge about systematic alternations in
verb argument structure with sentence-level features. We combine syntactic parsing
and semantic role identification into a single probability model in Section 8. Section 9
addresses the question of generalizing statistics from one target predicate to another,
beginning with a look at domain-independent thematic roles in Section 9.1. Finally we
draw conclusions and discuss future directions in Section 10.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992295" genericHeader="keywords">
2. Semantic Roles
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993347">
Semantic roles are one of the oldest classes of constructs in linguistic theory, dating
back thousands of years to Paninis karaka theory (Misra 1966; Rocher 1964; Dahiya
1995). Longevity, in this case, begets variety, and the literature records scores of pro-
posals for sets of semantic roles. These sets of roles range from the very specific to
the very general, and many have been used in computational implementations of one
type or another.
At the specific end of the spectrum are domain-specific roles such as the from air-
port, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as
eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theo-
ries with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient
(Van Valin 1993; Dowty 1991). In between lie many theories with approximately 10
roles, such as Fillmores (1971) list of nine: Agent, Experiencer, Instrument, Ob-
</bodyText>
<keyword confidence="0.597847">
ject, Source, Goal, Location, Time, and Path.1
</keyword>
<figure confidence="0.981797672727273">
1 There are scores of other theories with slightly different sets of roles, including those of Fillmore (1968),
Jackendoff (1972), and Schank (1972); see Somers (1987) for an excellent summary.
\x0c248
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
banterv
debatev
conversev
gossipv
disputen
discussionn
tiffn
Conversation
Frame:
Protagonist1
Protagonist2
Protagonists
Topic
Medium
Frame Elements:
arguev
Domain: Communication Domain: Cognition
Frame: Questioning
Topic
Medium
Frame Elements: Speaker
Addressee
Message
Frame:
Topic
Medium
Frame Elements: Speaker
Addressee
Message
Statement
Frame:
Frame Elements:
Judgment
Judge
Evaluee
Reason
Role
disputen
blamev faultn
admirev
admirationn
disapprovev
blamen
appreciatev
Frame:
Frame Elements:
Categorization
Cognizer
Item
Category
Criterion
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.903679">
Figure 1
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.967452466666667">
Sample domains and frames from the FrameNet lexicon.
Many of these sets of roles have been proposed by linguists as part of theories
of linking, the part of grammatical theory that describes the relationship between
semantic roles and their syntactic realization. Other sets have been used by computer
scientists in implementing natural language understanding systems. As a rule, the
more abstract roles have been proposed by linguists, who are more concerned with
explaining generalizations across verbs in the syntactic realization of their arguments,
whereas the more specific roles have more often been proposed by computer scientists,
who are more concerned with the details of the realization of the arguments of specific
verbs.
The FrameNet project (Baker, Fillmore, and Lowe 1998) proposes roles that are
neither as general as the 10 abstract thematic roles, nor as specific as the thousands of
potential verb-specific roles. FrameNet roles are defined for each semantic frame. A
frame is a schematic representation of situations involving various participants, props,
and other conceptual roles (Fillmore 1976). For example, the frame Conversation,
shown in Figure 1, is invoked by the semantically related verbs argue, banter, debate,
converse, and gossip, as well as the nouns dispute, discussion, and tiff, and is defined as
follows:
(7) Two (or more) people talk to one another. No person is construed as
only a speaker or only an addressee. Rather, it is understood that both
(or all) participants do some speaking and some listening: the process is
understood to be symmetrical or reciprocal.
The roles defined for this frame, and shared by all its lexical entries, include
Protagonist-1 and Protagonist-2 or simply Protagonists for the participants
in the conversation, as well as Medium and Topic. Similarly, the Judgment frame
mentioned above has the roles Judge, Evaluee, and Reason and is invoked by verbs
such as blame, admire, and praise and nouns such as fault and admiration. We refer to
the roles for a given frame as frame elements. A number of hand-annotated exam-
ples from the Judgment frame are included below to give a flavor of the FrameNet
database:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.979235555555556">
(8) [Judge She ] blames [Evaluee the Government ] [Reason for failing to do
enough to help ] .
(9) Holman would characterise this as blaming [Evaluee the poor ] .
\x0c249
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
(10) The letter quotes Black as saying that [Judge white and Navajo ranchers ]
misrepresent their livestock losses and blame [Reason everything ] [Evaluee
on coyotes ] .
(11) The only dish she made that we could tolerate was [Evaluee syrup tart
which2
] [Judge we ] praised extravagantly with the result that it became
our unhealthy staple diet.
(12) Im bound to say that I meet a lot of [Judge people who ] praise [Evaluee
me ] [Reason for speaking up ] but dont speak up themselves.
(13) Specimens of her verse translations of Tasso (Jerusalem Delivered) and
Verri (Roman Nights) circulated to [ Manner warm ] [Judge critical ] praise;
but unforeseen circumstance prevented their publication.
(14) And if Sam Snort hails Doyler as monumental is he perhaps erring on
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9898898125">
the side of being excessive in [ Judge his ] praise?
Defining semantic roles at this intermediate frame level helps avoid some of
the well-known difficulties of defining a unique small set of universal, abstract the-
matic roles while also allowing some generalization across the roles of different verbs,
nouns, and adjectives, each of which adds semantics to the general frame or high-
lights a particular aspect of the frame. One way of thinking about traditional ab-
stract thematic roles, such as Agent and Patient, in the context of FrameNet is to
conceive them as frame elements defined by abstract frames, such as action and mo-
tion, at the top of an inheritance hierarchy of semantic frames (Fillmore and Baker
2000).
The examples above illustrate another difference between frame elements and
thematic roles as commonly described in the literature. Whereas thematic roles tend
to be arguments mainly of verbs, frame elements can be arguments of any predicate,
and the FrameNet database thus includes nouns and adjectives as well as verbs.
The examples above also illustrate a few of the phenomena that make it hard to
identify frame elements automatically. Many of these are caused by the fact that there
is not always a direct correspondence between syntax and semantics. Whereas the
subject of blame is often the Judge, the direct object of blame can be an Evaluee (e.g.,
the poor in blaming the poor) or a Reason (e.g., everything in blame everything
on coyotes). The identity of the Judge can also be expressed in a genitive pronoun,
(e.g., his in his praise) or even an adjective (e.g., critical in critical praise).
The corpus used in this project is perhaps best described in terms of the method-
ology used by the FrameNet team. We outline the process here; for more detail see
Johnson et al. (2001). As the first step, semantic frames were defined for the general
domains chosen; the frame elements, or semantic roles for participants in a frame,
were defined; and a list of target words, or lexical predicates whose meaning includes
aspects of the frame, was compiled for each frame. Example sentences were chosen
by searching the British National Corpus for instances of each target word. Separate
searches were performed for various patterns over lexical items and part-of-speech
sequences in the target words context, producing a set of subcorpora for each tar-
get word, designed to capture different argument structures and ensure that some
examples of each possible syntactic usage of the target word would be included in
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.778986" genericHeader="introduction">
2 The FrameNet annotation includes both the relative pronoun and its antecedent in the target words
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973233388888889">
clause.
\x0c250
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
the final database. Thus, the focus of the project was on completeness of examples for
lexicographic needs, rather than on statistically representative data. Sentences from
each subcorpus were then annotated by hand, marking boundaries of each frame el-
ement expressed in the sentence and assigning tags for the annotated constituents
frame semantic role, syntactic category (e.g., noun phrase or prepositional phrase),
and grammatical function in relation to the target word (e.g., object or complement
of a verb). In the final phase of the process, the annotated sentences for each tar-
get word were checked for consistency. In addition to the tags just mentioned, the
annotations include certain other information, which we do not make use of in this
work, such as word sense tags for some target words and tags indicating metaphoric
usages.
Tests of interannotator agreement were performed for data from a small num-
ber of predicates before the final consistency check. Interannotator agreement at the
sentence level, including all frame element judgments and boundaries for one predi-
cate, varied from .66 to .82 depending on the predicate. The kappa statistic (Siegel
and Castellan 1988) varied from .67 to .82. Because of the large number of pos-
sible categories when boundary judgments are considered, kappa is nearly iden-
tical to the interannotator agreement. The system described in this article (which
gets .65/.61 precision/recall on individual frame elements; see Table 15) correctly
identifies all frame elements in 38% of test sentences. Although this .38 is not di-
rectly comparable to the .66.82 interannotator agreements, its clear that the per-
formance of our system still falls significantly short of human performance on the
task.
The British National Corpus was chosen as the basis of the FrameNet project
despite differences between British and American usage because, at 100 million words,
it provides the largest corpus of English with a balanced mixture of text genres. The
British National Corpus includes automatically assigned syntactic part-of-speech tags
for each word but does not include full syntactic parses. The FrameNet annotators did
not make use of, or produce, a complete syntactic parse of the annotated sentences,
although some syntactic information is provided by the grammatical function and
phrase type tags of the annotated frame elements.
The preliminary version of the FrameNet corpus used for our experiments con-
tained 67 frame types from 12 general semantic domains chosen for annotation. A
complete list of the semantic domains represented in our data is shown in Table 1,
along with representative frames and predicates. Within these frames, examples of a
total of 1,462 distinct lexical predicates, or target words, were annotated: 927 verbs,
339 nouns, and 175 adjectives. There are a total of 49,013 annotated sentences and
99,232 annotated frame elements (which do not include the target words them-
selves).
How important is the particular set of semantic roles that underlies our sys-
tem? For example, could the optimal choice of semantic roles be very dependent on
the application that needs to exploit their information? Although there may well be
application-specific constraints on semantic roles, our semantic role classifiers seem
in practice to be relatively independent of the exact set of semantic roles under con-
sideration. Section 9.1 describes an experiment in which we collapsed the FrameNet
roles into a set of 18 abstract thematic roles. We then retrained our classifier and
achieved roughly comparable results; overall performance was 82.1% for abstract the-
matic roles, compared to 80.4% for frame-specific roles. Although this doesnt show
that the detailed set of semantic roles is irrelevant, it does suggest that our statistical
classification algorithm, at least, is relatively robust to even quite large changes in role
identities.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.575409">
\x0c251
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.4475615">
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 1
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.995232090909091">
Semantic domains with sample frames and predicates from the FrameNet lexicon.
Domain Sample Frames Sample Predicates
Body Action flutter, wink
Cognition Awareness attention, obvious
Judgment blame, judge
Invention coin, contrive
Communication Conversation bicker, confer
Manner lisp, rant
Emotion Directed angry, pleased
Experiencer-Obj bewitch, rile
General Imitation bogus, forge
Health Response allergic, susceptible
Motion Arriving enter, visit
Filling annoint, pack
Perception Active glance, savour
Noise snort, whine
Society Leadership emperor, sultan
Space Adornment cloak, line
Time Duration chronic, short
Iteration daily, sporadic
Transaction Basic buy, spend
Wealthiness broke, well-off
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985405" genericHeader="related work">
3. Related Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99767632">
Assignment of semantic roles is an important part of language understanding, and
the problem of how to assign such roles has been attacked by many computational
systems. Traditional parsing and understanding systems, including implementations of
unification-based grammars such as Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar (HPSG)
(Pollard and Sag 1994), rely on hand-developed grammars that must anticipate each
way in which semantic roles may be realized syntactically. Writing such grammars is
time consuming, and typically such systems have limited coverage.
Data-driven techniques have recently been applied to template-based semantic
interpretation in limited domains by shallow systems that avoid complex feature
structures and often perform only shallow syntactic analysis. For example, in the
context of the Air Traveler Information System (ATIS) for spoken dialogue, Miller et
al. (1996) computed the probability that a constituent such as Atlanta filled a semantic
slot such as Destination in a semantic frame for air travel. In a data-driven approach
to information extraction, Riloff (1993) builds a dictionary of patterns for filling slots
in a specific domain such as terrorist attacks, and Riloff and Schmelzenbach (1998)
extend this technique to derive automatically entire case frames for words in the
domain. These last systems make use of a limited amount of hand labor to accept or
reject automatically generated hypotheses. They show promise for a more sophisticated
approach to generalizing beyond the relatively small number of frames considered in
the tasks. More recently, a domain-independent system has been trained by Blaheta
and Charniak (2000) on the function tags, such as Manner and Temporal, included
in the Penn Treebank corpus. Some of these tags correspond to FrameNet semantic
roles, but the Treebank tags do not include all the arguments of most predicates. In this
article, we aim to develop a statistical system for automatically learning to identify all
semantic roles for a wide variety of predicates in unrestricted text.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.647462">
\x0c252
</page>
<reference confidence="0.2437315">
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
4. Probability Estimation for Roles
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.998894625">
In this section we describe the first, basic version of our statistically trained system
for automatically identifying frame elements in text. The system will be extended in
later sections. We first describe in detail the sentence- and constituent-level features
on which our system is based and then use these features to calculate probabilities
for predicting frame element labels in Section 4.2. In this section we give results for
a system that labels roles using the human-annotated boundaries for the frame ele-
ments within the sentence; we return to the question of automatically identifying the
boundaries in Section 5.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.686133">
4.1 Features Used in Assigning Semantic Roles
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999854529411765">
Our system is a statistical one, based on training a classifier on a labeled training set
and testing on a held-out portion of the data. The system is trained by first using an
automatic syntactic parser to analyze the 36,995 training sentences, matching annotated
frame elements to parse constituents and extracting various features from the string
of words and the parse tree. During testing, the parser is run on the test sentences
and the same features are extracted. Probabilities for each possible semantic role r are
then computed from the features. The probability computation is described in the next
section; here we discuss the features used.
The features used represent various aspects of the syntactic structure of the sen-
tence as well as lexical information. The relationship between such surface manifes-
tations and semantic roles is the subject of linking theory (see Levin and Rappaport
Hovav [1996] for a synthesis of work in this area). In general, linking theory argues
that the syntactic realization of arguments of a predicate is predictable from semantics;
exactly how this relationship works, however, is the subject of much debate. Regardless
of the underlying mechanisms used to generate syntax from semantics, the relation-
ship between the two suggests that it may be possible to learn to recognize semantic
relationships from syntactic cues, given examples with both types of information.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.573304">
4.1.1 Phrase Type. Different semantic roles tend to be realized by different syntactic
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97461835">
categories. For example, in communication frames, the Speaker is likely to appear
as a noun phrase, Topic as a prepositional phrase or noun phrase, and Medium as a
prepositional phrase, as in: [Speaker We ] talked [Topic about the proposal ] [Medium over
the phone ] .
The phrase type feature we used indicates the syntactic category of the phrase
expressing the semantic roles, using the set of syntactic categories of the Penn Treebank
project, as described in Marcus, Santorini, and Marcinkiewicz (1993). In our data, frame
elements are most commonly expressed as noun phrases (NPs, 47% of frame elements
in the training set), and prepositional phrases (PPs, 22%). The next most common
categories are adverbial phrases (ADVPs, 4%), particles (e.g. make something up;
PRTs, 2%) and clauses (SBARs, 2%, and Ss, 2%). (Tables 22 and 23 in the Appendix
provides a listing of Penn Treebanks part-of-speech tags and constituent labels.)
We used Collins (1997) statistical parser trained on examples from the Penn Tree-
bank to generate parses of the same format for the sentences in our data. Phrase types
were derived automatically from parse trees generated by the parser, as shown in Fig-
ure 2. Given the automatically generated parse tree, the constituent spanning the same
set of words as each annotated frame element was found, and the constituents nonter-
minal label was taken as the phrase type. In cases in which more than one constituent
matches because of a unary production in the parse tree, the higher constituent was
chosen.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.996487636363636">
\x0c253
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
He
PRP
NP
heard
VBD
the sound of liquid slurping in a metal container
NP
as
IN
Farrell
NNP
NP
approached
VBD
him
PRP
NP
from
IN
behind
NN
NP
PP
VP
S
SBAR
VP
S
target Source
Goal
Theme
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.769641">
Figure 2
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.958124375">
A sample sentence with parser output (above) and FrameNet annotation (below). Parse
constituents corresponding to frame elements are highlighted.
The matching was performed by calculating the starting and ending word po-
sitions for each constituent in the parse tree, as well as for each annotated frame
element, and matching each frame element with the parse constituent with the same
beginning and ending points. Punctuation was ignored in this computation. Because
of parsing errors, or, less frequently, mismatches between the parse tree formalism and
the FrameNet annotation standards, for 13% of the frame elements in the training set,
there was no parse constituent matching an annotated frame element. The one case of
systematic mismatch between the parse tree formalism and the FrameNet annotation
standards is the FrameNet convention of including both a relative pronoun and its
antecedent in frame elements, as in the first frame element in the following sentence:
(15) In its rough state he showed it to [Agt the Professor, who ] bent [BPrt his
grey beard ] [Path over the neat script ] and read for some time in silence.
Mismatch caused by the treatment of relative pronouns accounts for 1% of the frame
elements in the training set.
During testing, the largest constituent beginning at the frame elements left bound-
ary and lying entirely within the element was used to calculate the frame elements
features. We did not use this technique on the training set, as we expected that it
would add noise to the data, but instead discarded examples with no matching parse
constituent. Our technique for finding a near match handles common parse errors
such as a prepositional phrase being incorrectly attached to a noun phrase at the
right-hand edge, and it guarantees that some syntactic category will be returned: the
part-of-speech tag of the frame elements first word in the limiting case.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.903707">
4.1.2 Governing Category. The correlation between semantic roles and syntactic re-
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97879775">
alization as subject or direct object is one of the primary facts that linking theory at-
tempts to explain. It was a motivation for the case hierarchy of Fillmore (1968), which
\x0c254
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
allowed such rules as If there is an underlying Agent, it becomes the syntactic sub-
ject. Similarly, in his theory of macroroles, Van Valin (1993) describes the Actor as
being preferred in English for the subject. Functional grammarians consider syntactic
subjects historically to have been grammaticalized agent markers. As an example of
how such a feature can be useful, in the sentence He drove the car over the cliff,
the subject NP is more likely to fill the Agent role than the other two NPs. We will
discuss various grammatical-function features that attempt to indicate a constituents
syntactic relation to the rest of the sentence, for example, as a subject or object of a
verb.
The first such feature, which we call governing category, or gov, has only two
values, S and VP, corresponding to subjects and objects of verbs, respectively. This
feature is restricted to apply only to NPs, as it was found to have little effect on other
phrase types. As with phrase type, the feature was read from parse trees returned by
the parser. We follow links from child to parent up the parse tree from the constituent
corresponding to a frame element until either an S or VP node is found and assign
the value of the feature according to whether this node is an S or a VP. NP nodes
found under S nodes are generally grammatical subjects, and NP nodes under VP
nodes are generally objects. In most cases the S or VP node determining the value of
this feature immediately dominates the NP node, but attachment errors by the parser
or constructions such as conjunction of two NPs can cause intermediate nodes to
be introduced. Searching for higher ancestor nodes makes the feature robust to such
cases. Even given good parses, this feature is not perfect in discriminating grammatical
functions, and in particular it confuses direct objects with adjunct NPs such as temporal
phrases. For example, town in the sentence He left town and yesterday in the sentence
He left yesterday will both be assigned a governing category of VP. Direct and
indirect objects both appear directly under the VP node. For example, in the sentence
He gave me a new hose, me and a new hose are both assigned a governing category
of VP. More sophisticated handling of such cases could improve our system.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.516358">
4.1.3 Parse Tree Path. Like the governing-category feature described above, the parse
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987284476190476">
tree path feature (path) is designed to capture the syntactic relation of a constituent
to the rest of the sentence. The path feature, however, describes the syntactic relation
between the target word (that is, the predicate invoking the semantic frame) and the
constituent in question, whereas the gov feature is independent of where the target
word appears in the sentence; that is, it identifies all subjects whether they are the
subject of the target word or not.
The path feature is defined as the path from the target word through the parse
tree to the constituent in question, represented as a string of parse tree nonterminals
linked by symbols indicating upward or downward movement through the tree, as
shown in Figure 3. Although the path is composed as a string of symbols, our system
treats the string as an atomic value. The path includes, as the first element of the
string, the part of speech of the target word and, as the last element, the phrase type
or syntactic category of the sentence constituent marked as a frame element. After
some experimentation, we settled on a version of the path feature that collapses the
various part-of-speech tags for verbs, including past-tense verb (VBD), third-person
singular present-tense verb (VBZ), other present-tense verb (VBP), and past participle
(VBN), into a single verb tag denoted VB.
Our path feature is dependent on the syntactic representation used, which in our
case is the Treebank-2 annotation style (Marcus et al. 1994), as our parser is trained
on this later version of the Treebank data. Figure 4 shows the annotation for the
sentence They expect him to cut costs throughout the organization, which exhibits
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9634604">
\x0c255
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
S
NP
VP
NP
He ate some pancakes
PRP
DT NN
VB
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.637616">
Figure 3
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9779052">
In this example, the path from the target word ate to the frame element He can be represented
as VBVPSNP, with indicating upward movement in the parse tree and downward
movement. The NP corresponding to He is found as described in Section 4.1.1.
Figure 4
Treebank annotation of raising constructions.
the syntactic phenomenon known as subject-to-object raising, in which the main verbs
object is interpreted as the embedded verbs subject. The Treebank-2 style tends to be
generous in its usage of S nodes to indicate clauses, a decision intended to make
possible a relatively straightforward mapping from S nodes to predications. In this
example, the path from cut to the frame element him would be VBVPVPSNP,
which typically indicates a verbs subject, despite the accusative case of the pronoun
him. For the target word of expect in the sentence of Figure 4, the path to him would
be VBVPSNP, rather than the typical direct-object path of VBVPNP.
An example of Treebank-2 annotation of an equi construction, in which a noun
phrase serves as an argument of both the main and subordinate verbs, is shown in
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.680985">
Figure 5. Here, an empty category is used in the subject position of the subordinate
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9579498">
clause and is co-indexed with the NP Congress in the direct-object position of the main
clause. The empty category, however, is not used in the statistical model of the parser
or shown in its output and is also not used by the FrameNet annotation, which would
mark the NP Congress as a frame element of raise in this example. Thus, the value
of our path feature from the target word raise to the frame element Congress would
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.594399555555556">
\x0c256
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Figure 5
Treebank annotation of equi constructions. An empty category is indicated by an asterisk, and
co-indexing by superscript numeral.
Table 2
Most frequent values of the path feature in the training data.
Frequency Path Description
14.2% VBVPPP PP argument/adjunct
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.496581" genericHeader="method">
11.8 VBVPSNP Subject
10.1 VBVPNP Object
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.672347">
7.9 VBVPVPSNP Subject (embedded VP)
4.1 VBVPADVP Adverbial adjunct
</subsectionHeader>
<listItem confidence="0.855769166666667">
3.0 NNNPNPPP Prepositional complement of noun
1.7 VBVPPRT Adverbial particle
1.6 VBVPVPVPSNP Subject (embedded VP)
14.2 No matching parse constituent
31.4 Other
be VBVPVPSVPNP, and from the target word of persuaded the path to Congress
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.94487855">
would be the standard direct-object path VBVPNP.
Other changes in annotation style from the original Treebank style were specifi-
cally intended to make predicate argument structure easy to read from the parse trees
and include new empty (or null) constituents, co-indexing relations between nodes,
and secondary functional tags such as subject and temporal. Our parser output, how-
ever, does not include this additional information, but rather simply gives trees of
phrase type categories. The sentence in Figure 4 is one example of how the change in
annotation style of Treebank-2 can affect this level of representation; the earlier style
assigned the word him an NP node directly under the VP of expect.
The most common values of the path feature, along with interpretations, are shown
in Table 2.
For the purposes of choosing a frame element label for a constituent, the path
feature is similar to the gov feature defined above. Because the path captures more
information than the governing category, it may be more susceptible to parser errors
and data sparseness. As an indication of this, our path feature takes on a total of
2,978 possible values in the training data when frame elements with no matching
\x0c257
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Figure 6
Example of target word renting in a small clause.
parse constituent are not counted and 4,086 possible values when paths are found to
the best-matching constituent in these cases. The governing-category feature, on the
other hand, which is defined only for NPs, has only two values (S, corresponding to
subjects, and VP, corresponding to objects). In cases in which the path feature includes
an S or VP ancestor of an NP node as part of the path to the target word, the gov
feature is a function of the path feature. This is the case most of the time, including for
our prototypical subject (VBVPSNP) and object (VBVPNP) paths. Of the 35,138
frame elements identified as NPs by the parser, only 4% have a path feature that does
not include a VP or S ancestor. One such example is shown in Figure 6, where the
small clause the remainder renting . . . has no S node, giving a path feature from
renting to the remainder of VBVPNPNP. The value of the gov feature here is VP, as
the algorithm finds the VP of the sentences main clause as it follows parent links up
the tree. The feature is spurious in this case, because the main VP is not headed by,
or relevant to, the target word renting.
Systems based on the path and gov features are compared in Section 4.3. The
differences between the two are relatively small for the purpose of identifying semantic
roles when frame element boundaries are known. The path feature will, however, be
important in identifying which constituents are frame elements for a given target word,
as it gives us a way of navigating through the parse tree to find the frame elements
in the sentence.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.555469">
4.1.4 Position. To overcome errors due to incorrect parses, as well as to see how
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972349688888889">
much can be done without parse trees, we introduced position as a feature. The position
feature simply indicates whether the constituent to be labeled occurs before or after the
predicate defining the semantic frame. We expected this feature to be highly correlated
with grammatical function, since subjects will generally appear before a verb and
objects after.
Although we do not have hand-checked parses against which to measure the per-
formance of the automatic parser on our corpus, the result that 13% of frame elements
have no matching parse constituent gives a rough idea of the parsers accuracy. Al-
\x0c258
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
most all of these cases in which no matching parse constituent was found are due to
parser error. Other parser errors include cases in which a constituent is found, but
with the incorrect label or internal structure. This result also considers only the indi-
vidual constituent representing the frame element: the parse for the rest of the sentence
may be incorrect, resulting in an incorrect value for the grammatical function features
described in the previous two sections. Collins (1997) reports 88% labeled precision
and recall on individual parse constituents on data from the Penn Treebank, roughly
consistent with our finding of at least 13% error.
4.1.5 Voice. The distinction between active and passive verbs plays an important role
in the connection between semantic role and grammatical function, since direct objects
of active verbs often correspond in semantic role to subjects of passive verbs. From
the parser output, verbs were classified as active or passive by building a set of 10
passive-identifying patterns. Each of the patterns requires both a passive auxiliary
(some form of to be or to get) and a past participle. Roughly 5% of the examples were
identified as passive uses.
4.1.6 Head Word. As previously noted, we expected lexical dependencies to be ex-
tremely important in labeling semantic roles, as indicated by their importance in re-
lated tasks such as parsing. Head words of noun phrases can be used to express
selectional restrictions on the semantic types of role fillers. For example, in a commu-
nication frame, noun phrases headed by Bill, brother, or he are more likely to be the
Speaker, whereas those headed by proposal, story, or question are more likely to be the
Topic. (We did not attempt to resolve pronoun references.)
Since the parser we used assigns each constituent a head word as an integral
part of the parsing model, we were able to read the head words of the constituents
from the parser output, employing the same set of rules for identifying the head child
of each constituent in the parse tree. The rules for assigning a head word are listed
in Collins (1999). Prepositions are considered to be the head words of prepositional
phrases. The rules for assigning head words do not attempt to distinguish between
cases in which the preposition expresses the semantic content of a role filler, such as
Path frame elements expressed by prepositional phrases headed by along, through, or
in, and cases in which the preposition might be considered to be purely a case marker,
as in most uses of of, where the semantic content of the role filler is expressed by
the prepositions object. Complementizers are considered to be heads, meaning that
infinitive verb phrases are always headed by to and subordinate clauses such as in the
sentence Im sure that he came are headed by that.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.997528">
4.2 Probability Estimation
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.890104375">
For our experiments, we divided the FrameNet corpus as follows: one-tenth of the
annotated sentences for each target word were reserved as a test set, and another one-
tenth were set aside as a tuning set for developing our system. A few target words
where fewer than 10 examples had been chosen for annotation were removed from the
corpus. (Section 9 will discuss generalization to unseen predicates.) In our corpus, the
average number of sentences per target word is only 34, and the number of sentences
per frame is 732, both relatively small amounts of data on which to train frame element
classifiers.
To label the semantic role of a constituent automatically, we wish to estimate a
probability distribution indicating how likely the constituent is to fill each possible
\x0c259
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 3
Distributions calculated for semantic role identification: r indicates semantic role, pt phrase
type, gov grammatical function, h head word, and t target word, or predicate.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.999629625">
P(r  |t) 100.0% 40.9% 40.9%
P(r  |pt, t) 92.5 60.1 55.6
P(r  |pt, gov, t) 92.0 66.6 61.3
P(r  |pt, position, voice) 98.8 57.1 56.4
P(r  |pt, position, voice, t) 90.8 70.1 63.7
P(r  |h) 80.3 73.6 59.1
P(r  |h, t) 56.0 86.6 48.5
P(r  |h, pt, t) 50.1 87.4 43.8
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.995560875">
role, given the features described above and the predicate, or target word, t:
P(r  |h, pt, gov, position, voice, t)
where r indicates semantic role, h head word, and pt phrase type. It would be possible
to calculate this distribution directly from the training data by counting the number
of times each role appears with a combination of features and dividing by the total
number of times the combination of features appears:
P(r  |h, pt, gov, position, voice, t) =
#(r, h, pt, gov, position, voice, t)
#(h, pt, gov, position, voice, t)
In many cases, however, we will never have seen a particular combination of features
in the training data, and in others we will have seen the combination only a small
number of times, providing a poor estimate of the probability. The small number
of training sentences for each target word and the large number of values that the
head word feature in particular can take (any word in the language) contribute to the
sparsity of the data. Although we expect our features to interact in various ways, we
cannot train directly on the full feature set. For this reason, we built our classifier by
combining probabilities from distributions conditioned on a variety of subsets of the
features.
Table 3 shows the probability distributions used in the final version of the system.
Coverage indicates the percentage of the test data for which the conditioning event had
been seen in training data. Accuracy is the proportion of covered test data for which
the correct role is given the highest probability, and Performance, which is the product
of coverage and accuracy, is the overall percentage of test data for which the correct
role is predicted.3
Accuracy is somewhat similar to the familiar metric of precision
in that it is calculated over cases for which a decision is made, and performance is
similar to recall in that it is calculated over all true frame elements. Unlike in a tra-
ditional precision/recall trade-off, however, these results have no threshold to adjust,
and the task is a multiway classification rather than a binary decision. The distribu-
tions calculated were simply the empirical distributions from the training data. That is,
occurrences of each role and each set of conditioning events were counted in a table,
and probabilities calculated by dividing the counts for each role by the total number
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.3596305">
3 Ties for the highest-probabilty role are resolved at random.
\x0c260
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Table 4
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9074185">
Sample probabilities for P(r  |pt, gov, t) calculated from training data for the verb abduct. The
variable gov is defined only for noun phrases. The roles defined for the removing frame in the
motion domain are Agent (Agt), Theme (Thm), CoTheme (CoThm) (. . . had been
abducted with him), and Manner (Manr).
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.996389">
P(r  |pt, gov, t) Count in training data
P(r = Agt  |pt = NP, gov = S, t = abduct) = .46 6
P(r = Thm  |pt = NP, gov = S, t = abduct) = .54 7
P(r = Thm  |pt = NP, gov = VP, t = abduct) = 1 9
P(r = Agt  |pt = PP, t = abduct) = .33 1
P(r = Thm  |pt = PP, t = abduct) = .33 1
P(r = CoThm  |pt = PP, t = abduct) = .33 1
P(r = Manr  |pt = ADVP, t = abduct) = 1 1
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.989679">
of observations for each conditioning event. For example, the distribution P(r  |pt, t)
was calculated as follows:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.970547666666667">
P(r  |pt, t) =
#(r, pt, t)
#(pt, t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9995343">
Some sample probabilities calculated from the training are shown in Table 4.
As can be seen from Table 3, there is a trade-off between more-specific distri-
butions, which have high accuracy but low coverage, and less-specific distributions,
which have low accuracy but high coverage. The lexical head word statistics, in par-
ticular, are valuable when data are available but are particularly sparse because of the
large number of possible head words.
To combine the strengths of the various distributions, we merged them in various
ways to obtain an estimate of the full distribution P(r  |h, pt, gov, position, voice, t). The
first combination method is linear interpolation, which simply averages the probabil-
ities given by each of the distributions:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.851372466666667">
P(r  |constituent) = 1P(r  |t) + 2P(r  |pt, t)
+ 3P(r  |pt, gov, t) + 4P(r  |pt, position, voice)
+ 5P(r  |pt, position, voice, t) + 6P(r  |h)
+ 7P(r  |h, t) + 8P(r  |h, pt, t)
where
\x01
i i = 1. The geometric mean, when expressed in the log domain, is similar:
P(r  |constituent) = 1
Z exp{ 1 log P(r  |t) + 2 log P(r  |pt, t)
+ 3 log P(r  |pt, gov, t) + 4 log P(r  |pt, position, voice)
+ 5 log P(r  |pt, position, voice, t) + 6 log P(r  |h)
+ 7 log P(r  |h, t) + 8 log P(r  |h, pt, t) }
where Z is a normalizing constant ensuring that
\x01
r P(r  |constituent) = 1.
</equation>
<tableCaption confidence="0.545948">
Results for systems based on linear interpolation are shown in the first row of
Table 5. These results were obtained using equal values of for each distribution
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.957191333333333">
defined for the relevant conditioning event (but excluding distributions for which the
conditioning event was not seen in the training data). As a more sophisticated method
of choosing interpolation weights, the expectation maximization (EM) algorithm was
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.802920823529412">
\x0c261
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 5
Results on development set, 8,167 observations.
Combining Method Correct
Equal linear interpolation 79.5%
EM linear interpolation 79.3
Geometric mean 79.6
Backoff, linear interpolation 80.4
Backoff, geometric mean 79.6
Baseline: Most common role 40.9
Table 6
Results on test set, 7,900 observations.
Combining Method Correct
EM linear interpolation 78.5%
Backoff, linear interpolation 76.9
Baseline: Most common role 40.6
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.983581433333333">
used to estimate the likelihood of the observed roles being produced by each of the
distributions in the general techniques of Jelinek and Mercer (1980). Because a number
of the distributions used may have no training data for a given set of variables, the
data were divided according to the set of distributions available, and a separate set of
interpolation weights was trained for each set of distributions. This technique (line 2
of Table 5) did not outperform equal weights even on the data used to determine
the weights. Although the EM algorithm is guaranteed to increase the likelihood of
the training data, that likelihood does not always correspond to our scoring, which is
based only on whether the correct outcome is assigned the highest probability. Results
of the EM interpolation on held-out test data are shown in Table 6.
Experimentation has shown that the weights used have relatively little impact in
our interpolation scheme, no doubt because the evaluation metric depends only on the
ranking of the probabilities and not on their exact values. Changing the interpolation
weights rarely changes the probabilities of the roles enough to change their ranking.
What matters most is whether a combination of variables has been seen in the training
data or not.
Results for the geometric mean are shown in row 3 of Table 5. As with linear
interpolation, the exact weights were found to have little effect, and the results shown
reflect equal weights. An area we have not explored is the use of the maximum-entropy
techniques of, for example, Pietra, Pietra, and Lafferty (1997), to set weights for the
log-linear model, either at the level of combining our probability distributions or at
the level of calculating weights for individual values of the features.
In the backoff combination method, a lattice was constructed over the distribu-
tions in Table 3 from more-specific conditioning events to less-specific, as shown in
Figure 7. The lattice is used to select a subset of the available distributions to com-
bine. The less-specific distributions were used only when no data were present for any
more-specific distribution. Thus, the distributions selected are arranged in a cut across
the lattice representing the most-specific distributions for which data are available. The
selected probabilities were combined with both linear interpolation and a geometric
mean, with results shown in Table 5. The final row of the table represents the baseline
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.898184625">
\x0c262
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
P(r  |h, t) P(r  |pt, t) P(r  |pt, position, voice)
P(r  |pt, position, voice, t)
P(r  |pt, gf, t)
P(r  |t)
P(r  |h)
P(r  |h, pt, t)
</equation>
<figureCaption confidence="0.959665">
Figure 7
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.963953861111111">
Lattice organization of the distributions from Table 3, with more-specific distributions toward
the top.
of always selecting the most common role of the target word for all its constituents,
that is, using only P(r  |t).
Although this lattice is reminiscent of techniques of backing off to less specific
distributions commonly used in n-gram language modeling, it differs in that we use the
lattice only to select distributions for which the conditioning event has been seen in the
training data. Discounting and deleted interpolation methods in language modeling
typically are used to assign small, nonzero probability to a predicted variable unseen in
the training data even when a specific conditioning event has been seen. In our case,
we are perfectly willing to assign zero probability to a specific role (the predicted
variable). We are interested only in finding the role with the highest probability, and
a role given a small, nonzero probability by smoothing techniques will still not be
chosen as the classifiers output.
The lattice presented in Figure 7 represents just one way of choosing subsets of
features for our system. Designing a feature lattice can be thought of as choosing
a set of feature subsets: once the probability distributions of the lattice have been
chosen, the graph structure of the lattice is determined by the subsumption relations
among the sets of conditioning variables. Given a set of N conditioning variables,
there are 2N
possible subsets, and 22N
possible sets of subsets, giving us a doubly
exponential number of possible lattices. The particular lattice of Figure 7 was chosen to
represent some expected interaction between features. For example, we expect position
and voice to interact, and they are always used together. We expect the head word h
and the phrase type pt to be relatively independent predictors of the semantic role
and therefore include them separately as roots of the backoff structure. Although we
will not explore all the possibilities for our lattice, some of the feature interactions are
examined more closely in Section 4.3.
The final system performed at 80.4% accuracy, which can be compared to the 40.9%
achieved by always choosing the most probable role for each target word, essentially
chance performance on this task. Results for this system on test data, held out during
development of the system, are shown in Table 6. Surprisingly, the EM-based interpo-
lation performed better than the lattice-based system on the held-out test set, but not
on the data used to set the weights in the EM-based system. We return to an analysis
of which roles are hardest to classify in Section 9.1.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999306">
4.3 Interaction of Features
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99524975">
Three of our features, position, gov, and path, attempt to capture the syntactic relation
between the target word and the constituent to be labeled, and in particular to dif-
ferentiate the subjects from objects of verbs. To compare these three features directly,
experiments were performed using each feature alone in an otherwise identical sys-
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.923712909090909">
\x0c263
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 7
Different estimators of grammatical function. The columns of the table correspond to
Figures 8a, 8b, and 8c.
Feature W/o voice Independent In conjunction
voice feature with voice
path 79.4% 79.2% 80.4%
gov 79.1 79.2 80.7
position 79.9 79.7 80.5
76.3 76.0 76.0
</table>
<equation confidence="0.9897655">
P(r  |h, t) P(r  |pt, t)
P(r  |t)
P(r  |h)
P(r  |h, pt, t)
P(r  |pt, GF, voice, t)
P(r  |pt, GF, voice)
P(r  |h, t) P(r  |pt, t)
P(r  |t)
P(r  |h)
P(r  |h, pt, t)
P(r  |pt, voice, t)
P(r  |pt, voice)
P(r  |pt, GF, t)
P(r  |h, t) P(r  |pt, t)
P(r  |t)
P(r  |h)
P(r  |h, pt, t)
P(r  |pt, GF, t)
a)
b)
c)
Figure 8
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.996882">
Lattice structures for comparing grammatical-function features.
tem. Results are shown in Table 7. For the first set of experiments, corresponding to
the first column of Table 7, no voice information was used, with the result that the
remaining distributions formed the lattice of Figure 8a. (GF (grammatical function)
in the figure represents one of the features position, gov, and path.) Adding voice infor-
mation back into the system independently of the grammatical-function feature results
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.828955666666667">
\x0c264
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
P(r  |h, t)
P(r  |t)
P(r  |pt, path, t)
Figure 9
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.985864512195122">
Minimal lattice.
in the lattice of Figure 8b, corresponding to the second column of Table 7. Choosing
distributions such that the grammatical function and voice features are always used
together results in Figure 8c, corresponding to the third column of Table 7. In each
case, as in previous results, the grammatical function feature was used only when
the candidate constituent was an NP. The last row of Table 7 shows results using no
grammatical-function feature: the distributions making use of GF are removed from
the lattices of Figure 8.
As a guideline for interpreting these results, with 8,167 observations, the threshold
for statistical significance with p &amp;lt; .05 is a 1.0% absolute difference in performance.
It is interesting to note that looking at a constituents position relative to the target
word performed as well as either of our features that read grammatical function off
the parse tree, both with and without passive information. The gov and path features
seem roughly equivalent in performance.
Using head word, phrase type, and target word without either position or gram-
matical function yielded only 76.3% accuracy, indicating that although the two features
accomplish a similar goal, it is important to include some measure of the constituents
relationship to the target word, whether relative position or either of the syntactic
features.
Use of the active/passive voice feature seems to be beneficial only when the feature
is tied to grammatical function: the second column in Table 7 shows no improvement
over the first, while the right-hand column, where grammatical function and voice are
tied, shows gains (although only trends) of at least 0.5% in all cases. As before, our
three indicators of grammatical function seem roughly equivalent, with the best result
in this case being the gov feature. The lattice of Figure 8c performs as well as our
system of Figure 7, indicating that including both position and either of the syntactic
relations is redundant.
As an experiment to see how much can be accomplished with as simple a system
as possible, we constructed the minimal lattice of Figure 9, which includes just two
distributions, along with a prior for the target word to be used as a last resort when no
data are available. This structure assumes that head word and grammatical function
are independent. It further makes no use of the voice feature. We chose the path feature
as the representation of grammatical function in this case. This system classified 76.3%
of frame elements correctly, indicating that one can obtain roughly nine-tenths the
performance of the full system with a simple approach. (We will return to a similar
system for the purposes of cross-domain experiments in Section 9.)
5. Identification of Frame Element Boundaries
In this section we examine the systems performance on the task of locating the frame
elements in a sentence. Although our probability model considers the question of
finding the boundaries of frame elements separately from the question of finding the
correct label for a particular frame element, similar features are used to calculate both
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.4435392">
\x0c265
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 8
Sample probabilities of a constituents being a frame element.
Distribution Sample Probability Count in training data
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.964385125">
P(fe  |path) P(fe  |path = VBVPADJPADVP) = 1 1
P(fe  |path = VBVPNP) = .73 3,963
P(fe  |path = VBVPNPPPS) = 0 22
P(fe  |path, t) P(fe  |path = JJADJPPP, t = apparent) = 1 10
P(fe  |path = NNNPPPVPPP, t = departure) = .4 5
P(fe  |h, t) P(fe  |h = sudden, t = apparent) = 0 2
P(fe  |h = to, t = apparent) = .11 93
P(fe  |h = that, t = apparent) = .21 81
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.98538175">
probabilities. In the experiments below, the system is no longer given frame element
boundaries but is still given as inputs the human-annotated target word and the frame
to which it belongs. We do not address the task of identifying which frames come into
play in a sentence but envision that existing word sense disambiguation techniques
could be applied to the task.
As before, features are extracted from the sentence and its parse and are used to
calculate probability tables, with the predicted variable in this case being fe, a binary
indicator of whether a given constituent in the parse tree is or is not a frame element.
The features used were the path feature of Section 4.1.3, the identity of the target
word, and the identity of the constituents head word. The probability distributions
calculated from the training data were P(fe  |path), P(fe  |path, t), and P(fe  |h, t), where
fe indicates an event where the parse constituent in question is a frame element, path
the path through the parse tree from the target word to the parse constituent, t the
identity of the target word, and h the head word of the parse constituent. Some sample
values from these distributions are shown in Table 8. For example, the path VBVPNP,
which corresponds to the direct object of a verbal target word, had a high probability
of being a frame element. The table also illustrates cases of sparse data for various
feature combinations.
By varying the probability threshold at which a decision is made, one can plot a
precision/recall curve as shown in Figure 10. P(fe  |path, t) performs relatively poorly
because of fragmentation of the training data (recall that only about 30 sentences are
available for each target word). Although the lexical statistic P(fe  |h, t) alone is not
useful as a classifier, using it in linear interpolation with the path statistics improves
results. The curve labeled interpolation in Figure 10 reflects a linear interpolation of
the form
P(fe  |p, h, t) = 1P(fe  |p) + 2P(fe  |p, t) + 3P(fe  |h, t) (16)
Note that this method can identify only those frame elements that have a correspond-
ing constituent in the automatically generated parse tree. For this reason, it is in-
teresting to calculate how many true frame elements overlap with the results of the
system, relaxing the criterion that the boundaries must match exactly. Results for par-
tial matching are shown in Table 9. Three types of overlap are possible: the identified
constituent entirely within the true frame element, the true frame element entirely
within the identified constituent, and each sequence partially contained by the other.
An example of the first case is shown in Figure 11, where the true Message frame ele-
ment is Mandarin by a head, but because of an error in the parser output, no constituent
exactly matches the frame elements boundaries. In this case, the system identifies
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.77583012">
\x0c266
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
0
0.1
0.2
0.3
0.4
0.5
0.6
0.7
0.8
0.9
1
0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1
recall
precision
P(fe|path)
P(fe|path, t)
interpolation
Figure 10
Plot of precision/recall curve for various methods of identifying frame elements. Recall is
calculated over only frame elements with matching parse constituents.
Table 9
Results on identifying frame elements (FEs), including partial matches. Results obtained using
P(fe  |path) with threshold at 0.5. A total of 7,681 constituents were identified as FEs, and 8,167
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.882634875">
FEs were present in hand-annotations, of which matching parse constituents were present for
7,053 (86%).
Type of Overlap Identified Constituents Number
Exactly matching boundaries 66% 5,421
Identified constituent entirely within true frame element 8 663
True frame element entirely within identified constituent 7 599
Both partially within the other 0 26
No overlap with any true frame element 13 972
two frame elements, indicated by shading, which together span the true frame ele-
ment.
When the automatically identified constituents were fed through the role-labeling
system described above, 79.6% of the constituents that had been correctly identified
in the first stage were assigned the correct role in the second, roughly equivalent
to the performance when roles were assigned to constituents identified by hand. A
more sophisticated integrated system for identifying and labeling frame elements is
described in Section 7.1.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.899014806451613">
6. Generalizing Lexical Statistics
As can be seen from Table 3, information about the head word of a constituent
is valuable in predicting the constituents role. Of all the distributions presented,
\x0c267
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
As the horses were led back... ,
SBAR
the
DT
result
NN
NP
was
VBD
announced :
VBN
Mandarin
NN
NP
by
IN
a
DT
head
NN
NP
PP
VP
VP
S
target Message
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.896972">
Figure 11
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.992266941176471">
An example of overlap between identified frame elements and the true boundaries, caused by
parser error. In this case two frame elements identified by the classifier (shaded subtrees) are
entirely within the human annotation (indicated below the sentence), contributing two
instances to row 2 of Table 9.
P(r  |h, pt, t) predicts the correct role most often (87.4% of the time) when training
data for a particular head word have been seen. Because of the large vocabulary of
possible head words, however, it also has the smallest coverage, meaning that it is
likely that, for a given case in the test data, no frame element with the same head
word will have been seen in the set of training sentences for the target word in ques-
tion. To capitalize on the information provided by the head word, we wish to find
a way to generalize from head words seen in the training data to other head words.
In this section we compare three different approaches to the task of generalizing over
head words: automatic clustering of a large vocabulary of head words to identify
words with similar semantics; use of a hand-built ontological resource, WordNet, to
organize head words in a semantic hierarchy; and bootstrapping to make use of un-
labeled data in training the system. We will focus on frame elements filled by noun
phrases, which constitute roughly half the total.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998962">
6.1 Automatic Clustering
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997113333333333">
To find groups of head words that are likely to fill the same semantic roles, an auto-
matic clustering of nouns was performed using word co-occurrence data from a large
corpus. This technique is based on the expectation that words with similar semantics
will tend to co-occur with the same other sets of words. For example, nouns describing
foods will tend to occur as direct objects of verbs such as eat devour, and savor. The
clustering algorithm attempts to find such patterns of co-occurrence from the counts
of grammatical relations between pairs of specific words in the corpus, without the
use of any external knowledge or semantic representation.
We extracted verbdirect object relations from an automatically parsed version of
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6720134">
the British National Corpus, using the parser of Carroll and Rooth (1998).4
Clustering
4 We are indebted to Mats Rooth and Sabine Schulte im Walde for providing us with the parsed corpus.
\x0c268
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.983791833333333">
was performed using the probabilistic model of co-occurrence described in detail by
Hofmann and Puzicha (1998). (For other natural language processing [NLP] applica-
tions of the probabilistic clustering algorithm, see, e.g., Rooth [1995], Rooth et al. [1999];
for application to language modeling, see Gildea and Hofmann [1999]. According to
this model, the two observed variables, in this case the verb and the head noun of its
object, can be considered independent given the value of a hidden cluster variable, c:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.99927775">
P(n, v) =
\x02
c
P(c)P(n  |c)P(v  |c)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999556238095238">
One begins by setting a priori the number of values that c can take and using the
EM algorithm to estimate the distributions P(c), P(n  |c), and P(v  |c). Deterministic
annealing was used to prevent overfitting of the training data.
We are interested only in the clusters of nouns given by the distribution P(n  |c):
the verbs and the distribution P(v  |c) are thrown away once training is complete. Other
grammatical relations besides direct object could be used, as could a set of relations.
We used the direct object (following other clustering work such as Pereira, Tishby, and
Lee [1993]) because it is particularly likely to exhibit semantically significant selectional
restrictions.
A total of 2,610,946 verb-object pairs were used as training data for the clustering,
with a further 290,105 pairs used as a cross-validation set to control the parameters of
the clustering algorithm. Direct objects were identified as noun phrases directly under
a verb phrase nodenot a perfect technique, since it also finds nominal adjuncts such
as I start today. Forms of the verb to be were excluded from the data, as its co-
occurrence patterns are not semantically informative. The number of values possible
for the latent cluster variable was set to 256. (Comparable results were found with 64
clusters; the use of deterministic annealing prevents large numbers of clusters from
resulting in overfitting.)
The soft clustering of nouns thus generated is used as follows: for each example
in the frame elementannotated training data, probabilities for values of the hidden
cluster variable were calculated using Bayes rule:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.99982125">
P(c  |h) =
P(h  |c)P(c)
\x01
c\x01 P(h  |c\x01)P(c\x01)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991685">
The clustering was applied only to noun phrase constituents; the distribution P(n  |c)
from the clustering is used as a distribution P(h  |c) over noun head words.
Using the cluster probabilities, a new estimate of P(r  |c, pt, t) is calculated for
cases where pt, the phrase type or syntactic category of the constituent, is NP:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.9996192">
P(r  |c, pt, t) =
\x01
j:ptj = pt,tj = t,rj = r P(cj  |hj)
\x01
j:ptj = pt,tj = t P(cj  |hj)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.994933">
where j is an index ranging over the frame elements in the training set and their
associated features pt, t, h and their semantic roles r.
During testing, a smoothed estimate of the head wordbased role probability is
calculated by marginalizing over cluster values:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.979476222222222">
P(r  |h, pt, t) =
\x02
c
P(r  |c, pt, t)P(c  |h)
again using P(c  |h) = P(h|c)P(c)
\x01
c\x01 P(h|c\x01)P(c\x01)
.
\x0c269
</equation>
<tableCaption confidence="0.7612495">
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 10
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.758711625">
Clustering results on NP constituents only, 4,086 instances.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
P(r  |h, pt, t) 41.6% 87.0% 36.1%
\x01
c
P(r  |c, pt, t)P(c  |h) 97.9 79.7 78.0
Interpolation of unclustered distributions 100.0 83.4 83.4
Unclustered distributions + clustering 100.0 85.0 85.0
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.993713210526316">
As with the other methods of generalization described in this section, automatic
clustering was applied only to noun phrases, which represent 50% of the constituents
in the test data. We would not expect head word to be as valuable for other phrase
types. The second most common category is prepositional phrases. The head of a
prepositional phrase (PP) is considered to be the preposition, according to the rules
we use, and because the set of prepositions is small, coverage is not as great a problem.
Furthermore, the preposition is often a direct indicator of the semantic role. (A more
complete model might distinguish between cases in which the preposition serves as a
case or role marker and others in which it is semantically informative, with clustering
performed on the prepositions object in the former case. We did not attempt to make
this distinction.) Phrase types other than NP and PP make up only a small proportion
of the data.
Table 10 shows results for the use of automatic clustering on constituents identified
by the parser as noun phrases. As can be seen in the table, the vocabulary used for
clustering includes almost all (97.9%) of the test data, and the decrease in accuracy from
direct lexical statistics to clustered statistics is relatively small (from 87.0% to 79.7%).
When combined with the full system described above, clustered statistics increase
performance on NP constituents from 83.4% to 85.0% (statistically significant at p &amp;lt;
.05). Over the entire test set, this translates into an improvement from 80.4% to 81.2%.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998711">
6.2 Using a Semantic Hierarchy: WordNet
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997224">
The automatic clustering described above can be seen as an imperfect method of
deriving semantic classes from the vocabulary, and we might expect a hand-developed
set of classes to do better. We tested this hypothesis using WordNet (Fellbaum 1998), a
freely available semantic hierarchy. The basic technique, when presented with a head
word for which no training examples had been seen, was to ascend the type hierarchy
until reaching a level for which training data are available. To do this, counts of
training data were percolated up the semantic hierarchy in a technique similar to that
of, for example, McCarthy (2000). For each training example, the count #(r, s, pt, t)
was incremented in a table indexed by the semantic role r, WordNet sense s, phrase
type pt, and target word t, for each WordNet sense s above the head word h in the
hypernym hierarchy. In fact, the WordNet hierarchy is not a tree, but rather includes
multiple inheritance. For example, person has as hypernyms both life form and causal
agent. In such cases, we simply took the first hypernym listed, effectively converting
the structure into a tree. A further complication is that several WordNet senses are
possible for a given head word. We simply used the first sense listed for each word; a
word sense disambiguation module capable of distinguishing WordNet senses might
improve our results.
As with the clustering experiments reported above, the WordNet hierarchy was
used only for noun phrases. The WordNet hierarchy does not include pronouns; to
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.658813111111111">
\x0c270
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Table 11
WordNet results on NP constituents only, 4,086 instances.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
P(r  |h, pt, t) 41.6% 87.0% 36.1%
WordNet: P(r  |s, pt, t) 80.8 79.5 64.1
Interpolation of unclustered distributions 100.0 83.4 83.4
Unclustered distributions + WordNet 100.0 84.3 84.3
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998642">
increase coverage, the personal pronouns I, me, you, he, she, him, her, we, and us were
added as hyponyms of person. Pronouns that refer to inanimate, or both animate and
inanimate, objects were not included. In addition, the CELEX English lexical database
(Baayen, Piepenbrock, and Gulikers 1995) was used to convert plural nouns to their
singular forms.
As shown in Table 11, accuracy for the WordNet technique is roughly the same as
that in the automatic clustering results in Table 10: 84.3% on NPs, as opposed to 85.0%
with automatic clustering. This indicates that the error introduced by the unsupervised
clustering is roughly equivalent to the error caused by our arbitrary choice of the
first WordNet sense for each word and the first hypernym for each WordNet sense.
Coverage for the WordNet technique is lower, however, largely because of the absence
of proper nouns from WordNet, as well as the absence of nonanimate pronouns (both
personal pronouns such as it and they and indefinite pronouns such as something and
anyone). A dictionary of proper nouns would likely help improve coverage, and a
module for anaphora resolution might help cases with pronouns, with or without
the use of WordNet. The conversion of plural forms to singular base forms was an
important part of the success of the WordNet system, increasing coverage from 71.0%
to 80.8%. Of the remaining 19.2% of all noun phrases not covered by the combination of
lexical and WordNet sense statistics, 22% consisted of head words defined in WordNet,
but for which no training data were available for any hypernym, and 78% consisted
of head words not defined in WordNet.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.99474">
6.3 Bootstrapping from Unannotated Data
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9958994375">
A third way of attempting to improve coverage of the lexical statistics is to bootstrap,
or label unannotated data with the automatic system described in Sections 4 and
5 and use the (imperfect) result as further training data. This can be considered a
variant of the EM algorithm, although we use the single most likely hypothesis for
the unannotated data, rather than calculating the expectation over all hypotheses. Only
one iteration of training on the unannotated data was performed.
The unannotated data used consisted of 156,590 sentences containing the target
words of our corpus, increasing the total amount of data available to roughly six times
the 36,995 annotated training sentences.
Table 12 shows results on noun phrases for the bootstrapping method. The accu-
racy of a system trained only on data from the automatic labeling (Pauto) is 81.0%, rea-
sonably close to the 87.0% for the system trained only on annotated data (Ptrain ). Com-
bining the annotated and automatically labeled data increases coverage from 41.6%
to 54.7% and performance to 44.5%. Because the automatically labeled data are not
as accurate as the annotated data, we can do slightly better by using the automatic
data only in cases where no training data are available, backing off to the distribution
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.75859">
Pauto from Ptrain . The fourth row of Table 12 shows results with Pauto incorporated
\x0c271
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 12
Bootstrapping results on NP constituents only, 4,086 instances.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
Ptrain(r  |h, pt, t) 41.6% 87.0% 36.1%
Pauto(r  |h, pt, t) 48.2 81.0 39.0
Ptrain+auto(r  |h, pt, t) 54.7 81.4 44.5
Ptrain, backoff to Pauto 54.7 81.7 44.7
Interpolation of unclustered distributions 100.0 83.4 83.4
Unclustered distributions + Pauto 100.0 83.2 83.2
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.995802">
into the backoff lattice of all the features of Figure 7, which actually resulted in a slight
decrease in performance from the system without the bootstrapped data, shown in the
third row. This is presumably because, although the system trained on automatically
labeled data performed with reasonable accuracy, many of the cases it classifies cor-
rectly overlap with the training data. In fact our backing-off estimate of P(r  |h, pt, t)
classifies correctly only 66% of the additional cases that it covers over Ptrain (r  |h, pt, t).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.992921">
6.4 Discussion
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992835666666667">
The three methods of generalizing lexical statistics each had roughly equivalent accu-
racy on cases for which they were able to derive an estimate of the role probabilities
for unseen head words. The differences between the three were primarily due to how
much they could improve the coverage of the estimator, that is, how many new noun
heads they were able to handle. The automatic-clustering method performed by far
the best on this metric; only 2.1% of test cases were unseen in the data used for the
automatic clustering. This indicates how much can be achieved with unsupervised
methods given very large training corpora. The bootstrapping technique described
here, although it has a similar unsupervised flavor, made use of much less data than
the corpus used for noun clustering. Unlike probabilistic clustering, the bootstrapping
technique can make use of only those sentences containing the target words in ques-
tion. The WordNet experiment, on the other hand, indicates both the usefulness of
hand-built resources when they apply and the difficulty of attaining broad coverage
with such resources. Combining the three systems described would indicate whether
their gains are complementary or overlapping.
7. Verb Argument Structure
One of the primary difficulties in labeling semantic roles is that one predicate may
be used with different argument structures: for example, in the sentences He opened
the door and The door opened, the verb open assigns different semantic roles to
its syntactic subject. In this section we compare two strategies for handling this type
of alternation in our system: a sentence-level feature for frame element groups and a
subcategorization feature for the syntactic uses of verbs. Then a simple system using
the predicates argument structure, or syntactic signature, as the primary feature will
be contrasted with previous systems based on local, independent features.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.977926">
7.1 Priors on Frame Element Groups
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970664333333333">
The system described in previous sections for classifying frame elements makes an
important simplifying assumption: it classifies each frame element independent of the
decisions made for the other frame elements in the sentence. In this section we remove
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.319268333333333">
\x0c272
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Table 13
Sample frame element groups for the verb blame.
Frame Element Group Example Sentences
{Evaluee} Holman would characterize this
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.895690545454546">
as blaming [Evaluee the poor ] .
{Judge, Evaluee, Reason} The letter quotes Black as
saying that [Judge white and Navajo ranchers ]
misrepresent their livestock losses and
blame [Reason everything ] [Evaluee on coyotes ] .
[Judge She ] blames [Evaluee the Government ]
[Reason for failing to do enough to help ] .
{Judge, Evaluee} The only dish she made that we could tolerate was
[Evaluee syrup tart which ] [Judge we ]
praised extravagantly with the result that it became
our unhealthy staple diet.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.803574">
Table 14
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.996874444444444">
Frame element groups for the verb blame in the Judgment frame.
Frame Element Group Probability
{Evaluee, Judge, Reason} 0.549
{Evaluee, Judge} 0.160
{Evaluee, Reason} 0.167
{Evaluee} 0.097
{Evaluee, Judge, Role } 0.014
{Judge} 0.007
{Judge, Reason} 0.007
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.987751117647059">
this assumption and present a system that can make use of the information that, for
example, a given target word requires that one role always be present or that having
two instances of the same role is extremely unlikely.
To capture this information, we introduce the notion of a frame element group,
which is the set of frame element roles present in a particular sentence (technically a
multiset, as duplicates are possible, though quite rare). Frame element groups (FEGs)
are unordered: examples are shown in Table 13. Sample probabilities from the training
data for the frame element groups of the target word blame are shown in Table 14.
The FrameNet corpus recognizes three types of null-instantiated frame elements
(Fillmore 1986), which are implied but do not appear in the sentence. An example of
null instantiation is the sentence Have you eaten? where food is understood. We
did not attempt to identify such null elements, and any null-instantiated roles are not
included in the sentences FEG. This increases the variability of observed FEGs, as a
predicate may require a certain role but allow it to be null instantiated.
Our system for choosing the most likely overall assignment of roles for all the
frame elements of a sentence uses an approximation that we derive beginning with
the true probability of the optimal role assignment r
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.94112825">
:
r
= argmaxr1...n
P(r1...n  |t, f1...n)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.925674666666667">
where P(r1...n  |t, f1...n) represents the probability of an overall assignment of roles ri
to each of the n constituents of a sentence, given the target word t and the various
features fi of each of the constituents. In the first step we apply Bayes rule to this
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.95049825">
\x0c273
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
quantity,
r
= argmaxr1...n
P(r1...n  |t)
P(f1...n  |r1...n, t)
P(f1...n  |t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.998965666666667">
and in the second we make the assumption that the features of the various constituents
of a sentence are independent given the target word and each constituents role and
discard the term P(f1...n  |t), which is constant with respect to r:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.997612166666667">
r
= argmaxr1...n
P(r1...n  |t)
\x03
i
P(fi  |ri, t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.966488">
We estimate the prior over frame element assignments as the probability of the frame
element groups, represented with the set operator {}:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.997523666666667">
r
= argmaxr1...n
P({r1...n}  |t)
\x03
i
P(fi  |ri, t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.84376">
We then apply Bayes rule again,
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.998263714285714">
r
= argmaxr1...n
P({r1...n}  |t)
\x03
i
P(ri  |fi, t)P(fi  |t)
P(ri  |t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9744405">
and finally discard the feature prior P(fi  |t) as being constant over the argmax expres-
sion:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.997972142857143">
r
= argmaxr1...n
P({r1...n}  |t)
\x03
i
P(ri  |fi, t)
P(ri  |t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999087285714286">
This leaves us with an expression in terms of the prior for frame element groups of
a particular target word P({r1...n}  |t), the local probability of a frame element given
a constituents features P(ri  |fi, t) on which our previous system was based, and the
individual priors for the frame elements chosen P(ri  |t). This formulation can be used
to assign roles either when the frame element boundaries are known or when they
are not, as we will discuss later in this section.
Calculating empirical FEG priors from the training data is relatively straightfor-
ward, but the sparseness of the data presents a problem. In fact, 15% of the test
sentences had an FEG not seen in the training data for the target word in question.
Using the empirical value for the FEG prior, these sentences could never be correctly
classified. For this reason, we introduce a smoothed estimate of the FEG prior con-
sisting of a linear interpolation of the empirical FEG prior and the product, for each
possible frame element, of the probability of being present or not present in a sentence
given the target word:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.999869111111111">
P({r1...n}  |t) + (1 )
\x03
rr1...n
P(r FEG  |t)
\x03
r/
r1...n
P(r /
FEG  |t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.995499">
The value of was empirically set to maximize performance on the development set;
a value of 0.6 yielded performance of 81.6%, a significant improvement over the 80.4%
of the baseline system. Results were relatively insensitive to the exact value of .
Up to this point, we have considered separately the problems of labeling roles
given that we know where the boundaries of the frame elements lie (Section 4, as
well as Section 6) and finding the constituents to label in the sentence (Section 5).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.537062625">
\x0c274
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Table 15
Combined results on boundary identification and role labeling.
Unlabeled Labeled
Method Precision Recall Precision Recall
Boundary id. + baseline role labeler 72.6 63.1 67.0 46.8
Boundary id. + labeler w/FEG priors 72.6 63.1 65.9 46.2
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.996144304347826">
Integrated boundary id. and labeling 74.0 70.1 64.6 61.2
We now turn to combining the two systems described above into a complete role
labeling system. We use equation (16), repeated below, to estimate the probability that
a constituent is a frame element:
P(fe  |p, h, t) = 1P(fe  |p) + 2P(fe  |p, t) + 3P(fe  |h, t)
where p is the path through the parse tree from the target word to the constituent, t
is the target word, and h is the constituents head word.
The first two rows of Table 15 show the results when constituents are determined
to be frame elements by setting the threshold on the probability P(fe  |p, h, t) to 0.5 and
then running the labeling system of Section 4 on the resulting set of constituents. The
first two columns of results show precision and recall for the task of identifying frame
element boundaries correctly. The second pair of columns gives precision and recall
for the combined task of boundary identification and role labeling; to be counted as
correct, the frame element must both have the correct boundary and be labeled with
the correct role.
Contrary to our results using human-annotated boundaries, incorporating FEG
priors into the system based on automatically identified boundaries had a negative
effect on labeled precision and recall. No doubt this is due to introducing a dependency
on other frame element decisions that may be incorrect: the use of FEG priors causes
errors in boundary identification to be compounded.
One way around this problem is to integrate boundary identification with role
labeling, allowing the FEG priors and the role-labeling decisions to affect which con-
stituents are frame elements. This was accomplished by extending the formulation
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.932756230769231">
argmaxr1...n
P({r1...n}  |t)
\x03
i
P(ri  |fi, t)
P(ri  |t)
to include frame element identification decisions:
argmaxr1...n
P({r1...n}  |t)
\x03
i
P(ri  |fi, fei, t)P(fei  |fi)
P(ri  |t)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.919345625">
where fei is a binary variable indicating that a constituent is a frame element and
P(fei  |fi) is calculated as above. When fei is true, role probabilities are calculated as
before; when fei is false, ri assumes an empty role with probability one and is not
included in the FEG represented by {r1...n}.
One caveat in using this integrated approach is its exponential complexity: each
combination of role assignments to constituents is considered, and the number of
combinations is exponential in the number of constituents. Although this did not pose
a problem when only the annotated frame elements were under consideration, now we
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9945373">
\x0c275
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
S
NP VP
NP
He
PRP
VB
DT NN
door
the
opened
S
VP
NP
VB
DT NN
door
opened
The
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.783876">
Figure 12
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.997387409090909">
Two subcategorizations for the target word open. The relevant production in the parse tree is
highlighted. On the left, the value of the feature is VP VB NP; on the right it is VP
VB.
must include every parse constituent with a nonzero probability for P(fei  |fi). To make
the computation tractable, we implement a pruning scheme: hypotheses are extended
by choosing assignments for one constituent at a time, and only the top m hypotheses
are retained for extension by assignments to the next constituent. Here we set m = 10
after experimentation showed that increasing m yielded no significant improvement.
Results for the integrated approach are shown in the last row of Table 15. Allowing
role assignments to influence boundary identification improves results both on the
unlabeled boundary identification task and on the combined identification and labeling
task. The integrated approach puts us in a different portion of the precision/recall
curve from the results in the first two rows, as it returns a higher number of frame
elements (7,736 vs. 5,719). A more direct comparison can be made by lowering the
probability threshold for frame element identification from 0.5 to 0.35 to force the
nonintegrated system to return the same number of frame elements as the integrated
system. This yields a frame element identification precision of 71.3% and recall of
67.6% and a labeled precision of 60.8% and recall of 57.6%, which is dominated by
the result for the integrated system. The integrated system does not have a probability
threshold to set; nonetheless it comes closer to identifying the correct number of frame
elements (8,167) than does the independent boundary identifier when the theoretically
optimal threshold of 0.5 is used with the latter.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998628">
7.2 Subcategorization
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977012129032258">
Recall that use of the FEG prior was motivated by the tendency of verbs to assign dif-
fering roles to the same syntactic position. For example, the verb open assigns different
roles to the syntactic subject in He opened the door and The door opened. In this section
we consider a different feature motivated by these problems: the syntactic subcate-
gorization of the verb. For example, the verb open seems to be more likely to assign
the role Patient to its subject in an intransitive context and Agent to its subject in a
transitive context. Our use of a subcategorization feature was intended to differentiate
between transitive and intransitive uses of a verb.
The feature used was the identity of the phrase structure rule expanding the target
words parent node in the parse tree, as shown in Figure 12. For example, for He closed
the door, with close as the target word, the subcategorization feature would be VP
VB NP. The subcategorization feature was used only when the target word was a
\x0c276
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
verb. The various part-of-speech tags for verb forms (VBD for past-tense verb forms,
VBZ for third-person singular present tense, VBP for other present tense, VBG for
present participles, and VBN for past participles) were collapsed into a single tag VB.
It is important to note that we are not able to distinguish complements from adjuncts,
and our subcategorization feature could be sabotaged by cases such as The door closed
yesterday. In the Penn Treebank style, yesterday is considered an NP with tree structure
equivalent to that of a direct object. Our subcategorization feature is fairly specific: for
example, the addition of an ADVP to a verb phrase will result in a different value. We
tested variations of the feature that counted the number of NPs in a VP or the total
number of children of the VP, with no significant change in results.
The subcategorization feature was used in conjunction with the path feature, which
represents the sequence of nonterminals along the path through the parse tree from
the target word to the constituent representing a frame element. Making use of the
new subcategorization (subcat) feature by adding the distribution P(r  |subcat, path, t)
to the lattice of distributions in the baseline system resulted in a slight improvement
to 80.8% performance from 80.4%. As with the gov feature in the baseline system, it
was found beneficial to use the subcat feature only for NP constituents.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.995138">
7.3 Discussion
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989545522727273">
Combining the FEG priors and subcategorization feature into a single system resulted
in performance of 81.6%, no improvement over using FEG priors without subcatego-
rization. We suspect that the two seemingly different approaches in fact provide similar
information. For example, in our hypothetical example of the sentence He opened the
door vs. the sentence The door opened, the verb open would have high priors for the FEGs
{Agent, Theme} and {Theme}, but a low prior for {Agent}. In sentences with only
one candidate frame element (the subject in The door closed), the use of the FEG prior
will cause it to be labeled Theme, even when the feature probabilities prefer labeling a
subject as Agent. Thus the FEG prior, by representing the set of arguments the predi-
cate is likely to take, essentially already performs the function of the subcategorization
feature.
The FEG prior allows us to introduce a dependency between the classifications
of the sentences various constituents with a single parameter. Thus, it can handle
the alternation of our example without, for example, introducing the role chosen for
one constituent as an additional feature in the probability distribution for the next
constituents role. It appears that because introducing additional features can further
fragment our already sparse data, it is preferable to have a single parameter for the
FEG prior.
An interesting result reinforcing this conclusion is that some of the argument-
structure features that aided the system when individual frame elements were consid-
ered independently are unnecessary when using FEG priors. Removing the features
passive and position from the system and using a smaller lattice of only the distribu-
tions not employing these features yields an improved performance of 82.8% on the
role-labeling task using hand-annotated boundaries. We believe that, because these
features pertain to syntactic alternations in how arguments are realized, they overlap
with the function of the FEG prior. Adding unnecessary features to the system can
reduce performance by fragmenting the training data.
8. Integrating Syntactic and Semantic Parsing
In the experiments reported in previous sections, we have used the parse tree returned
by a statistical parser as input to the role-labeling system. In this section, we explore
\x0c277
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
the interaction between semantic roles and syntactic parsing by integrating the parser
with the semantic-role probability model. This allows the semantic-role assignment
to affect the syntactic attachment decisions made by the parser, with the hope of
improving the accuracy of the complete system.
Although most statistical parsing work measures performance in terms of syntac-
tic trees without semantic information, an assignment of role fillers has been incor-
porated into a statistical parsing model by Miller et al. (2000) for the domain-specific
templates of the Message Understanding Conference (Defense Advanced Research
Projects Agency 1998) task. A key finding of Miller et al.s work was that a system
developed by annotating role fillers in text and training a statistical system performed
at the same level as one based on writing a large system of rules, which requires much
more highly skilled labor to design.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.674222">
8.1 Incorporating Roles into the Parsing Model
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998928085714285">
We use as the baseline of all our parsing experiments the model described in Collins
(1999). The algorithm is a form of chart parsing, which uses dynamic programming to
search through the exponential number of possible parses by considering subtrees for
each subsequence of the sentence independently. To apply chart parsing to a proba-
bilistic grammar, independence relations must be assumed to hold between the prob-
abilities of a parse tree and the internal structure of its subtrees.
In the case of stochastic context-free grammar, the probability of a tree is inde-
pendent of the internal structure of its subtrees, given the topmost nonterminal of
the subtree. The chart-parsing algorithm can simply find the highest-probability parse
for each nonterminal for each substring of the input sentence. No lower-probability
subtrees will ever be used in a complete parse, and they can be thrown away. Recent
lexicalized stochastic parsers such as Collins (1999), Charniak (1997), and others add
additional features to each constituent, the most important being the head word of
the parse constituent.
The statistical system for assigning semantic roles described in the previous sec-
tions does not fit easily into the chart-parsing framework, as it relies on long-distance
dependencies between the target word and its frame elements. In particular, the path
feature, which is used to navigate through the sentence from the target word to its
likely frame elements, may be an arbitrarily long sequence of syntactic constituents.
A path feature looking for frame elements for a target word in another part of the
sentence may examine the internal structure of a constituent, violating the indepen-
dence assumptions of the chart parser. The use of priors over FEGs further complicates
matters by introducing sentence-level features dependent on the entire parse.
For these reasons, we use the syntactic parsing model without frame element
probabilities to generate a number of candidate parses, compute the best frame element
assignment for each, and then choose the analysis with the highest overall probability.
The frame element assignments are computed as in Section 7.1, with frame element
probabilities being applied to every constituent in the parse.
To return a large number of candidate parses, the parser was modified to include
constituents in the chart even when they were equivalent, according to the parsing
model, to a higher-probability constituent. Rather than choosing a fixed n and keeping
the n best constituents for each entry in the chart, we chose a probability threshold
and kept all constituents within a margin of the highest-probability constituent. Thus
the mechanism is similar to the beam search used to prune nonequivalent edges, but
a lower threshold was used for equivalent edges (1
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.5895905">
e vs. 1
100 ).
Using these pruning parameters, an average of 14.9 parses per sentence were
obtained. After rescoring with frame element probabilities, 18% of the sentences were
\x0c278
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
</figure>
<tableCaption confidence="0.3255685">
Table 16
Results on rescoring parser output.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.98666">
Frame Frame Labeled Labeled
Method Element Precision Element Recall Precision Recall
Single-best parse 74.0 70.1 64.6 61.2
Rescoring parses 73.8 70.7 64.6 61.9
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.993859666666667">
assigned a parse different from the original best parse. Nevertheless, the impact on
identification of frame elements was small; results are shown in Table 16. The results
show a slight, but not statistically significant, increase in recall of frame elements. One
possible reason that the improvement is not greater is the relatively small number of
parses per sentence available for rescoring. Unfortunately, the parsing algorithm used
to generate n-best parses is inefficient, and generating large numbers of parses seems
to be computationally intractable. In theory, the complexity of n-best variations of the
Viterbi chart-parsing algorithm is quadratic in n. One can simply expand the dynamic
programming chart to have n slots for the best solutions to each subproblem, rather
than one. As our grammar forms new constituents from pairs of smaller constituents
(that is, it internally uses a binarized grammar), for each pair of constituents considered
in a single-best parser, up to n2
pairs would be present in the n-best variant. The
beam search used by modern parsers, however, makes the analysis more complex.
Lexicalization of parse constituents dramatically increases the number of categories
that must be stored in the chart, and efficient parsing requires that constituents below
a particular probability threshold be dropped from further consideration. In practice,
returning a larger number of parses with our algorithm seems to require increasing
the pruning beam size to a degree that makes run times prohibitive.
In addition to the robustness of even relatively simple parsing models, one expla-
nation for the modest improvement may be the fact that even our integrated system
includes semantic information for only one word in the sentence. As the coverage of
our frame descriptions increases, it may be possible to do better and to model the
interactions between the frames invoked by a text.
9. Generalizing to Unseen Predicates
Most of the statistics used in the system as described above are conditioned on the
target word, or predicate, for which semantic roles are being identified. This limits the
applicability of the system to words for which training data are available. In Section 6,
we attempted to generalize across fillers for the roles of a single predicate. In this
section, we turn to the related but somewhat more difficult question of generalizing
from seen to unseen predicates.
Many ways of attempting this generalization are possible, but the simplest is
provided by the frame-semantic information of the FrameNet database. We can use
data from target words in the same frame to predict behavior for an unseen word,
or, if no data are available for the frame in question, we can use data from the same
broad semantic domain into which the frames are grouped.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.992485">
9.1 Thematic Roles
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988596963636364">
To investigate the degree to which our system is dependent on the set of semantic
roles used, we performed experiments using abstract, general semantic roles such as
\x0c279
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Agent, Patient, and Goal. Such roles were proposed in theories of linking such as
Fillmore (1968) and Jackendoff (1972) to explain the syntactic realization of semantic
arguments. This level of roles, often called thematic roles, was seen as useful for
expressing generalizations such as If a sentence has an Agent, the Agent will occupy
the subject position. Such correlations might enable a statistical system to generalize
from one semantic domain to another.
Recent work on linguistic theories of linking has attempted to explain syntactic
realization in terms of the fundamentals of verbs meaning (see Levin and Rappaport
Hovav [1996] for a survey of a number of theories). Although such an explanation is
desirable, our goal is more modest: an automatic procedure for identifying semantic
roles in text. We aim to use abstract roles as a means of generalizing from limited
training data in various semantic domains. We see this effort as consistent with various
theoretical accounts of the underlying mechanisms of argument linking, since the
various theories all postulate some sort of generalization between the roles of specific
predicates.
To this end, we developed a correspondence from frame-specific roles to a set
of abstract thematic roles. For each frame, an abstract thematic role was assigned to
each frame element in the frames definition. Since there is no canonical set of abstract
semantic roles, we decided upon the list shown in Table 17. We are interested in
adjuncts as well as arguments, leading to roles such as Degree not found in many
theories of verb-argument linking. The difficulty of fitting many relations into standard
categories such as Agent and Patient led us to include other roles such as Topic.
In all, we used 18 roles, a somewhat richer set than is often used, but still much more
restricted than the frame-specific roles. Even with this enriched set, not all frame-
specific roles fit neatly into one category.
An experiment was performed replacing each role tag in the training and test
data with the corresponding thematic role and training the system as described above
on the new dataset. Results were roughly comparable for the two types of semantic
roles: overall performance was 82.1% for thematic roles, compared to 80.4% for frame-
specific roles. This reflects the fact that most frames had a one-to-one mapping from
frame-specific to abstract roles, so the tasks were largely equivalent. We expect abstract
roles to be most useful when one is generalizing to predicates and frames not found
in the training data, the topic of the following sections.
One interesting consequence of using abstract roles is that they allow us to compare
more easily the systems performance on different roles because of the smaller number
of categories. This breakdown is shown in Table 18. Results are given for two systems:
the first assumes that the frame element boundaries are known and the second finds
them automatically. The second system, which is described in Section 7.1, corresponds
to the rightmost two columns in Table 18. The Labeled Recall column shows how
often the frame element is correctly identified, whereas the Unlabeled Recall column
shows how often a constituent with the given role is correctly identified as being a
frame element, even if it is labeled with the wrong role.
Experiencer and Agent, two similar roles generally found as the subject for
complementary sets of verbs, are the roles that are correctly identified the most often.
The Unlabeled Recall column shows that these roles are easy to find in the sentence,
as a predicates subject is almost always a frame element, and the Known Boundaries
column shows that they are also not often confused with other roles when it is known
that they are frame elements. The two most difficult roles in terms of unlabeled recall,
Manner and Degree, are typically realized by adverbs or prepositional phrases and
considered adjuncts. It is interesting to note that these are considered in FrameNet to
be general frame elements that can be used in any frame.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9718878">
\x0c280
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Table 17
Abstract semantic roles, with representative examples from the FrameNet corpus.
Role Example
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.969708243243243">
Agent Henry pushed the door open and went in.
Cause Jeez, that amazes me as well as riles me.
Degree I rather deplore the recent manifestation of Pop; it doesnt seem to me to
have the intellectual force of the art of the Sixties.
Experiencer It may even have been that John anticipating his imminent doom ratified
some such arrangement perhaps in the ceremony at the Jordan.
Force If this is the case can it be substantiated by evidence from the history of
developed societies?
Goal Distant across the river the towers of the castle rose against the sky strad-
dling the only land approach into Shrewsbury.
Instrument In the children with colonic contractions fasting motility did not differentiate
children with and without constipation.
Location These fleshy appendages are used to detect and taste food amongst the
weed and debris on the bottom of a river.
Manner His brow arched delicately.
Null Yet while she had no intention of surrendering her home, it would be foolish
to let the atmosphere between them become too acrimonious.
Path The dung-collector ambled slowly over, one eye on Sir John.
Patient As soon as a character lays a hand on this item, the skeletal Cleric grips it
more tightly.
Percept What is apparent is that this manual is aimed at the non-specialist techni-
cian, possibly an embalmer who has good knowledge of some medical
procedures.
Proposition It says that rotation of partners does not demonstrate independence.
Result All the arrangements for stay-behind agents in north-west Europe collapsed,
but Dansey was able to charm most of the governments in exile in London
into recruiting spies.
Source He heard the sound of liquid slurping in a metal container as Farrell ap-
proached him from behind.
State Rex spied out Sam Maggott hollering at all and sundry and making good
use of his over-sized red gingham handkerchief.
Topic He said, We would urge people to be aware and be alert with fireworks
because your fun might be someone elses tragedy.
This section has shown that our system can use roles defined at a more abstract
level than the corpuss frame-level roles and in fact that when we are looking at a
single predicate, the choice has little effect. In the following sections, we attempt to
use the abstract roles to generalize the behavior of semantically related predicates.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.984613">
9.2 Unseen Predicates
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.868392352941176">
We will present results at different, successively broader levels of generalization, mak-
ing use of the categorization of FrameNet predicates into frames and more general
semantic domains. We first turn to using data from the appropriate frame when no
data for the target word are available.
Table 19 shows results for various probability distributions using a division of
training and test data constructed such that no target words are in common. Every
tenth target word was included in the test set. The amount of training data available
for each frame varied, from just one target word in some cases to 167 target words
in the perception/noise frame. The training set contained a total of 75,919 frame
elements and the test set 7,801 frame elements.
\x0c281
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 18
Performance broken down by abstract role. The third column represents accuracy when frame
element boundaries are given to the system, and the fourth and fifth columns reflect finding
the boundaries automatically. Unlabeled recall includes cases that were identified as a frame
element but given the wrong role.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.98462552">
Known Boundaries Unknown Boundaries
Role Number % Correct Labeled Recall Unlabeled Recall
Agent 2401 92.8 76.7 80.7
Experiencer 333 91.0 78.7 83.5
Source 503 87.3 67.4 74.2
Proposition 186 86.6 56.5 64.5
State 71 85.9 53.5 62.0
Patient 1161 83.3 63.1 69.1
Topic 244 82.4 64.3 72.1
Goal 694 82.1 60.2 69.6
Cause 424 76.2 61.6 73.8
Path 637 75.0 63.1 63.4
Manner 494 70.4 48.6 59.7
Percept 103 68.0 51.5 65.1
Degree 61 67.2 50.8 60.7
Null 55 65.5 70.9 85.5
Result 40 65.0 55.0 70.0
Location 275 63.3 47.6 63.6
Force 49 59.2 40.8 63.3
Instrument 30 43.3 30.0 73.3
(other) 406 57.9 40.9 63.1
Total 8167 82.1 63.6 72.1
Table 19
Cross-frame performance of various distributions. f represents the FrameNet semantic frame.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
</table>
<equation confidence="0.9201485">
P(r  |path) 95.3% 44.5% 42.4%
P(r  |path, f) 87.4 68.7 60.1
P(r  |h) 91.7 54.3 49.8
P(r  |h, f) 74.1 81.3 60.3
P(r  |pt, position, voice) 100.0 43.9 43.9
P(r  |pt, position, voice, f) 98.7 68.3 67.4
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9978025">
The results show a familiar trade-off between coverage and accuracy. Conditioning
both the head word and path features on the frame reduces coverage but improves
accuracy. A linear interpolation,
1P(r  |path, f) + 2P(r  |h, f) + 3P(r  |pt, position, voice, f)
achieved 79.4% performance on the test set, significantly better than any of the in-
dividual distributions and approaching the result of 82.1% for the original system,
using target-specific statistics and thematic roles. This result indicates that predicates
in the same frame behave similarly in terms of their argument structure, a finding
generally consistent with theories of linking that claim that the syntactic realization
of verb arguments can be predicted from their semantics. We would expect verbs in
the same frame to be semantically similar and to have the same patterns of argument
structure. The relatively high performance of frame-level statistics indicates that the
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9321894">
\x0c282
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Table 20
Cross-frame performance of various distributions. d represents the FrameNet semantic domain.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.967490555555556">
P(r  |path) 96.2% 41.2% 39.7%
P(r  |path, d) 85.7 42.7 36.6
P(r  |h) 91.0 44.7 40.6
P(r  |h, d) 75.2 54.3 40.9
P(r  |d) 95.1 29.9 28.4
P(r) 100.0 28.7 28.7
P(r  |h, d) P(r  |pt, path, d)
P(r  |d)
Figure 13
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.998816666666667">
Minimal lattice for cross-frame generalization.
frames defined by FrameNet are fine-grained enough to capture the relevant semantic
similarities.
This result is encouraging in that it indicates that a relatively small amount of data
can be annotated for a few words in a semantic frame and used to train a system that
can then bootstrap to a larger number of predicates.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.986116">
9.3 Unseen Frames
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999758083333333">
More difficult than the question of unseen predicates in a known frame are frames
for which no training data are present. The 67 frames in the current data set cover
only a fraction of the English language, and the high cost of annotation makes it
difficult to expand the data set to cover all semantic domains. The FrameNet project is
defining additional frames and annotating data to expand the scope of the database.
The question of how many frames exist, however, remains unanswered for the time
being; a full account of frame semantics is expected to include multiple frames being
invoked by many words, as well as an inheritance hierarchy of frames and a more
detailed representation of each frames meaning.
In this section, we examine the FrameNet data by holding out an entire frame for
testing and using other frames from the same general semantic domain for training.
Recall from Figure 1 that domains like Communication include frames like Conver-
sation, Questioning, and Statement. Because of the variation in difficulty between
different frames and the dependence of the results on which frames are held out for
testing, we used a jackknifing methodology. Each frame was used in turn as test data,
with all other frames used as training data. The results in Table 20 show average
results over the entire data set.
Combining the distributions gives a system based on the (very restricted) backoff
lattice of Figure 13. This system achieves performance of 51.0%, compared to 82.1%
for the original system and 79.4% for the within-frame generalization task. The results
show that generalizing across frames, even within a domain, is more difficult than
generalizing across target words within a frame. There are several factors that may
account for this: the FrameNet domains were intended primarily as a way of orga-
nizing the project, and their semantics have not been formalized. Thus, it may not be
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6727904">
\x0c283
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Table 21
Cross-domain performance of various distributions.
Distribution Coverage Accuracy Performance
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.599590666666667">
P(r  |path) 96.5% 35.3% 33.4%
P(r  |h) 88.8 36.0 31.9
P(r) 100.0 28.7 28.7
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999817518518519">
surprising that they do not correspond to significant generalizations about argument
structure. The domains are fairly broad, as indicated by the fact that always choosing
the most common role for a given domain (the baseline for cross-frame, within-domain
generalization, given as P(r  |d) in Table 20, classifies 28.4% of frame elements cor-
rectly) does not do better than the cross-domain baseline of always choosing the most
common role from the entire database regardless of domain (P(r) in Table 20, which
yields 28.7% correct). This contrasts with a 40.9% baseline for P(r  |t), that is, always
choosing the most common role for a particular target word (Table 5, last line). Do-
main information does not seem to help a great deal, given no information about the
frame.
Furthermore, the cross-frame experiments here are dependent on the mapping of
frame-level roles to abstract thematic roles. This mapping was done at the frame level;
that is, FrameNet roles with the same label in two different frames may be translated
into two different thematic roles, but all target words in the same frame make use of
the same mapping. The mapping of roles within a frame is generally one to one, and
therefore the choice of mapping has little effect when using statistics conditioned on
the target word and on the frame, as in the previous section. When we are attempting
to generalize between frames, the mapping determines which roles from the training
frame are used to calculate probabilities for the roles in the test frames, and the choice
of mapping is much more significant. The mapping used is necessarily somewhat
arbitrary.
It is interesting to note that the path feature performs better when not conditioned
on the domain. The head word, however, seems to be more domain-specific: although
coverage declines when the context is restricted to the semantic domain, accuracy
improves. This seems to indicate that the identity of certain role fillers is domain-
specific, but that the syntax/semantics correspondence captured by the path feature is
more general, as predicted by theories of syntactic linking.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.981193">
9.4 Unseen Domains
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98413975">
As general as they are, the semantic domains of the current FrameNet database cover
only a small portion of the language. The domains are defined at the level of, for
example, Communication and Emotion; a list of the 12 domains in our corpus is
given in Table 1. Whether generalization is possible across domains is an important
question for a general language-understanding system.
For these experiments, a jackknifing protocol similar to that of the previous section
was used, this time holding out one entire domain at a time and using all the others as
training material. Results for the path and head word feature are shown in Table 21.
The distributions P(r  |path), P(r  |h), and P(r) of Table 21 also appeared in Table 20;
the difference between the experiments is only in the division of training and test sets.
A linear interpolation, 1P(r  |path) + 2P(r  |h), classifies 39.8% of frame elements
correctly. This is no better than our result of 40.9% (Table 3) for always choosing a
\x0c284
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
predicates most frequent role; however, the cross-domain system does not have role
frequencies for the test predicates.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.859658">
9.5 Discussion
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988048568181818">
As one might expect, as we make successively broader generalizations to semantically
more distant predicates, performance degrades. Our results indicate that frame seman-
tics give us a level at which generalizations relevant to argument linking can be made.
Our results for unseen predicates within the same frame are encouraging, indicating
that the predicates are semantically similar in ways that result in similar argument
structure, as the semantically based theories of linking advocated by Levin (1993) and
Levin and Rappaport Hovav (1996) would predict. We hope that corpus-based sys-
tems such as ours can provide a way of testing and elaborating such theories in the
future. We believe that some level of skeletal representation of the relevant aspects
of a words meaning, along the lines of Kipper et al. (2000) and of the frame hierar-
chy being developed by the FrameNet project, could be used in the future to help a
statistical system generalize from similar words for which training data are available.
10. Conclusion
Our system is able to label semantic roles automatically with fairly high accuracy,
indicating promise for applications in various natural language tasks. Semantic roles
do not seem to be simple functions of a sentences syntactic tree structure, and lexical
statistics were found to be extremely valuable, as has been the case in other natural
language processing applications. Although lexical statistics are quite accurate on the
data covered by observations in the training set, the sparsity of their coverage led
us to introduce semantically motivated knowledge sources, which in turn allowed us
to compare automatically derived and hand-built semantic resources. Various meth-
ods of extending the coverage of lexical statistics indicated that the broader coverage
of automatic clustering outweighed its imprecision. Carefully choosing sentence-level
features for representing alternations in verb argument structure allowed us to intro-
duce dependencies between frame element decisions within a sentence without adding
too much complexity to the system. Integrating semantic interpretation and syntactic
parsing yielded only the slightest gain, showing that although probabilistic models
allow easy integration of modules, the gain over an unintegrated system may not be
large because of the robustness of even simple probabilistic systems.
Many aspects of our system are still quite preliminary. For example, our system
currently assumes knowledge of the correct frame type for the target word to deter-
mine the semantic roles of its arguments. A more complete semantic analysis system
would thus require a module for frame disambiguation. It is not clear how difficult
this problem is and how much it overlaps with the general problem of word-sense
disambiguation.
Much else remains to be done to apply the system described here to the inter-
pretation of general text. One technique for dealing with the sparseness of lexical
statistics would be the combination of FrameNet data with named-entity systems for
recognizing times, dates, and locations, the effort that has gone into recognizing these
items, typically used as adjuncts, should complement the FrameNet data, which is
more focused on arguments. Generalization to predicates for which no annotated data
are available may be possible using other lexical resources or automatic clustering of
predicates. Automatically learning generalizations about the semantics and syntactic
behavior of predicates is an exciting problem for the years to come.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.809249714285714">
\x0c285
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Appendix
Table 22
Penn Treebank part-of-speech tags (including punctuation).
Tag Description Example Tag Description Example
CC Coordin. Conjunction and, but, or SYM Symbol +,%, &amp;
CD Cardinal number one, two, three TO to to
DT Determiner a, the UH Interjection ah, oops
EX Existential there there VB Verb, base form eat
FW Foreign word mea culpa VBD Verb, past tense ate
IN Preposition/sub-conj of, in, by VBG Verb, gerund eating
JJ Adjective yellow VBN Verb, past participle eaten
JJR Adj., comparative bigger VBP Verb, non-3sg pres eat
JJS Adj., superlative wildest VBZ Verb, 3sg pres eats
LS List item marker 1, 2, One WDT Wh-determiner which, that
MD Modal can, should WP Wh-pronoun what, who
NN Noun, sing. or mass llama WP$ Possessive wh- whose
NNS Noun, plural llamas WRB Wh-adverb how, where
NNP Proper noun, singular IBM $ Dollar sign $
NNPS Proper noun, plural Carolinas # Pound sign #
PDT Predeterminer all, both Left quote ( or )
POS Possessive ending s Right quote ( or )
PRP Personal pronoun I, you, he ( Left parenthesis ( [, (, {, &amp;lt;)
PRP$ Possessive pronoun your, ones ) Right parenthesis ( ], ), }, &gt;)
RB Adverb quickly, never , Comma ,
RBR Adverb, comparative faster . Sentence-final punc (. ! ?)
RBS Adverb, superlative fastest : Mid-sentence punc (: ; ... -)
RP Particle up, off
Table 23
Penn Treebank constituent (or nonterminal) labels.
Label Description
ADJP Adjective Phrase
ADVP Adverb Phrase
CONJP Conjunction Phrase
FRAG Fragment
INTJ Interjection
NAC Not a constituent
NP Noun Phrase
NX Head subphrase of complex noun phrase
PP Prepositional Phrase
QP Quantifier Phrase
RRC Reduced Relative Clause
S Simple declarative clause (sentence)
SBAR Clause introduced by complementizer
SBARQ Question introduced by wh-word
SINV Inverted declarative sentence
SQ Inverted yes/no question
UCP Unlike Co-ordinated Phrase
VP Verb Phrase
WHADJP Wh-adjective Phrase
WHADVP Wh-adverb Phrase
WHNP Wh-noun Phrase
WHPP Wh-prepositional Phrase
\x0c286
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885565" genericHeader="method">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9177505">
We are grateful to Chuck Fillmore, Andreas
Stolcke, Jerry Feldman, and three
anonymous reviewers for their comments
and suggestions, to Collin Baker for his
assistance with the FrameNet data, and to
Mats Rooth and Sabine Schulte
im Walde for making available their parsed
corpus. This work was primarily funded by
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.519334" genericHeader="method">
National Science Foundation grant ITR/HCI
#0086132 to the FrameNet project.
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999244151639343">
Baayen, R. H., R. Piepenbrock, and
L. Gulikers. 1995. The CELEX Lexical
Database (Release 2) [CD-ROM]. Linguistic
Data Consortium, University of
Pennsylvania [Distributor], Philadelphia,
PA.
Baker, Collin F., Charles J. Fillmore, and
John B. Lowe. 1998. The Berkeley
FrameNet project. In Proceedings of
COLING/ACL, pages 8690, Montreal,
Canada.
Blaheta, Don and Eugene Charniak. 2000.
Assigning function tags to parsed text.
In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of
the North American Chapter of the ACL
(NAACL), pages 234240, Seattle,
Washington.
Carroll, Glenn and Mats Rooth. 1998.
Valence induction with a
head-lexicalized PCFG. In Proceedings of
the Third Conference on Empirical Methods in
Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 3),
Granada, Spain.
Charniak, Eugene. 1997. Statistical parsing
with a context-free grammar and word
statistics. In AAAI-97, pages 598603,
Menlo Park, August. AAAI Press, Menlo
Park, California.
Collins, Michael. 1997. Three generative,
lexicalised models for statistical parsing.
In Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of
the ACL, pages 1623, Madrid, Spain.
Collins, Michael. 1999. Head-Driven
Statistical Models for Natural Language
Parsing. Ph.D. dissertation, University of
Pennsylvania, Philadelphia.
Dahiya, Yajan Veer. 1995. Panini as a Linguist:
Ideas and Patterns. Eastern Book Linkers,
Delhi, India.
Defense Advanced Research Projects
Agency, editor. 1998. Proceedings of the
Seventh Message Understanding Conference.
Dowty, David R. 1991. Thematic proto-roles
and argument selection. Language
67(3):547619.
Fellbaum, Christiane, editor. 1998. WordNet:
An Electronic Lexical Database. MIT Press,
Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1968. The case for
case. In Emmon W. Bach and Robert T.
Harms, editors, Universals in Linguistic
Theory. Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston, New
York, pages 188.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1971. Some problems
for case grammar. In R. J. OBrien,
editor, 22nd Annual Round Table.
Linguistics: Developments of the
SixtiesViewpoints of the Seventies.
Volume 24 of Monograph Series on
Language and Linguistics. Georgetown
University Press, Washington, D.C.,
pages 3556.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1976. Frame semantics
and the nature of language. In Annals of
the New York Academy of Sciences:
Conference on the Origin and Development of
Language and Speech, Volume 280,
pages 2032. New York Academy of
Sciences, New York.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1986. Pragmatically
controlled zero anaphora. In Proceedings
of Berkeley Linguistics Society, pages 95107,
Berkeley, California.
Fillmore, Charles J. and Collin F. Baker.
2000. FrameNet: Frame semantics meets
the corpus. Poster presentation, 74th
Annual Meeting of the Linguistics Society
of America.
Gildea, Daniel and Thomas Hofmann. 1999.
Probabilistic topic analysis for language
modeling. In Eurospeech-99,
pages 21672170, Budapest.
Hearst, Marti. 1999. Untangling text data
mining. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual
Meeting of the ACL, pages 310, College
Park, Maryland.
Hobbs, Jerry R., Douglas Appelt, John Bear,
David Israel, Megumi Kameyama,
Mark E. Stickel, and Mabry Tyson. 1997.
FASTUS: A cascaded finite-state
transducer for extracting information
from natural-language text. In
Emmanuel Roche and Yves Schabes,
editors, Finite-State Language Processing.
MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts,
pages 383406.
Hofmann, Thomas and Jan Puzicha. 1998.
Statistical models for co-occurrence
data. Memorandum, Massachussetts
Institute of Technology Artificial
Intelligence Laboratory, Cambridge,
Massachusetts.
Jackendoff, Ray. 1972. Semantic Interpretation
in Generative Grammar. MIT Press,
\x0c287
Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles
Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Jelinek, Frederick and Robert L. Mercer.
1980. Interpolated estimation of Markov
source parameters from sparse data. In
Proceedings: Workshop on Pattern Recognition
in Practice, pages 381397. Amsterdam.
North Holland.
Johnson, Christopher R., Charles J. Fillmore,
Esther J. Wood, Josef Ruppenhofer,
Margaret Urban, Miriam R. L. Petruk, and
Collin F. Baker. 2001. The FrameNet
project: Tools for lexicon building. Version
0.7. Available at http:/
/www.icsi.
berkeley.edu/ framenet/book.html.
Kipper, Karin, Hoa Trang Dang, William
Schuler, and Martha Palmer. 2000.
Building a class-based verb lexicon using
TAGs. In TAG+5 Fifth International
Workshop on Tree Adjoining Grammars and
Related Formalisms, Paris, May.
Lapata, Maria and Chris Brew. 1999. Using
subcategorization to resolve verb class
ambiguity. In Joint SIGDAT Conference on
Empirical Methods in NLP and Very Large
Corpora, pages 266274, College Park,
Maryland.
Levin, Beth. 1993. English Verb Classes and
Alternations: A Preliminary Investigation.
University of Chicago Press, Chicago.
Levin, Beth and Malka Rappaport Hovav.
1996. From lexical semantics to
argument realization. Unpublished
manuscript.
Marcus, Mitchell P., Grace Kim, Mary Ann
Marcinkiewicz, Robert MacIntyre, Ann
Bies, Mark Ferguson, Karen Katz, and
Britta Schasberger. 1994. The Penn
Treebank: Annotating predicate argument
structure. In ARPA Human Language
Technology Workshop, pages 114119,
Plainsboro, New Jersey. Morgan
Kaufmann, San Francisco.
Marcus, Mitchell P., Beatrice Santorini, and
Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz. 1993. Building
a large annotated corpus of English: The
Penn treebank. Computational Linguistics
19(2):313330.
McCarthy, Diana. 2000. Using semantic
preferences to identify verbal
participation in role switching
alternations. In Proceedings of the First
Annual Meeting of the North American
Chapter of the ACL (NAACL),
pages 256263, Seattle, Washington.
Miller, Scott, Heidi Fox, Lance Ramshaw,
and Ralph Weischedel. 2000. A novel use
of statistical parsing to extract
information from text. In Proceedings of
the First Annual Meeting of the North
American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL),
pages 226233, Seattle, Washington.
Miller, Scott, David Stallard, Robert Bobrow,
and Richard Schwartz. 1996. A fully
statistical approach to natural language
interfaces. In Proceedings of the 34th
Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 5561,
Santa Cruz, California.
Misra, Vidya Niwas. 1966. The Descriptive
Technique of Panini. Mouton, The
Hague.
Pereira, Fernando, Naftali Tishby, and
Lillian Lee. 1993. Distributional
clustering of English words. In
Proceedings of the 31st Annual Meeting of the
ACL, pages 183190, Columbus, Ohio.
Pietra, Stephen Della, Vincent Della Pietra,
and John Lafferty. 1997. Inducing features
of random fields. IEEE Transactions on
Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence
19(4):380393.
Pollard, Carl and Ivan A. Sag. 1994.
Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar.
University of Chicago Press, Chicago.
Riloff, Ellen. 1993. Automatically
constructing a dictionary for information
extraction tasks. In Proceedings of the 11th
National Conference on Artificial Intelligence
(AAAI), pages 811816, Washington, D.C.
Riloff, Ellen and Mark Schmelzenbach. 1998.
An empirical approach to conceptual
case frame acquisition. In Proceedings of
the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora,
pages 4956, Montreal, Canada.
Rocher, Rosane. 1964. Agent et Objet
chez Panini. Journal of the American
Oriental Society 84:4454.
Rooth, Mats. 1995. Two-dimensional
clusters in grammatical relations. In
AAAI Symposium on Representation and
Acquisition of Lexical Knowledge, Stanford,
California.
Rooth, Mats, Stefan Riezler, Detlef Prescher,
Glenn Carroll, and Franz Beil. 1999.
Inducing a semantically annotated
lexicon via EM-based clustering. In
Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the
ACL, pages 104111, College Park,
Maryland.
Schank, Roger C. 1972. Conceptual
dependency: A theory of natural
language understanding. Cognitive
Psychology 3:552631.
Siegel, Sidney and N. John Castellan, Jr.
1988. Nonparametric Statistics for the
Behavioral Sciences. 2nd ed. McGraw-Hill,
New York.
Somers, Harold L. 1987. Valency and Case in
Computational Linguistics. Edinburgh
University Press, Edinburgh, Scotland.
Stallard, David. 2000. Talkntravel: A
conversational system for air travel
planning. In Proceedings of the Sixth
\x0c288
Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3
Applied Natural Language Processing
Conference (ANLP00), pages 6875.
Van Valin, Robert D. 1993. A synopsis of
role and reference grammar. In Robert D.
Van Valin, editor, Advances in Role and
Reference Grammar. John Benjamins
Publishing Company, Amsterdam,
pages 1166.
Winograd, Terry. 1972. Understanding
natural language. Cognitive Psychology,
3(1). Reprinted as a book by Academic
Press, 1972.
\x0c&amp;apos;
</reference>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.737588">
<note confidence="0.88785">b&amp;apos;c \x01 2002 Association for Computational Linguistics</note>
<title confidence="0.988468">Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles</title>
<author confidence="0.9953425">Daniel Gildea Daniel Jurafsky</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.986594333333333">University of California, Berkeley, and International Computer Science Institute University of Colorado, Boulder</affiliation>
<abstract confidence="0.99628855">We present a system for identifying the semantic relationships, or semantic roles, filled by constituents of a sentence within a semantic frame. Given an input sentence and a target word and frame, the system labels constituents with either abstract semantic roles, such as Agent or Patient, or more domain-specific semantic roles, such as Speaker, Message, and Topic. The system is based on statistical classifiers trained on roughly 50,000 sentences that were hand-annotated with semantic roles by the FrameNet semantic labeling project. We then parsed each training sentence into a syntactic tree and extracted various lexical and syntactic features, including the phrase type of each constituent, its grammatical function, and its position in the sentence. These features were combined with knowledge of the predicate verb, noun, or adjective, as well as information such as the prior probabilities of various combinations of semantic roles. We used various lexical clustering algorithms to generalize across possible fillers of roles. Test sentences were parsed, were annotated with these features, and were then passed through the classifiers. Our system achieves 82% accuracy in identifying the semantic role of presegmented constituents. At the more difficult task of simultaneously segmenting constituents and identifying their semantic role, the system achieved 65% precision and 61% recall. Our study also allowed us to compare the usefulness of different features and feature combination methods in the semantic role labeling task. We also explore the integration of role labeling with statistical syntactic parsing and attempt to generalize to predicates unseen in the training data.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Roles Baayen</author>
<author>R H</author>
<author>R Piepenbrock</author>
<author>L Gulikers</author>
</authors>
<title>4. Probability Estimation for</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>The CELEX Lexical Database (Release 2) [CD-ROM]. Linguistic</booktitle>
<volume>28</volume>
<institution>Computational Linguistics</institution>
<location>Philadelphia, PA.</location>
<marker>Baayen, H, Piepenbrock, Gulikers, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 4. Probability Estimation for Roles Baayen, R. H., R. Piepenbrock, and L. Gulikers. 1995. The CELEX Lexical Database (Release 2) [CD-ROM]. Linguistic Data Consortium, University of Pennsylvania [Distributor], Philadelphia, PA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Collin F Baker</author>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>John B Lowe</author>
</authors>
<title>The Berkeley FrameNet project.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of COLING/ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>8690</pages>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<marker>Baker, Fillmore, Lowe, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Baker, Collin F., Charles J. Fillmore, and John B. Lowe. 1998. The Berkeley FrameNet project. In Proceedings of COLING/ACL, pages 8690, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Don Blaheta</author>
<author>Eugene Charniak</author>
</authors>
<title>Assigning function tags to parsed text.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of the North American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL),</booktitle>
<pages>234240</pages>
<location>Seattle, Washington.</location>
<marker>Blaheta, Charniak, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Blaheta, Don and Eugene Charniak. 2000. Assigning function tags to parsed text. In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of the North American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL), pages 234240, Seattle, Washington.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Glenn Carroll</author>
<author>Mats Rooth</author>
</authors>
<title>Valence induction with a head-lexicalized PCFG.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Third Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 3),</booktitle>
<location>Granada,</location>
<marker>Carroll, Rooth, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Carroll, Glenn and Mats Rooth. 1998. Valence induction with a head-lexicalized PCFG. In Proceedings of the Third Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 3), Granada, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Eugene Charniak</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical parsing with a context-free grammar and word statistics.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In AAAI-97,</booktitle>
<pages>598603</pages>
<publisher>AAAI Press,</publisher>
<location>Menlo Park,</location>
<marker>Charniak, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Charniak, Eugene. 1997. Statistical parsing with a context-free grammar and word statistics. In AAAI-97, pages 598603, Menlo Park, August. AAAI Press, Menlo Park, California.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Collins</author>
</authors>
<title>Three generative, lexicalised models for statistical parsing.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<marker>Collins, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Collins, Michael. 1997. Three generative, lexicalised models for statistical parsing.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date></date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>1623</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>In Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 1623, Madrid, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Collins</author>
</authors>
<title>Head-Driven Statistical Models for Natural Language Parsing.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania,</institution>
<location>Philadelphia.</location>
<note>Ph.D. dissertation,</note>
<marker>Collins, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Collins, Michael. 1999. Head-Driven Statistical Models for Natural Language Parsing. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yajan Veer Dahiya</author>
</authors>
<title>Panini as a Linguist: Ideas and Patterns. Eastern Book Linkers,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<location>Delhi, India.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="9096" citStr="Dahiya 1995" startWordPosition="1348" endWordPosition="1349">nations in verb argument structure with sentence-level features. We combine syntactic parsing and semantic role identification into a single probability model in Section 8. Section 9 addresses the question of generalizing statistics from one target predicate to another, beginning with a look at domain-independent thematic roles in Section 9.1. Finally we draw conclusions and discuss future directions in Section 10. 2. Semantic Roles Semantic roles are one of the oldest classes of constructs in linguistic theory, dating back thousands of years to Paninis karaka theory (Misra 1966; Rocher 1964; Dahiya 1995). Longevity, in this case, begets variety, and the literature records scores of proposals for sets of semantic roles. These sets of roles range from the very specific to the very general, and many have been used in computational implementations of one type or another. At the specific end of the spectrum are domain-specific roles such as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient (Van Vali</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dahiya, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Dahiya, Yajan Veer. 1995. Panini as a Linguist: Ideas and Patterns. Eastern Book Linkers, Delhi, India.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, editor. 1998. Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference.</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, editor. 1998. Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David R Dowty</author>
</authors>
<title>Thematic proto-roles and argument selection.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<journal>Language</journal>
<volume>67</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="9715" citStr="Dowty 1991" startWordPosition="1452" endWordPosition="1453">ity, in this case, begets variety, and the literature records scores of proposals for sets of semantic roles. These sets of roles range from the very specific to the very general, and many have been used in computational implementations of one type or another. At the specific end of the spectrum are domain-specific roles such as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient (Van Valin 1993; Dowty 1991). In between lie many theories with approximately 10 roles, such as Fillmores (1971) list of nine: Agent, Experiencer, Instrument, Object, Source, Goal, Location, Time, and Path.1 1 There are scores of other theories with slightly different sets of roles, including those of Fillmore (1968), Jackendoff (1972), and Schank (1972); see Somers (1987) for an excellent summary. \x0c248 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 banterv debatev conversev gossipv disputen discussionn tiffn Conversation Frame: Protagonist1 Protagonist2 Protagonists Topic Medium Frame Elements: arguev Domain: Communic</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dowty, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Dowty, David R. 1991. Thematic proto-roles and argument selection. Language 67(3):547619.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>WordNet: An Electronic Lexical Database.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<editor>Fellbaum, Christiane, editor.</editor>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="22492" citStr="(1998)" startWordPosition="3430" endWordPosition="3430">semantic interpretation in limited domains by shallow systems that avoid complex feature structures and often perform only shallow syntactic analysis. For example, in the context of the Air Traveler Information System (ATIS) for spoken dialogue, Miller et al. (1996) computed the probability that a constituent such as Atlanta filled a semantic slot such as Destination in a semantic frame for air travel. In a data-driven approach to information extraction, Riloff (1993) builds a dictionary of patterns for filling slots in a specific domain such as terrorist attacks, and Riloff and Schmelzenbach (1998) extend this technique to derive automatically entire case frames for words in the domain. These last systems make use of a limited amount of hand labor to accept or reject automatically generated hypotheses. They show promise for a more sophisticated approach to generalizing beyond the relatively small number of frames considered in the tasks. More recently, a domain-independent system has been trained by Blaheta and Charniak (2000) on the function tags, such as Manner and Temporal, included in the Penn Treebank corpus. Some of these tags correspond to FrameNet semantic roles, but the Treeban</context>
</contexts>
<marker>1998</marker>
<rawString>Fellbaum, Christiane, editor. 1998. WordNet: An Electronic Lexical Database. MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>The case for case.</title>
<date>1968</date>
<booktitle>Universals in Linguistic Theory.</booktitle>
<pages>188</pages>
<editor>In Emmon W. Bach and Robert T. Harms, editors,</editor>
<publisher>Winston,</publisher>
<location>Holt, Rinehart</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10005" citStr="Fillmore (1968)" startWordPosition="1497" endWordPosition="1498">e spectrum are domain-specific roles such as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient (Van Valin 1993; Dowty 1991). In between lie many theories with approximately 10 roles, such as Fillmores (1971) list of nine: Agent, Experiencer, Instrument, Object, Source, Goal, Location, Time, and Path.1 1 There are scores of other theories with slightly different sets of roles, including those of Fillmore (1968), Jackendoff (1972), and Schank (1972); see Somers (1987) for an excellent summary. \x0c248 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 banterv debatev conversev gossipv disputen discussionn tiffn Conversation Frame: Protagonist1 Protagonist2 Protagonists Topic Medium Frame Elements: arguev Domain: Communication Domain: Cognition Frame: Questioning Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Frame: Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Statement Frame: Frame Elements: Judgment Judge Evaluee Reason Role disputen blamev faultn admirev admirationn disapprovev blamen </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, 1968</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. 1968. The case for case. In Emmon W. Bach and Robert T. Harms, editors, Universals in Linguistic Theory. Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston, New York, pages 188.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Some problems for case grammar. In</title>
<date>1971</date>
<booktitle>22nd Annual Round Table. Linguistics: Developments of the SixtiesViewpoints of the Seventies. Volume 24 of Monograph Series on Language and Linguistics.</booktitle>
<pages>3556</pages>
<editor>R. J. OBrien, editor,</editor>
<publisher>Georgetown University Press,</publisher>
<location>Washington, D.C.,</location>
<marker>Fillmore, 1971</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. 1971. Some problems for case grammar. In R. J. OBrien, editor, 22nd Annual Round Table. Linguistics: Developments of the SixtiesViewpoints of the Seventies. Volume 24 of Monograph Series on Language and Linguistics. Georgetown University Press, Washington, D.C., pages 3556.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Frame semantics and the nature of language.</title>
<date>1976</date>
<booktitle>In Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences: Conference on the Origin and Development of Language and Speech, Volume 280,</booktitle>
<pages>2032</pages>
<location>New York</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4346" citStr="Fillmore (1976)" startWordPosition="618" endWordPosition="619">d 2000). Systems for studying mergers and acquisitions use slots like products, relationship, joint venture company, and amount (Hobbs et al. 1997). For natural language understanding tasks to proceed beyond these specific domains, we need semantic frames and semantic understanding systems that do not require a new set of slots for each new application domain. In this article we describe a shallow semantic interpreter based on semantic roles that are less domain specific than to airport or joint venture company. These roles are defined at the level of semantic frames of the type introduced by Fillmore (1976), which describe abstract actions or relationships, along with their participants. For example, the Judgement frame contains roles like judge, evaluee, and reason, and the Statement frame contains roles like speaker, addressee, and message, as the following examples show: (1) [Judge She ] blames [Evaluee the Government ] [Reason for failing to do enough to help ] . (2) [Message Ill knock on your door at quarter to six ] [Speaker Susan] said. These shallow semantic roles could play an important role in information extraction. For example, a semantic role parse would allow a system to realize th</context>
<context position="11816" citStr="Fillmore 1976" startWordPosition="1750" endWordPosition="1751">in the syntactic realization of their arguments, whereas the more specific roles have more often been proposed by computer scientists, who are more concerned with the details of the realization of the arguments of specific verbs. The FrameNet project (Baker, Fillmore, and Lowe 1998) proposes roles that are neither as general as the 10 abstract thematic roles, nor as specific as the thousands of potential verb-specific roles. FrameNet roles are defined for each semantic frame. A frame is a schematic representation of situations involving various participants, props, and other conceptual roles (Fillmore 1976). For example, the frame Conversation, shown in Figure 1, is invoked by the semantically related verbs argue, banter, debate, converse, and gossip, as well as the nouns dispute, discussion, and tiff, and is defined as follows: (7) Two (or more) people talk to one another. No person is construed as only a speaker or only an addressee. Rather, it is understood that both (or all) participants do some speaking and some listening: the process is understood to be symmetrical or reciprocal. The roles defined for this frame, and shared by all its lexical entries, include Protagonist-1 and Protagonist-</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, 1976</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. 1976. Frame semantics and the nature of language. In Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences: Conference on the Origin and Development of Language and Speech, Volume 280, pages 2032. New York Academy of Sciences, New York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Pragmatically controlled zero anaphora.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Berkeley Linguistics Society,</booktitle>
<pages>95107</pages>
<location>Berkeley, California.</location>
<marker>Fillmore, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. 1986. Pragmatically controlled zero anaphora. In Proceedings of Berkeley Linguistics Society, pages 95107, Berkeley, California.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Collin F Baker</author>
</authors>
<title>FrameNet: Frame semantics meets the corpus.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>Poster presentation, 74th Annual Meeting of the Linguistics</booktitle>
<publisher>Society of America.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="14592" citStr="Fillmore and Baker 2000" startWordPosition="2218" endWordPosition="2221">ate frame level helps avoid some of the well-known difficulties of defining a unique small set of universal, abstract thematic roles while also allowing some generalization across the roles of different verbs, nouns, and adjectives, each of which adds semantics to the general frame or highlights a particular aspect of the frame. One way of thinking about traditional abstract thematic roles, such as Agent and Patient, in the context of FrameNet is to conceive them as frame elements defined by abstract frames, such as action and motion, at the top of an inheritance hierarchy of semantic frames (Fillmore and Baker 2000). The examples above illustrate another difference between frame elements and thematic roles as commonly described in the literature. Whereas thematic roles tend to be arguments mainly of verbs, frame elements can be arguments of any predicate, and the FrameNet database thus includes nouns and adjectives as well as verbs. The examples above also illustrate a few of the phenomena that make it hard to identify frame elements automatically. Many of these are caused by the fact that there is not always a direct correspondence between syntax and semantics. Whereas the subject of blame is often the </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, Baker, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. and Collin F. Baker. 2000. FrameNet: Frame semantics meets the corpus. Poster presentation, 74th Annual Meeting of the Linguistics Society of America.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
<author>Thomas Hofmann</author>
</authors>
<title>Probabilistic topic analysis for language modeling. In</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Eurospeech-99,</booktitle>
<pages>21672170</pages>
<location>Budapest.</location>
<marker>Gildea, Hofmann, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Gildea, Daniel and Thomas Hofmann. 1999. Probabilistic topic analysis for language modeling. In Eurospeech-99, pages 21672170, Budapest.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marti Hearst</author>
</authors>
<title>Untangling text data mining.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>310</pages>
<location>College Park, Maryland.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6608" citStr="Hearst 1999" startWordPosition="978" endWordPosition="979">or example, Lapata and Brew (1999) and others have shown that the different syntactic subcategorization frames of a verb such as serve can be used to help disambiguate a particular instance of the word. Adding semantic role subcategorization information to this syntactic information could extend this idea to \x0c247 Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles use richer semantic knowledge. Semantic roles could also act as an important intermediate representation in statistical machine translation or automatic text summarization and in the emerging field of text data mining (TDM) (Hearst 1999). Finally, incorporating semantic roles into probabilistic models of language may eventually yield more accurate parsers and better language models for speech recognition. This article describes an algorithm for identifying the semantic roles filled by constituents in a sentence. We apply statistical techniques that have been successful for the related problems of syntactic parsing, part-of-speech tagging, and word sense disambiguation, including probabilistic parsing and statistical classification. Our statistical algorithms are trained on a hand-labeled data set: the FrameNet database (Baker</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hearst, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Hearst, Marti. 1999. Untangling text data mining. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 310, College Park, Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jerry R Hobbs</author>
<author>Douglas Appelt</author>
<author>John Bear</author>
<author>David Israel</author>
<author>Megumi Kameyama</author>
<author>Mark E Stickel</author>
<author>Mabry Tyson</author>
</authors>
<title>FASTUS: A cascaded finite-state transducer for extracting information from natural-language text.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Emmanuel Roche and Yves Schabes, editors, Finite-State Language Processing.</booktitle>
<pages>383406</pages>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3878" citStr="Hobbs et al. 1997" startWordPosition="540" endWordPosition="543">nguistics Volume 28, Number 3 far away as it once was, thanks to the development of large semantic databases such as WordNet (Fellbaum 1998) and progress in domain-independent machine learning algorithms. Current information extraction and dialogue understanding systems, however, are still based on domain-specific frame-and-slot templates. Systems for booking airplane information use domain-specific frames with slots like orig city, dest city, or depart time (Stallard 2000). Systems for studying mergers and acquisitions use slots like products, relationship, joint venture company, and amount (Hobbs et al. 1997). For natural language understanding tasks to proceed beyond these specific domains, we need semantic frames and semantic understanding systems that do not require a new set of slots for each new application domain. In this article we describe a shallow semantic interpreter based on semantic roles that are less domain specific than to airport or joint venture company. These roles are defined at the level of semantic frames of the type introduced by Fillmore (1976), which describe abstract actions or relationships, along with their participants. For example, the Judgement frame contains roles l</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hobbs, Appelt, Bear, Israel, Kameyama, Stickel, Tyson, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Hobbs, Jerry R., Douglas Appelt, John Bear, David Israel, Megumi Kameyama, Mark E. Stickel, and Mabry Tyson. 1997. FASTUS: A cascaded finite-state transducer for extracting information from natural-language text. In Emmanuel Roche and Yves Schabes, editors, Finite-State Language Processing. MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts, pages 383406.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Thomas Hofmann</author>
<author>Jan Puzicha</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical models for co-occurrence data.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Memorandum, Massachussetts Institute of Technology Artificial Intelligence Laboratory,</journal>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts.</location>
<marker>Hofmann, Puzicha, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Hofmann, Thomas and Jan Puzicha. 1998. Statistical models for co-occurrence data. Memorandum, Massachussetts Institute of Technology Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ray Jackendoff</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic Interpretation in Generative Grammar.</title>
<date>1972</date>
<booktitle>x0c287 Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles</booktitle>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10024" citStr="Jackendoff (1972)" startWordPosition="1499" endWordPosition="1500">main-specific roles such as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient (Van Valin 1993; Dowty 1991). In between lie many theories with approximately 10 roles, such as Fillmores (1971) list of nine: Agent, Experiencer, Instrument, Object, Source, Goal, Location, Time, and Path.1 1 There are scores of other theories with slightly different sets of roles, including those of Fillmore (1968), Jackendoff (1972), and Schank (1972); see Somers (1987) for an excellent summary. \x0c248 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 banterv debatev conversev gossipv disputen discussionn tiffn Conversation Frame: Protagonist1 Protagonist2 Protagonists Topic Medium Frame Elements: arguev Domain: Communication Domain: Cognition Frame: Questioning Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Frame: Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Statement Frame: Frame Elements: Judgment Judge Evaluee Reason Role disputen blamev faultn admirev admirationn disapprovev blamen appreciatev Frame: </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Jackendoff, 1972</marker>
<rawString>Jackendoff, Ray. 1972. Semantic Interpretation in Generative Grammar. MIT Press, \x0c287 Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles Cambridge, Massachusetts.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Frederick Jelinek</author>
<author>Robert L Mercer</author>
</authors>
<title>Interpolated estimation of Markov source parameters from sparse data. In</title>
<date>1980</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings: Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Practice,</booktitle>
<pages>381397</pages>
<location>Amsterdam. North Holland.</location>
<marker>Jelinek, Mercer, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Jelinek, Frederick and Robert L. Mercer. 1980. Interpolated estimation of Markov source parameters from sparse data. In Proceedings: Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Practice, pages 381397. Amsterdam. North Holland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christopher R Johnson</author>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Esther J Wood</author>
<author>Josef Ruppenhofer</author>
<author>Margaret Urban</author>
<author>Miriam R L Petruk</author>
<author>Collin F Baker</author>
</authors>
<title>The FrameNet project: Tools for lexicon building. Version 0.7. Available at http:/ /www.icsi.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<note>berkeley.edu/ framenet/book.html.</note>
<contexts>
<context position="7255" citStr="Johnson et al. 2001" startWordPosition="1067" endWordPosition="1070">mantic roles into probabilistic models of language may eventually yield more accurate parsers and better language models for speech recognition. This article describes an algorithm for identifying the semantic roles filled by constituents in a sentence. We apply statistical techniques that have been successful for the related problems of syntactic parsing, part-of-speech tagging, and word sense disambiguation, including probabilistic parsing and statistical classification. Our statistical algorithms are trained on a hand-labeled data set: the FrameNet database (Baker, Fillmore, and Lowe 1998; Johnson et al. 2001). The FrameNet database defines a tag set of semantic roles called frame elements and included, at the time of our experiments, roughly 50,000 sentences from the British National Corpus hand-labeled with these frame elements. This article presents our system in stages, beginning in Section 2 with a more detailed description of the data and the set of frame elements or semantic roles used. We then introduce (in Section 3) the statistical classification technique used and examine in turn the knowledge sources of which our system makes use. Section 4 describes the basic syntactic and lexical feat</context>
<context position="15682" citStr="Johnson et al. (2001)" startWordPosition="2402" endWordPosition="2405"> the fact that there is not always a direct correspondence between syntax and semantics. Whereas the subject of blame is often the Judge, the direct object of blame can be an Evaluee (e.g., the poor in blaming the poor) or a Reason (e.g., everything in blame everything on coyotes). The identity of the Judge can also be expressed in a genitive pronoun, (e.g., his in his praise) or even an adjective (e.g., critical in critical praise). The corpus used in this project is perhaps best described in terms of the methodology used by the FrameNet team. We outline the process here; for more detail see Johnson et al. (2001). As the first step, semantic frames were defined for the general domains chosen; the frame elements, or semantic roles for participants in a frame, were defined; and a list of target words, or lexical predicates whose meaning includes aspects of the frame, was compiled for each frame. Example sentences were chosen by searching the British National Corpus for instances of each target word. Separate searches were performed for various patterns over lexical items and part-of-speech sequences in the target words context, producing a set of subcorpora for each target word, designed to capture diff</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Johnson, Fillmore, Wood, Ruppenhofer, Urban, Petruk, Baker, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Johnson, Christopher R., Charles J. Fillmore, Esther J. Wood, Josef Ruppenhofer, Margaret Urban, Miriam R. L. Petruk, and Collin F. Baker. 2001. The FrameNet project: Tools for lexicon building. Version 0.7. Available at http:/ /www.icsi. berkeley.edu/ framenet/book.html.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Karin Kipper</author>
<author>Hoa Trang Dang</author>
<author>William Schuler</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>Building a class-based verb lexicon using TAGs.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In TAG+5 Fifth International Workshop on Tree Adjoining Grammars and Related Formalisms,</booktitle>
<location>Paris,</location>
<marker>Kipper, Dang, Schuler, Palmer, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Kipper, Karin, Hoa Trang Dang, William Schuler, and Martha Palmer. 2000. Building a class-based verb lexicon using TAGs. In TAG+5 Fifth International Workshop on Tree Adjoining Grammars and Related Formalisms, Paris, May.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maria Lapata</author>
<author>Chris Brew</author>
</authors>
<title>Using subcategorization to resolve verb class ambiguity.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in NLP and Very Large Corpora,</booktitle>
<pages>266274</pages>
<location>College Park, Maryland.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6030" citStr="Lapata and Brew (1999)" startWordPosition="890" endWordPosition="893">me. Such common frames might allow a question-answering system to take a question like (5) and discover that (6) is relevant in constructing an answer to the question: (5) Which party sent absentee ballots to voters? (6) Both Democratic and Republican voters received absentee ballots from their party. This shallow semantic level of interpretation has additional uses outside of generalizing information extraction, question answering, and semantic dialogue systems. One such application is in word sense disambiguation, where the roles associated with a word can be cues to its sense. For example, Lapata and Brew (1999) and others have shown that the different syntactic subcategorization frames of a verb such as serve can be used to help disambiguate a particular instance of the word. Adding semantic role subcategorization information to this syntactic information could extend this idea to \x0c247 Gildea and Jurafsky Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles use richer semantic knowledge. Semantic roles could also act as an important intermediate representation in statistical machine translation or automatic text summarization and in the emerging field of text data mining (TDM) (Hearst 1999). Finally, incorporati</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lapata, Brew, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Lapata, Maria and Chris Brew. 1999. Using subcategorization to resolve verb class ambiguity. In Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in NLP and Very Large Corpora, pages 266274, College Park, Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Beth Levin</author>
</authors>
<title>English Verb Classes and Alternations: A Preliminary Investigation.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<publisher>University of Chicago Press,</publisher>
<location>Chicago.</location>
<marker>Levin, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Levin, Beth. 1993. English Verb Classes and Alternations: A Preliminary Investigation. University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Beth Levin</author>
<author>Malka Rappaport Hovav</author>
</authors>
<title>From lexical semantics to argument realization.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<note>Unpublished manuscript.</note>
<marker>Levin, Hovav, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Levin, Beth and Malka Rappaport Hovav. 1996. From lexical semantics to argument realization. Unpublished manuscript.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mitchell P Marcus</author>
<author>Grace Kim</author>
<author>Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz</author>
<author>Robert MacIntyre</author>
<author>Ann Bies</author>
<author>Mark Ferguson</author>
<author>Karen Katz</author>
<author>Britta Schasberger</author>
</authors>
<title>The Penn Treebank: Annotating predicate argument structure.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>In ARPA Human Language Technology Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>114119</pages>
<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann,</publisher>
<location>Plainsboro, New Jersey.</location>
<marker>Marcus, Kim, Marcinkiewicz, MacIntyre, Bies, Ferguson, Katz, Schasberger, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Marcus, Mitchell P., Grace Kim, Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz, Robert MacIntyre, Ann Bies, Mark Ferguson, Karen Katz, and Britta Schasberger. 1994. The Penn Treebank: Annotating predicate argument structure. In ARPA Human Language Technology Workshop, pages 114119, Plainsboro, New Jersey. Morgan Kaufmann, San Francisco.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mitchell P Marcus</author>
<author>Beatrice Santorini</author>
<author>Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz</author>
</authors>
<title>Building a large annotated corpus of English: The Penn treebank.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>Marcus, Santorini, Marcinkiewicz, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Marcus, Mitchell P., Beatrice Santorini, and Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz. 1993. Building a large annotated corpus of English: The Penn treebank. Computational Linguistics 19(2):313330.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Diana McCarthy</author>
</authors>
<title>Using semantic preferences to identify verbal participation in role switching alternations.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of the North American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL),</booktitle>
<pages>256263</pages>
<location>Seattle, Washington.</location>
<marker>McCarthy, 2000</marker>
<rawString>McCarthy, Diana. 2000. Using semantic preferences to identify verbal participation in role switching alternations. In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of the North American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL), pages 256263, Seattle, Washington.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Scott Miller</author>
<author>Heidi Fox</author>
<author>Lance Ramshaw</author>
<author>Ralph Weischedel</author>
</authors>
<title>A novel use of statistical parsing to extract information from text.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of the North American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL),</booktitle>
<pages>226233</pages>
<location>Seattle, Washington.</location>
<marker>Miller, Fox, Ramshaw, Weischedel, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Miller, Scott, Heidi Fox, Lance Ramshaw, and Ralph Weischedel. 2000. A novel use of statistical parsing to extract information from text. In Proceedings of the First Annual Meeting of the North American Chapter of the ACL (NAACL), pages 226233, Seattle, Washington.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Scott Miller</author>
<author>David Stallard</author>
<author>Robert Bobrow</author>
<author>Richard Schwartz</author>
</authors>
<title>A fully statistical approach to natural language interfaces.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>5561</pages>
<location>Santa Cruz, California.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="22152" citStr="Miller et al. (1996)" startWordPosition="3374" endWordPosition="3377">s such as Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar (HPSG) (Pollard and Sag 1994), rely on hand-developed grammars that must anticipate each way in which semantic roles may be realized syntactically. Writing such grammars is time consuming, and typically such systems have limited coverage. Data-driven techniques have recently been applied to template-based semantic interpretation in limited domains by shallow systems that avoid complex feature structures and often perform only shallow syntactic analysis. For example, in the context of the Air Traveler Information System (ATIS) for spoken dialogue, Miller et al. (1996) computed the probability that a constituent such as Atlanta filled a semantic slot such as Destination in a semantic frame for air travel. In a data-driven approach to information extraction, Riloff (1993) builds a dictionary of patterns for filling slots in a specific domain such as terrorist attacks, and Riloff and Schmelzenbach (1998) extend this technique to derive automatically entire case frames for words in the domain. These last systems make use of a limited amount of hand labor to accept or reject automatically generated hypotheses. They show promise for a more sophisticated approach</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Miller, Stallard, Bobrow, Schwartz, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Miller, Scott, David Stallard, Robert Bobrow, and Richard Schwartz. 1996. A fully statistical approach to natural language interfaces. In Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 5561, Santa Cruz, California.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Vidya Niwas Misra</author>
</authors>
<title>The Descriptive Technique of Panini.</title>
<date>1966</date>
<publisher>Mouton, The Hague.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="9069" citStr="Misra 1966" startWordPosition="1344" endWordPosition="1345">ge about systematic alternations in verb argument structure with sentence-level features. We combine syntactic parsing and semantic role identification into a single probability model in Section 8. Section 9 addresses the question of generalizing statistics from one target predicate to another, beginning with a look at domain-independent thematic roles in Section 9.1. Finally we draw conclusions and discuss future directions in Section 10. 2. Semantic Roles Semantic roles are one of the oldest classes of constructs in linguistic theory, dating back thousands of years to Paninis karaka theory (Misra 1966; Rocher 1964; Dahiya 1995). Longevity, in this case, begets variety, and the literature records scores of proposals for sets of semantic roles. These sets of roles range from the very specific to the very general, and many have been used in computational implementations of one type or another. At the specific end of the spectrum are domain-specific roles such as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Misra, 1966</marker>
<rawString>Misra, Vidya Niwas. 1966. The Descriptive Technique of Panini. Mouton, The Hague.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fernando Pereira</author>
<author>Naftali Tishby</author>
<author>Lillian Lee</author>
</authors>
<title>Distributional clustering of English words.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 31st Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>183190</pages>
<location>Columbus, Ohio.</location>
<marker>Pereira, Tishby, Lee, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Pereira, Fernando, Naftali Tishby, and Lillian Lee. 1993. Distributional clustering of English words. In Proceedings of the 31st Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 183190, Columbus, Ohio.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Stephen Della Pietra</author>
<author>Vincent Della Pietra</author>
<author>John Lafferty</author>
</authors>
<title>Inducing features of random fields.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>Pietra, Pietra, Lafferty, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Pietra, Stephen Della, Vincent Della Pietra, and John Lafferty. 1997. Inducing features of random fields. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence 19(4):380393.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Carl Pollard</author>
<author>Ivan A Sag</author>
</authors>
<title>Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<publisher>University of Chicago Press,</publisher>
<location>Chicago.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="21608" citStr="Pollard and Sag 1994" startWordPosition="3297" endWordPosition="3300">r, visit Filling annoint, pack Perception Active glance, savour Noise snort, whine Society Leadership emperor, sultan Space Adornment cloak, line Time Duration chronic, short Iteration daily, sporadic Transaction Basic buy, spend Wealthiness broke, well-off 3. Related Work Assignment of semantic roles is an important part of language understanding, and the problem of how to assign such roles has been attacked by many computational systems. Traditional parsing and understanding systems, including implementations of unification-based grammars such as Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar (HPSG) (Pollard and Sag 1994), rely on hand-developed grammars that must anticipate each way in which semantic roles may be realized syntactically. Writing such grammars is time consuming, and typically such systems have limited coverage. Data-driven techniques have recently been applied to template-based semantic interpretation in limited domains by shallow systems that avoid complex feature structures and often perform only shallow syntactic analysis. For example, in the context of the Air Traveler Information System (ATIS) for spoken dialogue, Miller et al. (1996) computed the probability that a constituent such as Atl</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pollard, Sag, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Pollard, Carl and Ivan A. Sag. 1994. Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar. University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Ellen Riloff</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatically constructing a dictionary for information extraction tasks.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 11th National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI),</booktitle>
<pages>811816</pages>
<location>Washington, D.C. Riloff, Ellen</location>
<contexts>
<context position="22358" citStr="Riloff (1993)" startWordPosition="3408" endWordPosition="3409">ars is time consuming, and typically such systems have limited coverage. Data-driven techniques have recently been applied to template-based semantic interpretation in limited domains by shallow systems that avoid complex feature structures and often perform only shallow syntactic analysis. For example, in the context of the Air Traveler Information System (ATIS) for spoken dialogue, Miller et al. (1996) computed the probability that a constituent such as Atlanta filled a semantic slot such as Destination in a semantic frame for air travel. In a data-driven approach to information extraction, Riloff (1993) builds a dictionary of patterns for filling slots in a specific domain such as terrorist attacks, and Riloff and Schmelzenbach (1998) extend this technique to derive automatically entire case frames for words in the domain. These last systems make use of a limited amount of hand labor to accept or reject automatically generated hypotheses. They show promise for a more sophisticated approach to generalizing beyond the relatively small number of frames considered in the tasks. More recently, a domain-independent system has been trained by Blaheta and Charniak (2000) on the function tags, such a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Riloff, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Riloff, Ellen. 1993. Automatically constructing a dictionary for information extraction tasks. In Proceedings of the 11th National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), pages 811816, Washington, D.C. Riloff, Ellen and Mark Schmelzenbach. 1998. An empirical approach to conceptual case frame acquisition. In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora, pages 4956, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Rosane Rocher</author>
</authors>
<title>Agent et Objet chez Panini.</title>
<date>1964</date>
<journal>Journal of the American Oriental Society</journal>
<pages>84--4454</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="9082" citStr="Rocher 1964" startWordPosition="1346" endWordPosition="1347">tematic alternations in verb argument structure with sentence-level features. We combine syntactic parsing and semantic role identification into a single probability model in Section 8. Section 9 addresses the question of generalizing statistics from one target predicate to another, beginning with a look at domain-independent thematic roles in Section 9.1. Finally we draw conclusions and discuss future directions in Section 10. 2. Semantic Roles Semantic roles are one of the oldest classes of constructs in linguistic theory, dating back thousands of years to Paninis karaka theory (Misra 1966; Rocher 1964; Dahiya 1995). Longevity, in this case, begets variety, and the literature records scores of proposals for sets of semantic roles. These sets of roles range from the very specific to the very general, and many have been used in computational implementations of one type or another. At the specific end of the spectrum are domain-specific roles such as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Pat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rocher, 1964</marker>
<rawString>Rocher, Rosane. 1964. Agent et Objet chez Panini. Journal of the American Oriental Society 84:4454.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mats Rooth</author>
</authors>
<title>Two-dimensional clusters in grammatical relations.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In AAAI Symposium on Representation and Acquisition of Lexical Knowledge,</booktitle>
<location>Stanford, California.</location>
<marker>Rooth, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Rooth, Mats. 1995. Two-dimensional clusters in grammatical relations. In AAAI Symposium on Representation and Acquisition of Lexical Knowledge, Stanford, California.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mats Rooth</author>
<author>Stefan Riezler</author>
<author>Detlef Prescher</author>
<author>Glenn Carroll</author>
<author>Franz Beil</author>
</authors>
<title>Inducing a semantically annotated lexicon via EM-based clustering.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>104111</pages>
<location>College Park, Maryland.</location>
<marker>Rooth, Riezler, Prescher, Carroll, Beil, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Rooth, Mats, Stefan Riezler, Detlef Prescher, Glenn Carroll, and Franz Beil. 1999. Inducing a semantically annotated lexicon via EM-based clustering. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 104111, College Park, Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Roger C Schank</author>
</authors>
<title>Conceptual dependency: A theory of natural language understanding.</title>
<date>1972</date>
<journal>Cognitive Psychology</journal>
<pages>3--552631</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10043" citStr="Schank (1972)" startWordPosition="1502" endWordPosition="1503">h as the from airport, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient (Van Valin 1993; Dowty 1991). In between lie many theories with approximately 10 roles, such as Fillmores (1971) list of nine: Agent, Experiencer, Instrument, Object, Source, Goal, Location, Time, and Path.1 1 There are scores of other theories with slightly different sets of roles, including those of Fillmore (1968), Jackendoff (1972), and Schank (1972); see Somers (1987) for an excellent summary. \x0c248 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 banterv debatev conversev gossipv disputen discussionn tiffn Conversation Frame: Protagonist1 Protagonist2 Protagonists Topic Medium Frame Elements: arguev Domain: Communication Domain: Cognition Frame: Questioning Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Frame: Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Statement Frame: Frame Elements: Judgment Judge Evaluee Reason Role disputen blamev faultn admirev admirationn disapprovev blamen appreciatev Frame: Frame Elements: Cat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Schank, 1972</marker>
<rawString>Schank, Roger C. 1972. Conceptual dependency: A theory of natural language understanding. Cognitive Psychology 3:552631.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sidney Siegel</author>
<author>N John Castellan</author>
</authors>
<title>Nonparametric Statistics for the Behavioral Sciences. 2nd ed.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<publisher>McGraw-Hill,</publisher>
<location>New York.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="17762" citStr="Siegel and Castellan 1988" startWordPosition="2727" endWordPosition="2730"> sentences for each target word were checked for consistency. In addition to the tags just mentioned, the annotations include certain other information, which we do not make use of in this work, such as word sense tags for some target words and tags indicating metaphoric usages. Tests of interannotator agreement were performed for data from a small number of predicates before the final consistency check. Interannotator agreement at the sentence level, including all frame element judgments and boundaries for one predicate, varied from .66 to .82 depending on the predicate. The kappa statistic (Siegel and Castellan 1988) varied from .67 to .82. Because of the large number of possible categories when boundary judgments are considered, kappa is nearly identical to the interannotator agreement. The system described in this article (which gets .65/.61 precision/recall on individual frame elements; see Table 15) correctly identifies all frame elements in 38% of test sentences. Although this .38 is not directly comparable to the .66.82 interannotator agreements, its clear that the performance of our system still falls significantly short of human performance on the task. The British National Corpus was chosen as th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Siegel, Castellan, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Siegel, Sidney and N. John Castellan, Jr. 1988. Nonparametric Statistics for the Behavioral Sciences. 2nd ed. McGraw-Hill, New York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Harold L Somers</author>
</authors>
<title>Valency and Case in Computational Linguistics.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<publisher>Edinburgh University Press,</publisher>
<location>Edinburgh, Scotland.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10062" citStr="Somers (1987)" startWordPosition="1505" endWordPosition="1506">rt, to airport, or depart time discussed above, or verb-specific roles such as eater and eaten for the verb eat. The opposite end of the spectrum consists of theories with only two proto-roles or macroroles: Proto-Agent and Proto-Patient (Van Valin 1993; Dowty 1991). In between lie many theories with approximately 10 roles, such as Fillmores (1971) list of nine: Agent, Experiencer, Instrument, Object, Source, Goal, Location, Time, and Path.1 1 There are scores of other theories with slightly different sets of roles, including those of Fillmore (1968), Jackendoff (1972), and Schank (1972); see Somers (1987) for an excellent summary. \x0c248 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 banterv debatev conversev gossipv disputen discussionn tiffn Conversation Frame: Protagonist1 Protagonist2 Protagonists Topic Medium Frame Elements: arguev Domain: Communication Domain: Cognition Frame: Questioning Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Frame: Topic Medium Frame Elements: Speaker Addressee Message Statement Frame: Frame Elements: Judgment Judge Evaluee Reason Role disputen blamev faultn admirev admirationn disapprovev blamen appreciatev Frame: Frame Elements: Categorization Cognize</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Somers, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Somers, Harold L. 1987. Valency and Case in Computational Linguistics. Edinburgh University Press, Edinburgh, Scotland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Stallard</author>
</authors>
<title>Talkntravel: A conversational system for air travel planning.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth \x0c288 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 Applied Natural Language Processing Conference (ANLP00),</booktitle>
<pages>6875</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3738" citStr="Stallard 2000" startWordPosition="522" endWordPosition="523">s of Linguistics and Computer Science, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309. E-mail: jurafsky@colorado.edu \x0c246 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 far away as it once was, thanks to the development of large semantic databases such as WordNet (Fellbaum 1998) and progress in domain-independent machine learning algorithms. Current information extraction and dialogue understanding systems, however, are still based on domain-specific frame-and-slot templates. Systems for booking airplane information use domain-specific frames with slots like orig city, dest city, or depart time (Stallard 2000). Systems for studying mergers and acquisitions use slots like products, relationship, joint venture company, and amount (Hobbs et al. 1997). For natural language understanding tasks to proceed beyond these specific domains, we need semantic frames and semantic understanding systems that do not require a new set of slots for each new application domain. In this article we describe a shallow semantic interpreter based on semantic roles that are less domain specific than to airport or joint venture company. These roles are defined at the level of semantic frames of the type introduced by Fillmor</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Stallard, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Stallard, David. 2000. Talkntravel: A conversational system for air travel planning. In Proceedings of the Sixth \x0c288 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 Applied Natural Language Processing Conference (ANLP00), pages 6875.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Robert D Van Valin</author>
</authors>
<title>A synopsis of role and reference grammar.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>In Robert D.</booktitle>
<marker>Van Valin, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Van Valin, Robert D. 1993. A synopsis of role and reference grammar. In Robert D.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>Advances in Role and Reference Grammar.</booktitle>
<pages>1166</pages>
<editor>Van Valin, editor,</editor>
<publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company,</publisher>
<location>Amsterdam,</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Van Valin, editor, Advances in Role and Reference Grammar. John Benjamins Publishing Company, Amsterdam, pages 1166.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Terry Winograd</author>
</authors>
<title>Understanding natural language. Cognitive Psychology, 3(1). Reprinted as a book by</title>
<date>1972</date>
<pages>0</pages>
<publisher>Academic Press,</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="2812" citStr="Winograd (1972)" startWordPosition="400" endWordPosition="401"> to appear in tasks in which understanding and semantics play a greater role. For example, there has been widespread commercial deployment of simple speech-based natural language understanding systems that answer questions about flight arrival times, give directions, report on bank balances, or perform simple financial transactions. More sophisticated research systems generate concise summaries of news articles, answer fact-based questions, and recognize complex semantic and dialogue structure. But the challenges that lie ahead are still similar to the challenge that the field has faced since Winograd (1972): moving away from carefully hand-crafted, domaindependent systems toward robustness and domain independence. This goal is not as Currently at Institute for Research in Cognitive Science, University of Pennsylvania, 3401 Walnut Street, Suite 400A, Philadelphia, PA 19104. E-mail: dgildea@cis.upenn.edu Departments of Linguistics and Computer Science, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309. E-mail: jurafsky@colorado.edu \x0c246 Computational Linguistics Volume 28, Number 3 far away as it once was, thanks to the development of large semantic databases such as WordNet (Fellbaum 1998) and progres</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Winograd, 1972</marker>
<rawString>Winograd, Terry. 1972. Understanding natural language. Cognitive Psychology, 3(1). Reprinted as a book by Academic Press, 1972. \x0c&amp;apos;</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>