<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000002">
<bodyText confidence="0.886805">
b&amp;apos;Proceedings of the COLING/ACL 2006 Interactive Presentation Sessions, pages 1720,
Sydney, July 2006. c
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.776553" genericHeader="abstract">
2006 Association for Computational Linguistics
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9212095">
An intelligent search engine and GUI-based efficient MEDLINE search
tool based on deep syntactic parsing
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.938595375">
Tomoko Ohta
Yoshimasa Tsuruoka
Jumpei Takeuchi
Jin-Dong Kim
Yusuke Miyao
Akane Yakushiji
Kazuhiro Yoshida
Yuka Tateisi
</figure>
<affiliation confidence="0.908731">
Department of Computer Science, University of Tokyo
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.698125">
Hongo 7-3-1, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-0033 JAPAN
</address>
<keyword confidence="0.5256905">
{okap, yusuke, ninomi, tsuruoka, akane, kmasuda, tj jug,
kyoshida, harasan, jdkim, yucca, tsujii}@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp
</keyword>
<figure confidence="0.8600005">
Takashi Ninomiya
Katsuya Masuda
Tadayoshi Hara
Junichi Tsujii
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880185" genericHeader="keywords">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996629375">
We present a practical HPSG parser for
English, an intelligent search engine to re-
trieve MEDLINE abstracts that represent
biomedical events and an efficient MED-
LINE search tool helping users to find in-
formation about biomedical entities such
as genes, proteins, and the interactions be-
tween them.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998107" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998045578947369">
Recently, biomedical researchers have been fac-
ing the vast repository of research papers, e.g.
MEDLINE. These researchers are eager to search
biomedical correlations such as protein-protein or
gene-disease associations. The use of natural lan-
guage processing technology is expected to re-
duce their burden, and various attempts of infor-
mation extraction using NLP has been being made
(Blaschke and Valencia, 2002; Hao et al., 2005;
Chun et al., 2006). However, the framework of
traditional information retrieval (IR) has difficulty
with the accurate retrieval of such relational con-
cepts. This is because relational concepts are
essentially determined by semantic relations of
words, and keyword-based IR techniques are in-
sufficient to describe such relations precisely.
This paper proposes a practical HPSG parser
for English, Enju, an intelligent search engine for
the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.917636222222222">
Current Affiliation:
School of Informatics, University of Manchester
Knowledge Research Center, Fujitsu Laboratories LTD.
Faculty of Informatics, Kogakuin University
Information Technology Center, University of Tokyo
F-Score
GENIA treebank Penn Treebank
HPSG-PTB 85.10% 87.16%
HPSG-GENIA 86.87% 86.81%
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.871684">
Table 1: Performance for Penn Treebank and the
</tableCaption>
<construct confidence="0.299956">
GENIA corpus
MEDLINE, MEDIE, and a GUI-based efficient
MEDLINE search tool, Info-PubMed.
</construct>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.745957" genericHeader="method">
2 Enju: An English HPSG Parser
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998234782608696">
We developed an English HPSG parser, Enju 1
(Miyao and Tsujii, 2005; Hara et al., 2005; Ni-
nomiya et al., 2005). Table 1 shows the perfor-
mance. The F-score in the table was accuracy
of the predicate-argument relations output by the
parser. A predicate-argument relation is defined
as a tuple h, wh, a, wai, where is the predi-
cate type (e.g., adjective, intransitive verb), wh
is the head word of the predicate, a is the argu-
ment label (MOD, ARG1, ..., ARG4), and wa is
the head word of the argument. Precision/recall
is the ratio of tuples correctly identified by the
parser. The lexicon of the grammar was extracted
from Sections 02-21 of Penn Treebank (39,832
sentences). In the table, HPSG-PTB means that
the statistical model was trained on Penn Tree-
bank. HPSG-GENIA means that the statistical
model was trained on both Penn Treebank and GE-
NIA treebank as described in (Hara et al., 2005).
The GENIA treebank (Tateisi et al., 2005) consists
of 500 abstracts (4,446 sentences) extracted from
MEDLINE.
Figure 1 shows a part of the parse tree and fea-
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.5033305">
1
http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/enju/
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.966667">
17
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.788039">
\x0cFigure 1: Snapshot of Enju
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.7752755">
ture structure for the sentence NASA officials
vowed to land Discovery early Tuesday at one
of three locations after weather conditions forced
them to scrub Mondays scheduled return.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.731849" genericHeader="method">
3 MEDIE: a search engine for
MEDLINE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99252">
Figure 2 shows the top page of the MEDIE. ME-
DIE is an intelligent search engine for the accu-
rate retrieval of relational concepts from MED-
LINE 2 (Miyao et al., 2006). Prior to retrieval, all
sentences are annotated with predicate argument
structures and ontological identifiers by applying
Enju and a term recognizer.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999384">
3.1 Automatically Annotated Corpus
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997931538461538">
First, we applied a POS analyzer and then Enju.
The POS analyzer and HPSG parser are trained
by using the GENIA corpus (Tsuruoka et al.,
2005; Hara et al., 2005), which comprises around
2,000 MEDLINE abstracts annotated with POS
and Penn Treebank style syntactic parse trees
(Tateisi et al., 2005). The HPSG parser generates
parse trees in a stand-off format that can be con-
verted to XML by combining it with the original
text.
We also annotated technical terms of genes and
diseases in our developed corpus. Technical terms
are annotated simply by exact matching of dictio-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.734176">
2
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.962739285714286">
http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/medie/
nary entries and the terms separated by space, tab,
period, comma, hat, colon, semi-colon, brackets,
square brackets and slash in MEDLINE.
The entire dictionary was generated by apply-
ing the automatic generation method of name vari-
ations (Tsuruoka and Tsujii, 2004) to the GENA
dictionary for the gene names (Koike and Takagi,
2004) and the UMLS (Unified Medical Language
System) meta-thesaurus for the disease names
(Lindberg et al., 1993). It was generated by ap-
plying the name-variation generation method, and
we obtained 4,467,855 entries of a gene and dis-
ease dictionary.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999281">
3.2 Functions of MEDIE
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999281689655172">
MEDIE provides three types of search, seman-
tic search, keyword search, GCL search. GCL
search provides us the most fundamental and pow-
erful functions in which users can specify the
boolean relations, linear order relation and struc-
tural relations with variables. Trained users can
enjoy all functions in MEDIE by the GCL search,
but it is not easy for general users to write ap-
propriate queries for the parsed corpus. The se-
mantic search enables us to specify an event verb
with its subject and object easily. MEDIE auto-
matically generates the GCL query from the se-
mantic query, and runs the GCL search. Figure 3
shows the output of semantic search for the query
What disease does dystrophin cause?. This ex-
ample will give us the most intuitive understand-
ings of the proximal and structural retrieval with a
richly annotated parsed corpus. MEDIE retrieves
sentences which include event verbs of cause
and noun dystrophin such that dystrophin is the
subject of the event verbs. The event verb and its
subject and object are highlighted with designated
colors. As seen in the figure, small sentences in
relative clauses, passive forms or coordination are
retrieved. As the objects of the event verbs are
highlighted, we can easily see what disease dys-
trophin caused. As the target corpus is already
annotated with diseases entities, MEDIE can ef-
ficiently retrieve the disease expressions.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.926251" genericHeader="method">
4 Info-PubMed: a GUI-based
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.88441875">
MEDLINE search tool
Info-PubMed is a MEDLINE search tool with
GUI, helping users to find information about
biomedical entities such as genes, proteins, and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997622">
18
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.968280666666667">
\x0cFigure 2: Snapshot of MEDIE: top page
Figure 3: Snapshot of MEDIE: What disease does
dystrophin cause?
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9301874">
the interactions between them 3.
Info-PubMed provides information from MED-
LINE on protein-protein interactions. Given the
name of a gene or protein, it shows a list of the
names of other genes/proteins which co-occur in
sentences from MEDLINE, along with the fre-
quency of co-occurrence.
Co-occurrence of two proteins/genes in the
same sentence does not always imply that they in-
teract. For more accurate extraction of sentences
that indicate interactions, it is necessary to iden-
tify relations between the two substances. We
adopted PASs derived by Enju and constructed ex-
traction patterns on specific verbs and their argu-
ments based on the derived PASs (Yakusiji, 2006).
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999992666666667">
Figure 4: Snapshot of Info-PubMed (1)
Figure 5: Snapshot of Info-PubMed (2)
Figure 6: Snapshot of Info-PubMed (3)
</figureCaption>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998595">
4.1 Functions of Info-PubMed
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9882725">
In the Gene Searcher window, enter the name
of a gene or protein that you are interested in.
For example, if you are interested in Raf1, type
raf1 in the Gene Searcher (Figure 4). You
will see a list of genes whose description in our
dictionary contains raf1 (Figure 5). Then, drag
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.792381">
3
</page>
<footnote confidence="0.518015">
http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/info-pubmed/
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.996225">
19
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99832155">
\x0cone of the GeneBoxes from the Gene Searcher
to the Interaction Viewer. You will see a list
of genes/proteins which co-occur in the same
sentences, along with co-occurrence frequency.
The GeneBox in the leftmost column is the one
you have moved to Interaction Viewer. The
GeneBoxes in the second column correspond to
gene/proteins which co-occur in the same sen-
tences, followed by the boxes in the third column,
InteractionBoxes.
Drag an InteractionBox to ContentViewer to
see the content of the box (Figure 6). An In-
teractionBox is a set of SentenceBoxes. A Sen-
tenceBox corresponds to a sentence in MEDLINE
in which the two gene/proteins co-occur. A Sen-
tenceBox indicates whether the co-occurrence in
the sentence is direct evidence of interaction or
not. If it is judged as direct evidence of interac-
tion, it is indicated as Interaction. Otherwise, it is
indicated as Co-occurrence.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994364" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9982365">
We presented an English HPSG parser, Enju, a
search engine for relational concepts from MED-
LINE, MEDIE, and a GUI-based MEDLINE
search tool, Info-PubMed.
MEDIE and Info-PubMed demonstrate how the
results of deep parsing can be used for intelligent
text mining and semantic information retrieval in
the biomedical domain.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996951" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
6 Acknowledgment
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.915419">
This work was partially supported by Grant-in-Aid
for Scientific Research on Priority Areas Sys-
tems Genomics (MEXT, Japan) and Solution-
Oriented Research for Science and Technology
(JST, Japan).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.95517" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.928200285714286">
C. Blaschke and A. Valencia. 2002. The frame-based
module of the SUISEKI information extraction sys-
tem. IEEE Intelligent Systems, 17(2):1420.
Y. Hao, X. Zhu, M. Huang, and M. Li. 2005. Dis-
covering patterns to extract protein-protein interac-
tions from the literature: Part II. Bioinformatics,
21(15):32943300.
H.-W. Chun, Y. Tsuruoka, J.-D. Kim, R. Shiba, N. Na-
gata, T. Hishiki, and J. Tsujii. 2006. Extraction
of gene-disease relations from MedLine using do-
main dictionaries and machine learning. In Proc.
PSB 2006, pages 415.
Carl Pollard and Ivan A. Sag. 1994. Head-Driven
Phrase Structure Grammar. University of Chicago
Press.
Yusuke Miyao and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Probabilis-
tic disambiguation models for wide-coverage HPSG
parsing. In Proc. of ACL05, pages 8390.
Tadayoshi Hara, Yusuke Miyao, and Junichi Tsu-
jii. 2005. Adapting a probabilistic disambiguation
model of an HPSG parser to a new domain. In Proc.
of IJCNLP 2005.
Takashi Ninomiya, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka, Yusuke
Miyao, and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Efficacy of beam
thresholding, unification filtering and hybrid parsing
in probabilistic HPSG parsing. In Proc. of IWPT
2005, pages 103114.
Yuka Tateisi, Akane Yakushiji, Tomoko Ohta, and
Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Syntax Annotation for the
GENIA corpus. In Proc. of the IJCNLP 2005, Com-
panion volume, pp. 222227.
Yusuke Miyao, Tomoko Ohta, Katsuya Masuda, Yoshi-
masa Tsuruoka, Kazuhiro Yoshida, Takashi Ni-
nomiya and Junichi Tsujii. 2006. Semantic Re-
trieval for the Accurate Identification of Relational
Concepts in Massive Textbases. In Proc. of ACL 06,
to appear.
Yoshimasa Tsuruoka, Yuka Tateisi, Jin-Dong Kim,
Tomoko Ohta, John McNaught, Sophia Ananiadou,
and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Part-of-speech tagger for
biomedical text. In Proc. of the 10th Panhellenic
Conference on Informatics.
Y. Tsuruoka and J. Tsujii. 2004. Improving the per-
formance of dictionary-based approaches in protein
name recognition. Journal of Biomedical Informat-
ics, 37(6):461470.
Asako Koike and Toshihisa Takagi. 2004.
Gene/protein/family name recognition in biomed-
ical literature. In Proc. of HLT-NAACL 2004
Workshop: Biolink 2004, pages 916.
D.A. Lindberg, B.L. Humphreys, and A.T. McCray.
1993. The unified medical language system. Meth-
ods in Inf. Med., 32(4):281291.
Akane Yakushiji. 2006. Relation Information Extrac-
tion Using Deep Syntactic Analysis. Ph.D. Thesis,
University of Tokyo.
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.427058">
20
\x0c&amp;apos;
</figure>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.053776">
<note confidence="0.899596666666667">b&amp;apos;Proceedings of the COLING/ACL 2006 Interactive Presentation Sessions, pages 1720, Sydney, July 2006. c 2006 Association for Computational Linguistics</note>
<title confidence="0.72226">An intelligent search engine and GUI-based efficient MEDLINE search tool based on deep syntactic parsing</title>
<author confidence="0.842456375">Tomoko Ohta Yoshimasa Tsuruoka Jumpei Takeuchi Jin-Dong Kim Yusuke Miyao Akane Yakushiji Kazuhiro Yoshida Yuka Tateisi</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.99995">Department of Computer Science, University of Tokyo</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.956382">Hongo 7-3-1, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-0033 JAPAN</address>
<email confidence="0.772839">okap@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">yusuke@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">ninomi@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">tsuruoka@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">akane@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">kmasuda@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">tjjug@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">kyoshida@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">harasan@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">jdkim@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">yucca@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<email confidence="0.772839">tsujii@is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
<author confidence="0.900605">Takashi Ninomiya Katsuya Masuda Tadayoshi Hara Junichi Tsujii</author>
<abstract confidence="0.997856777777778">We present a practical HPSG parser for English, an intelligent search engine to retrieve MEDLINE abstracts that represent biomedical events and an efficient MED- LINE search tool helping users to find information about biomedical entities such as genes, proteins, and the interactions between them.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Blaschke</author>
<author>A Valencia</author>
</authors>
<title>The frame-based module of the SUISEKI information extraction system.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>IEEE Intelligent Systems,</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="1384" citStr="Blaschke and Valencia, 2002" startWordPosition="191" endWordPosition="194"> abstracts that represent biomedical events and an efficient MEDLINE search tool helping users to find information about biomedical entities such as genes, proteins, and the interactions between them. 1 Introduction Recently, biomedical researchers have been facing the vast repository of research papers, e.g. MEDLINE. These researchers are eager to search biomedical correlations such as protein-protein or gene-disease associations. The use of natural language processing technology is expected to reduce their burden, and various attempts of information extraction using NLP has been being made (Blaschke and Valencia, 2002; Hao et al., 2005; Chun et al., 2006). However, the framework of traditional information retrieval (IR) has difficulty with the accurate retrieval of such relational concepts. This is because relational concepts are essentially determined by semantic relations of words, and keyword-based IR techniques are insufficient to describe such relations precisely. This paper proposes a practical HPSG parser for English, Enju, an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from Current Affiliation: School of Informatics, University of Manchester Knowledge Research Center</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Blaschke, Valencia, 2002</marker>
<rawString>C. Blaschke and A. Valencia. 2002. The frame-based module of the SUISEKI information extraction system. IEEE Intelligent Systems, 17(2):1420.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Hao</author>
<author>X Zhu</author>
<author>M Huang</author>
<author>M Li</author>
</authors>
<title>Discovering patterns to extract protein-protein interactions from the literature: Part II.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>Bioinformatics,</journal>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>15</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="1402" citStr="Hao et al., 2005" startWordPosition="195" endWordPosition="198">medical events and an efficient MEDLINE search tool helping users to find information about biomedical entities such as genes, proteins, and the interactions between them. 1 Introduction Recently, biomedical researchers have been facing the vast repository of research papers, e.g. MEDLINE. These researchers are eager to search biomedical correlations such as protein-protein or gene-disease associations. The use of natural language processing technology is expected to reduce their burden, and various attempts of information extraction using NLP has been being made (Blaschke and Valencia, 2002; Hao et al., 2005; Chun et al., 2006). However, the framework of traditional information retrieval (IR) has difficulty with the accurate retrieval of such relational concepts. This is because relational concepts are essentially determined by semantic relations of words, and keyword-based IR techniques are insufficient to describe such relations precisely. This paper proposes a practical HPSG parser for English, Enju, an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from Current Affiliation: School of Informatics, University of Manchester Knowledge Research Center, Fujitsu Laborato</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hao, Zhu, Huang, Li, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Y. Hao, X. Zhu, M. Huang, and M. Li. 2005. Discovering patterns to extract protein-protein interactions from the literature: Part II. Bioinformatics, 21(15):32943300.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H-W Chun</author>
<author>Y Tsuruoka</author>
<author>J-D Kim</author>
<author>R Shiba</author>
<author>N Nagata</author>
<author>T Hishiki</author>
<author>J Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Extraction of gene-disease relations from MedLine using domain dictionaries and machine learning.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proc.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="1422" citStr="Chun et al., 2006" startWordPosition="199" endWordPosition="202"> an efficient MEDLINE search tool helping users to find information about biomedical entities such as genes, proteins, and the interactions between them. 1 Introduction Recently, biomedical researchers have been facing the vast repository of research papers, e.g. MEDLINE. These researchers are eager to search biomedical correlations such as protein-protein or gene-disease associations. The use of natural language processing technology is expected to reduce their burden, and various attempts of information extraction using NLP has been being made (Blaschke and Valencia, 2002; Hao et al., 2005; Chun et al., 2006). However, the framework of traditional information retrieval (IR) has difficulty with the accurate retrieval of such relational concepts. This is because relational concepts are essentially determined by semantic relations of words, and keyword-based IR techniques are insufficient to describe such relations precisely. This paper proposes a practical HPSG parser for English, Enju, an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from Current Affiliation: School of Informatics, University of Manchester Knowledge Research Center, Fujitsu Laboratories LTD. Faculty of</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chun, Tsuruoka, Kim, Shiba, Nagata, Hishiki, Tsujii, 2006</marker>
<rawString>H.-W. Chun, Y. Tsuruoka, J.-D. Kim, R. Shiba, N. Nagata, T. Hishiki, and J. Tsujii. 2006. Extraction of gene-disease relations from MedLine using domain dictionaries and machine learning. In Proc.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>PSB</author>
</authors>
<date>2006</date>
<pages>415</pages>
<marker>PSB, 2006</marker>
<rawString>PSB 2006, pages 415.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Carl Pollard</author>
<author>Ivan A Sag</author>
</authors>
<title>Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
<marker>Pollard, Sag, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Carl Pollard and Ivan A. Sag. 1994. Head-Driven Phrase Structure Grammar. University of Chicago Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yusuke Miyao</author>
<author>Junichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Probabilistic disambiguation models for wide-coverage HPSG parsing.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of ACL05,</booktitle>
<pages>8390</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2426" citStr="Miyao and Tsujii, 2005" startWordPosition="339" endWordPosition="342">, an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from Current Affiliation: School of Informatics, University of Manchester Knowledge Research Center, Fujitsu Laboratories LTD. Faculty of Informatics, Kogakuin University Information Technology Center, University of Tokyo F-Score GENIA treebank Penn Treebank HPSG-PTB 85.10% 87.16% HPSG-GENIA 86.87% 86.81% Table 1: Performance for Penn Treebank and the GENIA corpus MEDLINE, MEDIE, and a GUI-based efficient MEDLINE search tool, Info-PubMed. 2 Enju: An English HPSG Parser We developed an English HPSG parser, Enju 1 (Miyao and Tsujii, 2005; Hara et al., 2005; Ninomiya et al., 2005). Table 1 shows the performance. The F-score in the table was accuracy of the predicate-argument relations output by the parser. A predicate-argument relation is defined as a tuple h, wh, a, wai, where is the predicate type (e.g., adjective, intransitive verb), wh is the head word of the predicate, a is the argument label (MOD, ARG1, ..., ARG4), and wa is the head word of the argument. Precision/recall is the ratio of tuples correctly identified by the parser. The lexicon of the grammar was extracted from Sections 02-21 of Penn Treebank (39,832 senten</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Miyao, Tsujii, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Yusuke Miyao and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Probabilistic disambiguation models for wide-coverage HPSG parsing. In Proc. of ACL05, pages 8390.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Tadayoshi Hara</author>
<author>Yusuke Miyao</author>
<author>Junichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Adapting a probabilistic disambiguation model of an HPSG parser to a new domain.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="2445" citStr="Hara et al., 2005" startWordPosition="343" endWordPosition="346">engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from Current Affiliation: School of Informatics, University of Manchester Knowledge Research Center, Fujitsu Laboratories LTD. Faculty of Informatics, Kogakuin University Information Technology Center, University of Tokyo F-Score GENIA treebank Penn Treebank HPSG-PTB 85.10% 87.16% HPSG-GENIA 86.87% 86.81% Table 1: Performance for Penn Treebank and the GENIA corpus MEDLINE, MEDIE, and a GUI-based efficient MEDLINE search tool, Info-PubMed. 2 Enju: An English HPSG Parser We developed an English HPSG parser, Enju 1 (Miyao and Tsujii, 2005; Hara et al., 2005; Ninomiya et al., 2005). Table 1 shows the performance. The F-score in the table was accuracy of the predicate-argument relations output by the parser. A predicate-argument relation is defined as a tuple h, wh, a, wai, where is the predicate type (e.g., adjective, intransitive verb), wh is the head word of the predicate, a is the argument label (MOD, ARG1, ..., ARG4), and wa is the head word of the argument. Precision/recall is the ratio of tuples correctly identified by the parser. The lexicon of the grammar was extracted from Sections 02-21 of Penn Treebank (39,832 sentences). In the table,</context>
<context position="4222" citStr="Hara et al., 2005" startWordPosition="639" endWordPosition="642"> weather conditions forced them to scrub Mondays scheduled return. 3 MEDIE: a search engine for MEDLINE Figure 2 shows the top page of the MEDIE. MEDIE is an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from MEDLINE 2 (Miyao et al., 2006). Prior to retrieval, all sentences are annotated with predicate argument structures and ontological identifiers by applying Enju and a term recognizer. 3.1 Automatically Annotated Corpus First, we applied a POS analyzer and then Enju. The POS analyzer and HPSG parser are trained by using the GENIA corpus (Tsuruoka et al., 2005; Hara et al., 2005), which comprises around 2,000 MEDLINE abstracts annotated with POS and Penn Treebank style syntactic parse trees (Tateisi et al., 2005). The HPSG parser generates parse trees in a stand-off format that can be converted to XML by combining it with the original text. We also annotated technical terms of genes and diseases in our developed corpus. Technical terms are annotated simply by exact matching of dictio2 http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/medie/ nary entries and the terms separated by space, tab, period, comma, hat, colon, semi-colon, brackets, square brackets and slash in MEDLINE. The</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hara, Miyao, Tsujii, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Tadayoshi Hara, Yusuke Miyao, and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Adapting a probabilistic disambiguation model of an HPSG parser to a new domain. In Proc.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<date>2005</date>
<institution>of IJCNLP</institution>
<marker>2005</marker>
<rawString>of IJCNLP 2005.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Takashi Ninomiya</author>
<author>Yoshimasa Tsuruoka</author>
<author>Yusuke Miyao</author>
<author>Junichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Efficacy of beam thresholding, unification filtering and hybrid parsing in probabilistic HPSG parsing.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of IWPT</booktitle>
<pages>103114</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2469" citStr="Ninomiya et al., 2005" startWordPosition="347" endWordPosition="351">rate retrieval of relational concepts from Current Affiliation: School of Informatics, University of Manchester Knowledge Research Center, Fujitsu Laboratories LTD. Faculty of Informatics, Kogakuin University Information Technology Center, University of Tokyo F-Score GENIA treebank Penn Treebank HPSG-PTB 85.10% 87.16% HPSG-GENIA 86.87% 86.81% Table 1: Performance for Penn Treebank and the GENIA corpus MEDLINE, MEDIE, and a GUI-based efficient MEDLINE search tool, Info-PubMed. 2 Enju: An English HPSG Parser We developed an English HPSG parser, Enju 1 (Miyao and Tsujii, 2005; Hara et al., 2005; Ninomiya et al., 2005). Table 1 shows the performance. The F-score in the table was accuracy of the predicate-argument relations output by the parser. A predicate-argument relation is defined as a tuple h, wh, a, wai, where is the predicate type (e.g., adjective, intransitive verb), wh is the head word of the predicate, a is the argument label (MOD, ARG1, ..., ARG4), and wa is the head word of the argument. Precision/recall is the ratio of tuples correctly identified by the parser. The lexicon of the grammar was extracted from Sections 02-21 of Penn Treebank (39,832 sentences). In the table, HPSG-PTB means that the</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ninomiya, Tsuruoka, Miyao, Tsujii, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Takashi Ninomiya, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka, Yusuke Miyao, and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Efficacy of beam thresholding, unification filtering and hybrid parsing in probabilistic HPSG parsing. In Proc. of IWPT 2005, pages 103114.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yuka Tateisi</author>
<author>Akane Yakushiji</author>
<author>Tomoko Ohta</author>
<author>Junichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntax Annotation for the GENIA corpus.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the IJCNLP 2005, Companion volume,</booktitle>
<pages>222227</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3293" citStr="Tateisi et al., 2005" startWordPosition="489" endWordPosition="492">s the predicate type (e.g., adjective, intransitive verb), wh is the head word of the predicate, a is the argument label (MOD, ARG1, ..., ARG4), and wa is the head word of the argument. Precision/recall is the ratio of tuples correctly identified by the parser. The lexicon of the grammar was extracted from Sections 02-21 of Penn Treebank (39,832 sentences). In the table, HPSG-PTB means that the statistical model was trained on Penn Treebank. HPSG-GENIA means that the statistical model was trained on both Penn Treebank and GENIA treebank as described in (Hara et al., 2005). The GENIA treebank (Tateisi et al., 2005) consists of 500 abstracts (4,446 sentences) extracted from MEDLINE. Figure 1 shows a part of the parse tree and fea1 http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/enju/ 17 \x0cFigure 1: Snapshot of Enju ture structure for the sentence NASA officials vowed to land Discovery early Tuesday at one of three locations after weather conditions forced them to scrub Mondays scheduled return. 3 MEDIE: a search engine for MEDLINE Figure 2 shows the top page of the MEDIE. MEDIE is an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from MEDLINE 2 (Miyao et al., 2006). Prior to retrieval</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tateisi, Yakushiji, Ohta, Tsujii, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Yuka Tateisi, Akane Yakushiji, Tomoko Ohta, and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Syntax Annotation for the GENIA corpus. In Proc. of the IJCNLP 2005, Companion volume, pp. 222227.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yusuke Miyao</author>
</authors>
<title>Tomoko Ohta, Katsuya Masuda, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka, Kazuhiro Yoshida, Takashi Ninomiya and Junichi Tsujii.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of ACL 06,</booktitle>
<note>to appear.</note>
<marker>Miyao, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Yusuke Miyao, Tomoko Ohta, Katsuya Masuda, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka, Kazuhiro Yoshida, Takashi Ninomiya and Junichi Tsujii. 2006. Semantic Retrieval for the Accurate Identification of Relational Concepts in Massive Textbases. In Proc. of ACL 06, to appear.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yoshimasa Tsuruoka</author>
<author>Yuka Tateisi</author>
<author>Jin-Dong Kim</author>
<author>Tomoko Ohta</author>
<author>John McNaught</author>
<author>Sophia Ananiadou</author>
<author>Junichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Part-of-speech tagger for biomedical text.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 10th Panhellenic Conference on Informatics.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="4202" citStr="Tsuruoka et al., 2005" startWordPosition="635" endWordPosition="638">f three locations after weather conditions forced them to scrub Mondays scheduled return. 3 MEDIE: a search engine for MEDLINE Figure 2 shows the top page of the MEDIE. MEDIE is an intelligent search engine for the accurate retrieval of relational concepts from MEDLINE 2 (Miyao et al., 2006). Prior to retrieval, all sentences are annotated with predicate argument structures and ontological identifiers by applying Enju and a term recognizer. 3.1 Automatically Annotated Corpus First, we applied a POS analyzer and then Enju. The POS analyzer and HPSG parser are trained by using the GENIA corpus (Tsuruoka et al., 2005; Hara et al., 2005), which comprises around 2,000 MEDLINE abstracts annotated with POS and Penn Treebank style syntactic parse trees (Tateisi et al., 2005). The HPSG parser generates parse trees in a stand-off format that can be converted to XML by combining it with the original text. We also annotated technical terms of genes and diseases in our developed corpus. Technical terms are annotated simply by exact matching of dictio2 http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/medie/ nary entries and the terms separated by space, tab, period, comma, hat, colon, semi-colon, brackets, square brackets and s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tsuruoka, Tateisi, Kim, Ohta, McNaught, Ananiadou, Tsujii, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Yoshimasa Tsuruoka, Yuka Tateisi, Jin-Dong Kim, Tomoko Ohta, John McNaught, Sophia Ananiadou, and Junichi Tsujii. 2005. Part-of-speech tagger for biomedical text. In Proc. of the 10th Panhellenic Conference on Informatics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Tsuruoka</author>
<author>J Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Improving the performance of dictionary-based approaches in protein name recognition.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<journal>Journal of Biomedical Informatics,</journal>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="4945" citStr="Tsuruoka and Tsujii, 2004" startWordPosition="749" endWordPosition="752">ctic parse trees (Tateisi et al., 2005). The HPSG parser generates parse trees in a stand-off format that can be converted to XML by combining it with the original text. We also annotated technical terms of genes and diseases in our developed corpus. Technical terms are annotated simply by exact matching of dictio2 http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/medie/ nary entries and the terms separated by space, tab, period, comma, hat, colon, semi-colon, brackets, square brackets and slash in MEDLINE. The entire dictionary was generated by applying the automatic generation method of name variations (Tsuruoka and Tsujii, 2004) to the GENA dictionary for the gene names (Koike and Takagi, 2004) and the UMLS (Unified Medical Language System) meta-thesaurus for the disease names (Lindberg et al., 1993). It was generated by applying the name-variation generation method, and we obtained 4,467,855 entries of a gene and disease dictionary. 3.2 Functions of MEDIE MEDIE provides three types of search, semantic search, keyword search, GCL search. GCL search provides us the most fundamental and powerful functions in which users can specify the boolean relations, linear order relation and structural relations with variables. Tr</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tsuruoka, Tsujii, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Y. Tsuruoka and J. Tsujii. 2004. Improving the performance of dictionary-based approaches in protein name recognition. Journal of Biomedical Informatics, 37(6):461470.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Asako Koike</author>
<author>Toshihisa Takagi</author>
</authors>
<date>2004</date>
<contexts>
<context position="5012" citStr="Koike and Takagi, 2004" startWordPosition="761" endWordPosition="764">se trees in a stand-off format that can be converted to XML by combining it with the original text. We also annotated technical terms of genes and diseases in our developed corpus. Technical terms are annotated simply by exact matching of dictio2 http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/medie/ nary entries and the terms separated by space, tab, period, comma, hat, colon, semi-colon, brackets, square brackets and slash in MEDLINE. The entire dictionary was generated by applying the automatic generation method of name variations (Tsuruoka and Tsujii, 2004) to the GENA dictionary for the gene names (Koike and Takagi, 2004) and the UMLS (Unified Medical Language System) meta-thesaurus for the disease names (Lindberg et al., 1993). It was generated by applying the name-variation generation method, and we obtained 4,467,855 entries of a gene and disease dictionary. 3.2 Functions of MEDIE MEDIE provides three types of search, semantic search, keyword search, GCL search. GCL search provides us the most fundamental and powerful functions in which users can specify the boolean relations, linear order relation and structural relations with variables. Trained users can enjoy all functions in MEDIE by the GCL search, but</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Koike, Takagi, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Asako Koike and Toshihisa Takagi. 2004.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Gene/protein/family name recognition in biomedical literature.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of HLT-NAACL</booktitle>
<pages>916</pages>
<marker>2004</marker>
<rawString>Gene/protein/family name recognition in biomedical literature. In Proc. of HLT-NAACL 2004 Workshop: Biolink 2004, pages 916.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D A Lindberg</author>
<author>B L Humphreys</author>
<author>A T McCray</author>
</authors>
<title>The unified medical language system.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>Methods in Inf. Med.,</booktitle>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="5120" citStr="Lindberg et al., 1993" startWordPosition="777" endWordPosition="780">nnotated technical terms of genes and diseases in our developed corpus. Technical terms are annotated simply by exact matching of dictio2 http://www-tsujii.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/medie/ nary entries and the terms separated by space, tab, period, comma, hat, colon, semi-colon, brackets, square brackets and slash in MEDLINE. The entire dictionary was generated by applying the automatic generation method of name variations (Tsuruoka and Tsujii, 2004) to the GENA dictionary for the gene names (Koike and Takagi, 2004) and the UMLS (Unified Medical Language System) meta-thesaurus for the disease names (Lindberg et al., 1993). It was generated by applying the name-variation generation method, and we obtained 4,467,855 entries of a gene and disease dictionary. 3.2 Functions of MEDIE MEDIE provides three types of search, semantic search, keyword search, GCL search. GCL search provides us the most fundamental and powerful functions in which users can specify the boolean relations, linear order relation and structural relations with variables. Trained users can enjoy all functions in MEDIE by the GCL search, but it is not easy for general users to write appropriate queries for the parsed corpus. The semantic search en</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lindberg, Humphreys, McCray, 1993</marker>
<rawString>D.A. Lindberg, B.L. Humphreys, and A.T. McCray. 1993. The unified medical language system. Methods in Inf. Med., 32(4):281291.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Akane Yakushiji</author>
</authors>
<title>Relation Information Extraction Using Deep Syntactic Analysis.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<tech>Ph.D. Thesis,</tech>
<institution>University of Tokyo.</institution>
<marker>Yakushiji, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Akane Yakushiji. 2006. Relation Information Extraction Using Deep Syntactic Analysis. Ph.D. Thesis, University of Tokyo.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>