<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000006">
<bodyText confidence="0.7618905">
b&apos;Proceedings of the 21st International Conference on Computational Linguistics and 44th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 337344,
Sydney, July 2006. c
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527564" genericHeader="abstract">
2006 Association for Computational Linguistics
</sectionHeader>
<title confidence="0.973156">
Reranking and Self-Training for Parser Adaptation
</title>
<author confidence="0.996146">
David McClosky, Eugene Charniak, and Mark Johnson
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.936675">
Brown Laboratory for Linguistic Information Processing (BLLIP)
Brown University
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.976097">
Providence, RI 02912
</address>
<email confidence="0.998568">
{dmcc|ec|mj}@cs.brown.edu
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990283" genericHeader="keywords">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993997185185185">
Statistical parsers trained and tested on the
Penn Wall Street Journal (WSJ) treebank
have shown vast improvements over the
last 10 years. Much of this improvement,
however, is based upon an ever-increasing
number of features to be trained on (typi-
cally) the WSJ treebank data. This has led
to concern that such parsers may be too
finely tuned to this corpus at the expense
of portability to other genres. Such wor-
ries have merit. The standard Charniak
parser checks in at a labeled precision-
recall f-measure of 89.7% on the Penn
WSJ test set, but only 82.9% on the test set
from the Brown treebank corpus.
This paper should allay these fears. In par-
ticular, we show that the reranking parser
described in Charniak and Johnson (2005)
improves performance of the parser on
Brown to 85.2%. Furthermore, use of the
self-training techniques described in (Mc-
Closky et al., 2006) raise this to 87.8%
(an error reduction of 28%) again with-
out any use of labeled Brown data. This
is remarkable since training the parser and
reranker on labeled Brown data achieves
only 88.4%.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997783" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999495977272727">
Modern statistical parsers require treebanks to
train their parameters, but their performance de-
clines when one parses genres more distant from
the training datas domain. Furthermore, the tree-
banks required to train said parsers are expensive
and difficult to produce.
Naturally, one of the goals of statistical parsing
is to produce a broad-coverage parser which is rel-
atively insensitive to textual domain. But the lack
of corpora has led to a situation where much of
the current work on parsing is performed on a sin-
gle domain using training data from that domain
the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) section of the
Penn Treebank (Marcus et al., 1993). Given the
aforementioned costs, it is unlikely that many sig-
nificant treebanks will be created for new genres.
Thus, parser adaptation attempts to leverage ex-
isting labeled data from one domain and create a
parser capable of parsing a different domain.
Unfortunately, the state of the art in parser
portability (i.e. using a parser trained on one do-
main to parse a different domain) is not good. The
Charniak parser has a labeled precision-recall
f-measure of 89.7% on WSJ but a lowly 82.9%
on the test set from the Brown corpus treebank.
Furthermore, the treebanked Brown data is mostly
general non-fiction and much closer to WSJ than,
e.g., medical corpora would be. Thus, most work
on parser adaptation resorts to using some labeled
in-domain data to fortify the larger quantity of out-
of-domain data.
In this paper, we present some encouraging re-
sults on parser adaptation without any in-domain
data. (Though we also present results with in-
domain data as a reference point.) In particular we
note the effects of two comparatively recent tech-
niques for parser improvement.
The first of these, parse-reranking (Collins,
2000; Charniak and Johnson, 2005) starts with a
standard generative parser, but uses it to gener-
ate the n-best parses rather than a single parse.
Then a reranking phase uses more detailed fea-
tures, features which would (mostly) be impossi-
ble to incorporate in the initial phase, to reorder
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996495">
337
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985953708333333">
\x0cthe list and pick a possibly different best parse.
At first blush one might think that gathering even
more fine-grained features from a WSJ treebank
would not help adaptation. However, we find that
reranking improves the parsers performance from
82.9% to 85.2%.
The second technique is self-training pars-
ing unlabeled data and adding it to the training
corpus. Recent work, (McClosky et al., 2006),
has shown that adding many millions of words
of machine parsed and reranked LA Times arti-
cles does, in fact, improve performance of the
parser on the closely related WSJ data. Here we
show that it also helps the father-afield Brown
data. Adding it improves performance yet-again,
this time from 85.2% to 87.8%, for a net error re-
duction of 28%. It is interesting to compare this to
our results for a completely Brown trained system
(i.e. one in which the first-phase parser is trained
on just Brown training data, and the second-phase
reranker is trained on Brown 50-best lists). This
system performs at a 88.4% level only slightly
higher than that achieved by our system with only
WSJ data.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999539" genericHeader="related work">
2 Related Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99000544">
Work in parser adaptation is premised on the as-
sumption that one wants a single parser that can
handle a wide variety of domains. While this is the
goal of the majority of parsing researchers, it is not
quite universal. Sekine (1997) observes that for
parsing a specific domain, data from that domain
is most beneficial, followed by data from the same
class, data from a different class, and data from
a different domain. He also notes that different
domains have very different structures by looking
at frequent grammar productions. For these rea-
sons he takes the position that we should, instead,
simply create treebanks for a large number of do-
mains. While this is a coherent position, it is far
from the majority view.
There are many different approaches to parser
adaptation. Steedman et al. (2003) apply co-
training to parser adaptation and find that co-
training can work across domains. The need to
parse biomedical literature inspires (Clegg and
Shepherd, 2005; Lease and Charniak, 2005).
Clegg and Shepherd (2005) provide an extensive
side-by-side performance analysis of several mod-
ern statistical parsers when faced with such data.
They find that techniques which combine differ-
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.959335142857143">
Training Testing
f-measure
Gildea Bacchiani
WSJ WSJ 86.4 87.0
WSJ Brown 80.6 81.1
Brown Brown 84.0 84.7
WSJ+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.99904">
Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.998581666666666">
Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown
training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of
length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences.
ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse se-
lection can improve performance on biomedical
data. Lease and Charniak (2005) use the Charniak
parser for biomedical data and find that the use of
out-of-domain trees and in-domain vocabulary in-
formation can considerably improve performance.
However, the work which is most directly com-
parable to ours is that of (Ratnaparkhi, 1999; Hwa,
1999; Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006). All
of these papers look at what happens to mod-
ern WSJ-trained statistical parsers (Ratnaparkhis,
Collins, Gildeas and Roarks, respectively) as
training data varies in size or usefulness (because
we are testing on something other than WSJ). We
concentrate particularly on the work of (Gildea,
2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006) as they provide re-
sults which are directly comparable to those pre-
sented in this paper.
Looking at Table 1, the first line shows us
the standard training and testing on WSJ both
parsers perform in the 86-87% range. The next
line shows what happens when parsing Brown us-
ing a WSJ-trained parser. As with the Charniak
parser, both parsers take an approximately 6% hit.
It is at this point that our work deviates from
these two papers. Lacking alternatives, both
(Gildea, 2001) and (Bacchiani et al., 2006) give
up on adapting a pure WSJ trained system, instead
looking at the issue of how much of an improve-
ment one gets over a pure Brown system by adding
WSJ data (as seen in the last two lines of Table 1).
Both systems use a model-merging (Bacchiani
et al., 2006) approach. The different corpora are,
in effect, concatenated together. However, (Bac-
chiani et al., 2006) achieve a larger gain by weight-
ing the in-domain (Brown) data more heavily than
the out-of-domain WSJ data. One can imagine, for
instance, five copies of the Brown data concate-
nated with just one copy of WSJ data.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997865">
338
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.770093" genericHeader="method">
\x0c3 Corpora
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971200545454546">
We primarily use three corpora in this paper. Self-
training requires labeled and unlabeled data. We
assume that these sets of data must be in similar
domains (e.g. news articles) though the effective-
ness of self-training across domains is currently an
open question. Thus, we have labeled (WSJ) and
unlabeled (NANC) out-of-domain data and labeled
in-domain data (BROWN). Unfortunately, lacking
a corresponding corpus to NANC for BROWN, we
cannot perform the opposite scenario and adapt
BROWN to WSJ.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.992612">
3.1 Brown
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998266411764706">
The BROWN corpus (Francis and Kucera, 1979)
consists of many different genres of text, intended
to approximate a balanced corpus. While the
full corpus consists of fiction and nonfiction do-
mains, the sections that have been annotated in
Treebank II bracketing are primarily those con-
taining fiction. Examples of the sections annotated
include science fiction, humor, romance, mystery,
adventure, and popular lore. We use the same
divisions as Bacchiani et al. (2006), who base
their divisions on Gildea (2001). Each division of
the corpus consists of sentences from all available
genres. The training division consists of approx-
imately 80% of the data, while held-out develop-
ment and testing divisions each make up 10% of
the data. The treebanked sections contain approx-
imately 25,000 sentences (458,000 words).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999248">
3.2 Wall Street Journal
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9974935">
Our out-of-domain data is the Wall Street Journal
(WSJ) portion of the Penn Treebank (Marcus et al.,
1993) which consists of about 40,000 sentences
(one million words) annotated with syntactic in-
formation. We use the standard divisions: Sec-
tions 2 through 21 are used for training, section 24
for held-out development, and section 23 for final
testing.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9975">
3.3 North American News Corpus
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997176833333333">
In addition to labeled news data, we make use
of a large quantity of unlabeled news data. The
unlabeled data is the North American News Cor-
pus, NANC (Graff, 1995), which is approximately
24 million unlabeled sentences from various news
sources. NANC contains no syntactic information
and sentence boundaries are induced by a simple
discriminative model. We also perform some basic
cleanups on NANC to ease parsing. NANC contains
news articles from various news sources including
the Wall Street Journal, though for this paper, we
only use articles from the LA Times portion.
To use the data from NANC, we use self-training
(McClosky et al., 2006). First, we take a WSJ
trained reranking parser (i.e. both the parser and
reranker are built from WSJ training data) and
parse the sentences from NANC with the 50-best
(Charniak and Johnson, 2005) parser. Next, the
50-best parses are reordered by the reranker. Fi-
nally, the 1-best parses after reranking are com-
bined with the WSJ training set to retrain the first-
stage parser.1 McClosky et al. (2006) find that the
self-trained models help considerably when pars-
ing WSJ.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999479" genericHeader="method">
4 Experiments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9961363">
We use the Charniak and Johnson (2005) rerank-
ing parser in our experiments. Unless mentioned
otherwise, we use the WSJ-trained reranker (as op-
posed to a BROWN-trained reranker). To evaluate,
we report bracketing f-scores.2 Parser f-scores
reported are for sentences up to 100 words long,
while reranking parser f-scores are over all sen-
tences. For simplicity and ease of comparison,
most of our evaluations are performed on the de-
velopment section of BROWN.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.997898">
4.1 Adapting self-training
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994707222222222">
Our first experiment examines the performance
of the self-trained parsers. While the parsers are
created entirely from labeled WSJ data and unla-
beled NANC data, they perform extremely well on
BROWN development (Table 2). The trends are the
same as in (McClosky et al., 2006): Adding NANC
data improves parsing performance on BROWN
development considerably, improving the f-score
from 83.9% to 86.4%. As more NANC data is
added, the f-score appears to approach an asymp-
tote. The NANC data appears to help reduce data
sparsity and fill in some of the gaps in the WSJ
model. Additionally, the reranker provides fur-
ther benefit and adds an absolute 1-2% to the f-
score. The improvements appear to be orthogonal,
as our best performance is reached when we use
the reranker and add 2,500k self-trained sentences
from NANC.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.739745">
1
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.969521">
We trained a new reranker from this data as well, but it
does not seem to get significantly different performance.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.871509">
2
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.7468875">
The harmonic mean of labeled precision (P) and labeled
recall (R), i.e. f = 2P R
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.740858">
P +R
</equation>
<page confidence="0.921825">
339
</page>
<table confidence="0.998892">
\x0cSentences added Parser Reranking Parser
Baseline BROWN 86.4 87.4
Baseline WSJ 83.9 85.8
WSJ+50k 84.8 86.6
WSJ+250k 85.7 87.2
WSJ+500k 86.0 87.3
WSJ+750k 86.1 87.5
WSJ+1,000k 86.2 87.3
WSJ+1,500k 86.2 87.6
WSJ+2,000k 86.1 87.7
WSJ+2,500k 86.4 87.7
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.82104">
Table 2: Effects of adding NANC sentences to WSJ
training data on parsing performance. f-scores
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999030538461539">
for the parser with and without the WSJ reranker
are shown when evaluating on BROWN develop-
ment. For this experiment, we use the WSJ-trained
reranker.
The results are even more surprising when we
compare against a parser3 trained on the labeled
training section of the BROWN corpus, with pa-
rameters tuned against its held-out section. De-
spite seeing no in-domain data, the WSJ based
parser is able to match the BROWN based parser.
For the remainder of this paper, we will refer
to the model trained on WSJ+2,500k sentences of
NANC as our best WSJ+NANC model. We also
note that this best parser is different from the
best parser for parsing WSJ, which was trained
on WSJ with a relative weight4 of 5 and 1,750k
sentences from NANC. For parsing BROWN, the
difference between these two parsers is not large,
though.
Increasing the relative weight of WSJ sentences
versus NANC sentences when testing on BROWN
development does not appear to have a significant
effect. While (McClosky et al., 2006) showed that
this technique was effective when testing on WSJ,
the true distribution was closer to WSJ so it made
sense to emphasize it.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.994025">
4.2 Incorporating In-Domain Data
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9963515">
Up to this point, we have only considered the sit-
uation where we have no in-domain data. We now
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.972098">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997812333333333">
In this case, only the parser is trained on BROWN. In sec-
tion 4.3, we compare against a fully BROWN-trained rerank-
ing parser as well.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.962957">
4
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998705607142857">
A relative weight of n is equivalent to using n copies of
the corpus, i.e. an event that occurred x times in the corpus
would occur xn times in the weighted corpus. Thus, larger
corpora will tend to dominate smaller corpora of the same
relative weight in terms of event counts.
explore different ways of making use of labeled
and unlabeled in-domain data.
Bacchiani et al. (2006) applies self-training to
parser adaptation to utilize unlabeled in-domain
data. The authors find that it helps quite a bit when
adapting from BROWN to WSJ. They use a parser
trained from the BROWN train set to parse WSJ and
add the parsed WSJ sentences to their training set.
We perform a similar experiment, using our WSJ-
trained reranking parser to parse BROWN train and
testing on BROWN development. We achieved a
boost from 84.8% to 85.6% when we added the
parsed BROWN sentences to our training. Adding
in 1,000k sentences from NANC as well, we saw a
further increase to 86.3%. However, the technique
does not seem as effective in our case. While the
self-trained BROWN data helps the parser, it ad-
versely affects the performance of the reranking
parser. When self-trained BROWN data is added to
WSJ training, the reranking parsers performance
drops from 86.6% to 86.1%. We see a similar
degradation as NANC data is added to the train-
ing set as well. We are not yet able to explain this
unusual behavior.
We now turn to the scenario where we have
some labeled in-domain data. The most obvious
way to incorporate labeled in-domain data is to
combine it with the labeled out-of-domain data.
We have already seen the results (Gildea, 2001)
and (Bacchiani et al., 2006) achieve in Table 1.
We explore various combinations of BROWN,
WSJ, and NANC corpora. Because we are
mainly interested in exploring techniques with
self-trained models rather than optimizing perfor-
mance, we only consider weighting each corpus
with a relative weight of one for this paper. The
models generated are tuned on section 24 from
WSJ. The results are summarized in Table 3.
While both WSJ and BROWN models bene-
fit from a small amount of NANC data, adding
more than 250k NANC sentences to the BROWN
or combined models causes their performance to
drop. This is not surprising, though, since adding
too much NANC overwhelms the more accurate
BROWN or WSJ counts. By weighting the counts
from each corpus appropriately, this problem can
be avoided.
Another way to incorporate labeled data is to
tune the parser back-off parameters on it. Bac-
chiani et al. (2006) report that tuning on held-out
BROWN data gives a large improvement over tun-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.98288">
340
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993906">
\x0cing on WSJ data. The improvement is mostly (but
not entirely) in precision. We do not see the same
improvement (Figure 1) but this is likely due to
differences in the parsers. However, we do see
a similar improvement for parsing accuracy once
NANC data has been added. The reranking parser
generally sees an improvement, but it does not ap-
pear to be significant.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998381">
4.3 Reranker Portability
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998969666666666">
We have shown that the WSJ-trained reranker is
actually quite portable to the BROWN fiction do-
main. This is surprising given the large number
of features (over a million in the case of the WSJ
reranker) tuned to adjust for errors made in the 50-
best lists by the first-stage parser. It would seem
the corrections memorized by the reranker are not
as domain-specific as we might expect.
As further evidence, we present the results of
applying the WSJ model to the Switchboard cor-
pus a domain much less similar to WSJ than
BROWN. In Table 4, we see that while the parsers
performance is low, self-training and reranking
provide orthogonal benefits. The improvements
represent a 12% error reduction with no additional
in-domain data. Naturally, in-domain data and
speech-specific handling (e.g. disfluency model-
ing) would probably help dramatically as well.
Finally, to compare against a model fully
trained on BROWN data, we created a BROWN
reranker. We parsed the BROWN training set with
20-fold cross-validation, selected features that oc-
curred 5 times or more in the training set, and
fed the 50-best lists from the parser to a numeri-
cal optimizer to estimate feature weights. The re-
sulting reranker model had approximately 700,000
features, which is about half as many as the WSJ
trained reranker. This may be due to the smaller
size of the BROWN training set or because the
feature schemas for the reranker were developed
on WSJ data. As seen in Table 5, the BROWN
reranker is not a significant improvement over the
WSJ reranker for parsing BROWN data.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990295" genericHeader="method">
5 Analysis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995935">
We perform several types of analysis to measure
some of the differences and similarities between
the BROWN-trained and WSJ-trained reranking
parsers. While the two parsers agree on a large
number of parse brackets (Section 5.2), there are
categorical differences between them (as seen in
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.982917666666667">
Parser model Parser f-score Reranker f-score
WSJ 74.0 75.9
WSJ+NANC 75.6 77.0
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.988648">
Table 4: Parser and reranking parser performance
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.491497">
on the SWITCHBOARD development corpus. In
this case, WSJ+NANC is a model created from WSJ
and 1,750k sentences from NANC.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9991265">
Model 1-best 10-best 25-best 50-best
WSJ 82.6 88.9 90.7 91.9
WSJ+NANC 86.4 92.1 93.5 94.3
BROWN 86.3 92.0 93.3 94.2
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.995386">
Table 6: Oracle f-scores of top n parses pro-
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.825651333333333">
duced by baseline WSJ parser, a combined WSJ and
NANC parser, and a baseline BROWN parser.
Section 5.3).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.988278">
5.1 Oracle Scores
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999776666666667">
Table 6 shows the f-scores of an oracle reranker
i.e. one which would always choose the parse
with the highest f-score in the n-best list. While
the WSJ parser has relatively low f-scores, adding
NANC data results in a parser with comparable ora-
cle scores as the parser trained from BROWN train-
ing. Thus, the WSJ+NANC model has better oracle
rates than the WSJ model (McClosky et al., 2006)
for both the WSJ and BROWN domains.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999374">
5.2 Parser Agreement
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997250545454546">
In this section, we compare the output of the
WSJ+NANC-trained and BROWN-trained rerank-
ing parsers. We use evalb to calculate how sim-
ilar the two sets of output are on a bracket level.
Table 7 shows various statistics. The two parsers
achieved an 88.0% f-score between them. Ad-
ditionally, the two parsers agreed on all brackets
almost half the time. The part of speech tagging
agreement is fairly high as well. Considering they
were created from different corpora, this seems
like a high level of agreement.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.997516">
5.3 Statistical Analysis
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998927428571429">
We conducted randomization tests for the signifi-
cance of the difference in corpus f-score, based on
the randomization version of the paired sample t-
test described by Cohen (1995). The null hypoth-
esis is that the two parsers being compared are in
fact behaving identically, so permuting or swap-
ping the parse trees produced by the parsers for
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.985969">
341
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9556605">
\x0cWSJ tuned parser
BROWN tuned parser
WSJ tuned reranking parser
BROWN tuned reranking parser
NANC sentences added
f
-score
2000k
1750k
1500k
1250k
1000k
750k
500k
250k
0k
87.8
87.0
86.0
85.0
</figure>
<page confidence="0.634141">
83.8
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999816">
Figure 1: Precision and recall f-scores when testing on BROWN development as a function of the number
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9551165">
of NANC sentences added under four test conditions. BROWN tuned indicates that BROWN training data
was used to tune the parameters (since the normal held-out section was being used for testing). For WSJ
tuned, we tuned the parameters from section 24 of WSJ. Tuning on BROWN helps the parser, but not for
the reranking parser.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.983215727272727">
Parser model Parser alone Reranking parser
WSJ alone 83.9 85.8
WSJ+2,500k NANC 86.4 87.7
BROWN alone 86.3 87.4
BROWN+50k NANC 86.8 88.0
BROWN+250k NANC 86.8 88.1
BROWN+500k NANC 86.7 87.8
WSJ+BROWN 86.5 88.1
WSJ+BROWN+50k NANC 86.8 88.1
WSJ+BROWN+250k NANC 86.8 88.1
WSJ+BROWN+500k NANC 86.6 87.7
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.995741">
Table 3: f-scores from various combinations of WSJ, NANC, and BROWN corpora on BROWN develop-
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.849293">
ment. The reranking parser used the WSJ-trained reranker model. The BROWN parsing model is naturally
better than the WSJ model for this task, but combining the two training corpora results in a better model
(as in Gildea (2001)). Adding small amounts of NANC further improves the models.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.99227275">
Parser model Parser alone WSJ-reranker BROWN-reranker
WSJ 82.9 85.2 85.2
WSJ+NANC 87.1 87.8 87.9
BROWN 86.7 88.2 88.4
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.99812">
Table 5: Performance of various combinations of parser and reranker models when evaluated on BROWN
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.897528">
test. The WSJ+NANC parser with the WSJ reranker comes close to the BROWN-trained reranking parser.
The BROWN reranker provides only a small improvement over its WSJ counterpart, which is not statisti-
cally significant.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993918">
342
</page>
<table confidence="0.998742">
\x0cBracketing agreement f-score 88.03%
Complete match 44.92%
Average crossing brackets 0.94
POS Tagging agreement 94.85%
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.990247">
Table 7: Agreement between the WSJ+NANC
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999423780487805">
parser with the WSJ reranker and the BROWN
parser with the BROWN reranker. Complete match
is how often the two reranking parsers returned the
exact same parse.
the same test sentence should not affect the cor-
pus f-scores. By estimating the proportion of per-
mutations that result in an absolute difference in
corpus f-scores at least as great as that observed
in the actual output, we obtain a distribution-
free estimate of significance that is robust against
parser and evaluator failures. The results of this
test are shown in Table 8. The table shows that
the BROWN reranker is not significantly different
from the WSJ reranker.
In order to better understand the difference be-
tween the reranking parser trained on Brown and
the WSJ+NANC/WSJ reranking parser (a reranking
parser with the first-stage trained on WSJ+NANC
and the second-stage trained on WSJ) on Brown
data, we constructed a logistic regression model
of the difference between the two parsers f-
scores on the development data using the R sta-
tistical package5. Of the 2,078 sentences in the
development data, 29 sentences were discarded
because evalb failed to evaluate at least one of
the parses.6 A Wilcoxon signed rank test on the
remaining 2,049 paired sentence level f-scores
was significant at p = 0.0003. Of these 2,049
sentences, there were 983 parse pairs with the
same sentence-level f-score. Of the 1,066 sen-
tences for which the parsers produced parses with
different f-scores, there were 580 sentences for
which the BROWN/BROWN parser produced a
parse with a higher sentence-level f-score and 486
sentences for which the WSJ+NANC/WSJ parser
produce a parse with a higher f-score. We
constructed a generalized linear model with a
binomial link with BROWN/BROWN f-score &gt;
WSJ+NANC/WSJ f-score as the predicted variable,
and sentence length, the number of prepositions
(IN), the number of conjunctions (CC) and Brown
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.3686215">
5
http://www.r-project.org
</figure>
<page confidence="0.947659">
6
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987693">
This occurs when an apostrophe is analyzed as a posses-
sive marker in the gold tree and a punctuation symbol in the
parse tree, or vice versa.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9993786">
Feature Estimate z-value Pr(&gt; |z|)
(Intercept) 0.054 0.3 0.77
IN -0.134 -4.4 8.4e-06 ***
ID=G 0.584 2.5 0.011 *
ID=K 0.697 2.9 0.003 **
ID=L 0.552 2.3 0.021 *
ID=M 0.376 0.9 0.33
ID=N 0.642 2.7 0.0055 **
ID=P 0.624 2.7 0.0069 **
ID=R 0.040 0.1 0.90
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.997703">
Table 9: The logistic model of BROWN/BROWN
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.986570333333334">
f-score &gt; WSJ+NANC/WSJ f-score identified by
model selection. The feature IN is the num-
ber prepositions in the sentence, while ID identi-
fies the Brown subcorpus that the sentence comes
from. Stars indicate significance level.
subcorpus ID as explanatory variables. Model
selection (using the step procedure) discarded
all but the IN and Brown ID explanatory vari-
ables. The final estimated model is shown in Ta-
ble 9. It shows that the WSJ+NANC/WSJ parser
becomes more likely to have a higher f-score
than the BROWN/BROWN parser as the number
of prepositions in the sentence increases, and that
the BROWN/BROWN parser is more likely to have
a higher f-score on Brown sections K, N, P, G
and L (these are the general fiction, adventure and
western fiction, romance and love story, letters and
memories, and mystery sections of the Brown cor-
pus, respectively). The three sections of BROWN
not in this list are F, M, and R (popular lore, sci-
ence fiction, and humor).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99678" genericHeader="conclusions">
6 Conclusions and Future Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9993242">
We have demonstrated that rerankers and self-
trained models can work well across domains.
Models self-trained on WSJ appear to be better
parsing models in general, the benefits of which
are not limited to the WSJ domain. The WSJ-
trained reranker using out-of-domain LA Times
parses (produced by the WSJ-trained reranker)
achieves a labeled precision-recall f-measure of
87.8% on Brown data, nearly equal to the per-
formance one achieves by using a purely Brown
trained parser-reranker. The 87.8% f-score on
Brown represents a 24% error reduction on the
corpus.
Of course, as corpora differences go, Brown is
relatively close to WSJ. While we also find that our
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997943">
343
</page>
<table confidence="0.994149">
\x0cWSJ+NANC/WSJ BROWN/WSJ BROWN/BROWN
WSJ/WSJ 0.025 (0) 0.030 (0) 0.031 (0)
WSJ+NANC/WSJ 0.004 (0.1) 0.006 (0.025)
BROWN/WSJ 0.002 (0.27)
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.998368">
Table 8: The difference in corpus f-score between the various reranking parsers, and the significance of
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9969278">
the difference in parentheses as estimated by a randomization test with 106 samples. x/y indicates that
the first-stage parser was trained on data set x and the second-stage reranker was trained on data set y.
best WSJ-parser-reranker improves performance
on the Switchboard corpus, it starts from a much
lower base (74.0%), and achieves a much less sig-
nificant improvement (3% absolute, 11% error re-
duction). Bridging these larger gaps is still for the
future.
One intriguing idea is what we call self-trained
bridging-corpora. We have not yet experimented
with medical text but we expect that the best
WSJ+NANC parser will not perform very well.
However, suppose one does self-training on a bi-
ology textbook instead of the LA Times. One
might hope that such a text will split the differ-
ence between more normal newspaper articles
and the specialized medical text. Thus, a self-
trained parser based upon such text might do much
better than our standard best. This is, of course,
highly speculative.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983881" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.3670715">
This work was supported by NSF grants LIS9720368, and
IIS0095940, and DARPA GALE contract HR0011-06-2-
0001. We would like to thank the BLLIP team for their com-
ments.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.696935" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999559728813559">
Michiel Bacchiani, Michael Riley, Brian Roark, and
Richard Sproat. 2006. MAP adaptation of stochas-
tic grammars. Computer Speech and Language,
20(1):4168.
Eugene Charniak and Mark Johnson. 2005. Coarse-
to-fine n-best parsing and MaxEnt discriminative
reranking. In Proc. of the 2005 Meeting of the
Assoc. for Computational Linguistics (ACL), pages
173180.
Andrew B. Clegg and Adrian Shepherd. 2005. Evalu-
ating and integrating treebank parsers on a biomedi-
cal corpus. In Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on
Software.
Paul R. Cohen. 1995. Empirical Methods for Artifi-
cial Intelligence. The MIT Press, Cambridge, Mas-
sachusetts.
Michael Collins. 2000. Discriminative reranking
for natural language parsing. In Machine Learn-
ing: Proceedings of the Seventeenth International
Conference (ICML 2000), pages 175182, Stanford,
California.
W. Nelson Francis and Henry Kucera. 1979. Manual
of Information to accompany a Standard Corpus of
Present-day Edited American English, for use with
Digital Computers. Brown University, Providence,
Rhode Island.
Daniel Gildea. 2001. Corpus variation and parser per-
formance. In Empirical Methods in Natural Lan-
guage Processing (EMNLP), pages 167202.
David Graff. 1995. North American News Text Cor-
pus. Linguistic Data Consortium. LDC95T21.
Rebecca Hwa. 1999. Supervised grammar induction
using training data with limited constituent infor-
mation. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meet-
ing of the Association for Computational Linguis-
tics, pages 7280, University of Maryland.
Matthew Lease and Eugene Charniak. 2005. Parsing
biomedical literature. In Second International Joint
Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJC-
NLP05).
Michell P. Marcus, Beatrice Santorini, and Mary Ann
Marcinkiewicz. 1993. Building a large annotated
corpus of English: The Penn Treebank. Comp. Lin-
guistics, 19(2):313330.
David McClosky, Eugene Charniak, and Mark John-
son. 2006. Effective self-training for parsing. In
Proceedings of HLT-NAACL 2006.
Adwait Ratnaparkhi. 1999. Learning to parse natural
language with maximum entropy models. Machine
Learning, 34(1-3):151175.
Satoshi Sekine. 1997. The domain dependence of
parsing. In Proc. Applied Natural Language Pro-
cessing (ANLP), pages 96102.
Mark Steedman, Miles Osborne, Anoop Sarkar,
Stephen Clark, Rebecca Hwa, Julia Hockenmaier,
Paul Ruhlen, Steven Baker, and Jeremiah Crim.
2003. Bootstrapping statistical parsers from small
datasets. In Proc. of European ACL (EACL), pages
331338.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996339">
344
</page>
<figure confidence="0.244669">
\x0c&apos;
</figure>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.821697">
<note confidence="0.939067333333333">b&apos;Proceedings of the 21st International Conference on Computational Linguistics and 44th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 337344, Sydney, July 2006. c 2006 Association for Computational Linguistics</note>
<title confidence="0.998349">Reranking and Self-Training for Parser Adaptation</title>
<author confidence="0.999992">David McClosky</author>
<author confidence="0.999992">Eugene Charniak</author>
<author confidence="0.999992">Mark Johnson</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.995955">Brown Laboratory for Linguistic Information Processing (BLLIP) Brown University</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.999058">Providence, RI 02912</address>
<email confidence="0.999781">{dmcc|ec|mj}@cs.brown.edu</email>
<abstract confidence="0.998296178571428">Statistical parsers trained and tested on the Penn Wall Street Journal (WSJ) treebank have shown vast improvements over the last 10 years. Much of this improvement, however, is based upon an ever-increasing number of features to be trained on (typically) the WSJ treebank data. This has led to concern that such parsers may be too finely tuned to this corpus at the expense of portability to other genres. Such worries have merit. The standard Charniak parser checks in at a labeled precisionrecall f-measure of 89.7% on the Penn WSJ test set, but only 82.9% on the test set from the Brown treebank corpus. This paper should allay these fears. In particular, we show that the reranking parser described in Charniak and Johnson (2005) improves performance of the parser on Brown to 85.2%. Furthermore, use of the self-training techniques described in (Mc- Closky et al., 2006) raise this to 87.8% (an error reduction of 28%) again without any use of labeled Brown data. This is remarkable since training the parser and reranker on labeled Brown data achieves only 88.4%.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michiel Bacchiani</author>
<author>Michael Riley</author>
<author>Brian Roark</author>
<author>Richard Sproat</author>
</authors>
<title>MAP adaptation of stochastic grammars.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Computer Speech and Language,</journal>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="6621" citStr="Bacchiani et al., 2006" startWordPosition="1077" endWordPosition="1080">84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences. ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse selection can improve performance on biomedical data. Lease and Charniak (2005) use the Charniak parser for biomedical data and find that the use of out-of-domain trees and in-domain vocabulary information can considerably improve performance. However, the work which is most directly comparable to ours is that of (Ratnaparkhi, 1999; Hwa, 1999; Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006). All of these papers look at what happens to modern WSJ-trained statistical parsers (Ratnaparkhis, Collins, Gildeas and Roarks, respectively) as training data varies in size or usefulness (because we are testing on something other than WSJ). We concentrate particularly on the work of (Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006) as they provide results which are directly comparable to those presented in this paper. Looking at Table 1, the first line shows us the standard training and testing on WSJ both parsers perform in the 86-87% range. The next line shows what happens when parsing Brown using a </context>
<context position="9023" citStr="Bacchiani et al. (2006)" startWordPosition="1474" endWordPosition="1477">ain data (BROWN). Unfortunately, lacking a corresponding corpus to NANC for BROWN, we cannot perform the opposite scenario and adapt BROWN to WSJ. 3.1 Brown The BROWN corpus (Francis and Kucera, 1979) consists of many different genres of text, intended to approximate a balanced corpus. While the full corpus consists of fiction and nonfiction domains, the sections that have been annotated in Treebank II bracketing are primarily those containing fiction. Examples of the sections annotated include science fiction, humor, romance, mystery, adventure, and popular lore. We use the same divisions as Bacchiani et al. (2006), who base their divisions on Gildea (2001). Each division of the corpus consists of sentences from all available genres. The training division consists of approximately 80% of the data, while held-out development and testing divisions each make up 10% of the data. The treebanked sections contain approximately 25,000 sentences (458,000 words). 3.2 Wall Street Journal Our out-of-domain data is the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) portion of the Penn Treebank (Marcus et al., 1993) which consists of about 40,000 sentences (one million words) annotated with syntactic information. We use the standard divi</context>
<context position="14540" citStr="Bacchiani et al. (2006)" startWordPosition="2396" endWordPosition="2399">main Data Up to this point, we have only considered the situation where we have no in-domain data. We now 3 In this case, only the parser is trained on BROWN. In section 4.3, we compare against a fully BROWN-trained reranking parser as well. 4 A relative weight of n is equivalent to using n copies of the corpus, i.e. an event that occurred x times in the corpus would occur xn times in the weighted corpus. Thus, larger corpora will tend to dominate smaller corpora of the same relative weight in terms of event counts. explore different ways of making use of labeled and unlabeled in-domain data. Bacchiani et al. (2006) applies self-training to parser adaptation to utilize unlabeled in-domain data. The authors find that it helps quite a bit when adapting from BROWN to WSJ. They use a parser trained from the BROWN train set to parse WSJ and add the parsed WSJ sentences to their training set. We perform a similar experiment, using our WSJtrained reranking parser to parse BROWN train and testing on BROWN development. We achieved a boost from 84.8% to 85.6% when we added the parsed BROWN sentences to our training. Adding in 1,000k sentences from NANC as well, we saw a further increase to 86.3%. However, the tech</context>
<context position="15810" citStr="Bacchiani et al., 2006" startWordPosition="2615" endWordPosition="2618">hile the self-trained BROWN data helps the parser, it adversely affects the performance of the reranking parser. When self-trained BROWN data is added to WSJ training, the reranking parsers performance drops from 86.6% to 86.1%. We see a similar degradation as NANC data is added to the training set as well. We are not yet able to explain this unusual behavior. We now turn to the scenario where we have some labeled in-domain data. The most obvious way to incorporate labeled in-domain data is to combine it with the labeled out-of-domain data. We have already seen the results (Gildea, 2001) and (Bacchiani et al., 2006) achieve in Table 1. We explore various combinations of BROWN, WSJ, and NANC corpora. Because we are mainly interested in exploring techniques with self-trained models rather than optimizing performance, we only consider weighting each corpus with a relative weight of one for this paper. The models generated are tuned on section 24 from WSJ. The results are summarized in Table 3. While both WSJ and BROWN models benefit from a small amount of NANC data, adding more than 250k NANC sentences to the BROWN or combined models causes their performance to drop. This is not surprising, though, since ad</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bacchiani, Riley, Roark, Sproat, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Michiel Bacchiani, Michael Riley, Brian Roark, and Richard Sproat. 2006. MAP adaptation of stochastic grammars. Computer Speech and Language, 20(1):4168.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Eugene Charniak</author>
<author>Mark Johnson</author>
</authors>
<title>Coarseto-fine n-best parsing and MaxEnt discriminative reranking.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 2005 Meeting of the Assoc. for Computational Linguistics (ACL),</booktitle>
<pages>173180</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1167" citStr="Charniak and Johnson (2005)" startWordPosition="177" endWordPosition="180">ovements over the last 10 years. Much of this improvement, however, is based upon an ever-increasing number of features to be trained on (typically) the WSJ treebank data. This has led to concern that such parsers may be too finely tuned to this corpus at the expense of portability to other genres. Such worries have merit. The standard Charniak parser checks in at a labeled precisionrecall f-measure of 89.7% on the Penn WSJ test set, but only 82.9% on the test set from the Brown treebank corpus. This paper should allay these fears. In particular, we show that the reranking parser described in Charniak and Johnson (2005) improves performance of the parser on Brown to 85.2%. Furthermore, use of the self-training techniques described in (McClosky et al., 2006) raise this to 87.8% (an error reduction of 28%) again without any use of labeled Brown data. This is remarkable since training the parser and reranker on labeled Brown data achieves only 88.4%. 1 Introduction Modern statistical parsers require treebanks to train their parameters, but their performance declines when one parses genres more distant from the training datas domain. Furthermore, the treebanks required to train said parsers are expensive and dif</context>
<context position="3320" citStr="Charniak and Johnson, 2005" startWordPosition="531" endWordPosition="534">s treebank. Furthermore, the treebanked Brown data is mostly general non-fiction and much closer to WSJ than, e.g., medical corpora would be. Thus, most work on parser adaptation resorts to using some labeled in-domain data to fortify the larger quantity of outof-domain data. In this paper, we present some encouraging results on parser adaptation without any in-domain data. (Though we also present results with indomain data as a reference point.) In particular we note the effects of two comparatively recent techniques for parser improvement. The first of these, parse-reranking (Collins, 2000; Charniak and Johnson, 2005) starts with a standard generative parser, but uses it to generate the n-best parses rather than a single parse. Then a reranking phase uses more detailed features, features which would (mostly) be impossible to incorporate in the initial phase, to reorder 337 \x0cthe list and pick a possibly different best parse. At first blush one might think that gathering even more fine-grained features from a WSJ treebank would not help adaptation. However, we find that reranking improves the parsers performance from 82.9% to 85.2%. The second technique is self-training parsing unlabeled data and adding i</context>
<context position="10619" citStr="Charniak and Johnson, 2005" startWordPosition="1733" endWordPosition="1736">es from various news sources. NANC contains no syntactic information and sentence boundaries are induced by a simple discriminative model. We also perform some basic cleanups on NANC to ease parsing. NANC contains news articles from various news sources including the Wall Street Journal, though for this paper, we only use articles from the LA Times portion. To use the data from NANC, we use self-training (McClosky et al., 2006). First, we take a WSJ trained reranking parser (i.e. both the parser and reranker are built from WSJ training data) and parse the sentences from NANC with the 50-best (Charniak and Johnson, 2005) parser. Next, the 50-best parses are reordered by the reranker. Finally, the 1-best parses after reranking are combined with the WSJ training set to retrain the firststage parser.1 McClosky et al. (2006) find that the self-trained models help considerably when parsing WSJ. 4 Experiments We use the Charniak and Johnson (2005) reranking parser in our experiments. Unless mentioned otherwise, we use the WSJ-trained reranker (as opposed to a BROWN-trained reranker). To evaluate, we report bracketing f-scores.2 Parser f-scores reported are for sentences up to 100 words long, while reranking parser </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Charniak, Johnson, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Eugene Charniak and Mark Johnson. 2005. Coarseto-fine n-best parsing and MaxEnt discriminative reranking. In Proc. of the 2005 Meeting of the Assoc. for Computational Linguistics (ACL), pages 173180.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Andrew B Clegg</author>
<author>Adrian Shepherd</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluating and integrating treebank parsers on a biomedical corpus.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on Software.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="5657" citStr="Clegg and Shepherd, 2005" startWordPosition="926" endWordPosition="929"> the same class, data from a different class, and data from a different domain. He also notes that different domains have very different structures by looking at frequent grammar productions. For these reasons he takes the position that we should, instead, simply create treebanks for a large number of domains. While this is a coherent position, it is far from the majority view. There are many different approaches to parser adaptation. Steedman et al. (2003) apply cotraining to parser adaptation and find that cotraining can work across domains. The need to parse biomedical literature inspires (Clegg and Shepherd, 2005; Lease and Charniak, 2005). Clegg and Shepherd (2005) provide an extensive side-by-side performance analysis of several modern statistical parsers when faced with such data. They find that techniques which combine differTraining Testing f-measure Gildea Bacchiani WSJ WSJ 86.4 87.0 WSJ Brown 80.6 81.1 Brown Brown 84.0 84.7 WSJ+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences. ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse selection can impro</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Clegg, Shepherd, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Andrew B. Clegg and Adrian Shepherd. 2005. Evaluating and integrating treebank parsers on a biomedical corpus. In Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on Software.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Paul R Cohen</author>
</authors>
<title>Empirical Methods for Artificial Intelligence.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<publisher>The MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="20696" citStr="Cohen (1995)" startWordPosition="3437" endWordPosition="3438"> We use evalb to calculate how similar the two sets of output are on a bracket level. Table 7 shows various statistics. The two parsers achieved an 88.0% f-score between them. Additionally, the two parsers agreed on all brackets almost half the time. The part of speech tagging agreement is fairly high as well. Considering they were created from different corpora, this seems like a high level of agreement. 5.3 Statistical Analysis We conducted randomization tests for the significance of the difference in corpus f-score, based on the randomization version of the paired sample ttest described by Cohen (1995). The null hypothesis is that the two parsers being compared are in fact behaving identically, so permuting or swapping the parse trees produced by the parsers for 341 \x0cWSJ tuned parser BROWN tuned parser WSJ tuned reranking parser BROWN tuned reranking parser NANC sentences added f -score 2000k 1750k 1500k 1250k 1000k 750k 500k 250k 0k 87.8 87.0 86.0 85.0 83.8 Figure 1: Precision and recall f-scores when testing on BROWN development as a function of the number of NANC sentences added under four test conditions. BROWN tuned indicates that BROWN training data was used to tune the parameters </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cohen, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Paul R. Cohen. 1995. Empirical Methods for Artificial Intelligence. The MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Collins</author>
</authors>
<title>Discriminative reranking for natural language parsing.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Machine Learning: Proceedings of the Seventeenth International Conference (ICML</booktitle>
<pages>175182</pages>
<location>Stanford, California.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3291" citStr="Collins, 2000" startWordPosition="529" endWordPosition="530">the Brown corpus treebank. Furthermore, the treebanked Brown data is mostly general non-fiction and much closer to WSJ than, e.g., medical corpora would be. Thus, most work on parser adaptation resorts to using some labeled in-domain data to fortify the larger quantity of outof-domain data. In this paper, we present some encouraging results on parser adaptation without any in-domain data. (Though we also present results with indomain data as a reference point.) In particular we note the effects of two comparatively recent techniques for parser improvement. The first of these, parse-reranking (Collins, 2000; Charniak and Johnson, 2005) starts with a standard generative parser, but uses it to generate the n-best parses rather than a single parse. Then a reranking phase uses more detailed features, features which would (mostly) be impossible to incorporate in the initial phase, to reorder 337 \x0cthe list and pick a possibly different best parse. At first blush one might think that gathering even more fine-grained features from a WSJ treebank would not help adaptation. However, we find that reranking improves the parsers performance from 82.9% to 85.2%. The second technique is self-training parsin</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Collins, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Michael Collins. 2000. Discriminative reranking for natural language parsing. In Machine Learning: Proceedings of the Seventeenth International Conference (ICML 2000), pages 175182, Stanford, California.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W Nelson Francis</author>
<author>Henry Kucera</author>
</authors>
<title>Manual of Information to accompany a Standard Corpus of Present-day Edited American English, for use with Digital Computers.</title>
<date>1979</date>
<institution>Brown University,</institution>
<location>Providence, Rhode Island.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="8600" citStr="Francis and Kucera, 1979" startWordPosition="1409" endWordPosition="1412">rown data concatenated with just one copy of WSJ data. 338 \x0c3 Corpora We primarily use three corpora in this paper. Selftraining requires labeled and unlabeled data. We assume that these sets of data must be in similar domains (e.g. news articles) though the effectiveness of self-training across domains is currently an open question. Thus, we have labeled (WSJ) and unlabeled (NANC) out-of-domain data and labeled in-domain data (BROWN). Unfortunately, lacking a corresponding corpus to NANC for BROWN, we cannot perform the opposite scenario and adapt BROWN to WSJ. 3.1 Brown The BROWN corpus (Francis and Kucera, 1979) consists of many different genres of text, intended to approximate a balanced corpus. While the full corpus consists of fiction and nonfiction domains, the sections that have been annotated in Treebank II bracketing are primarily those containing fiction. Examples of the sections annotated include science fiction, humor, romance, mystery, adventure, and popular lore. We use the same divisions as Bacchiani et al. (2006), who base their divisions on Gildea (2001). Each division of the corpus consists of sentences from all available genres. The training division consists of approximately 80% of </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Francis, Kucera, 1979</marker>
<rawString>W. Nelson Francis and Henry Kucera. 1979. Manual of Information to accompany a Standard Corpus of Present-day Edited American English, for use with Digital Computers. Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
</authors>
<title>Corpus variation and parser performance.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP),</booktitle>
<pages>167202</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6596" citStr="Gildea, 2001" startWordPosition="1075" endWordPosition="1076">J+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences. ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse selection can improve performance on biomedical data. Lease and Charniak (2005) use the Charniak parser for biomedical data and find that the use of out-of-domain trees and in-domain vocabulary information can considerably improve performance. However, the work which is most directly comparable to ours is that of (Ratnaparkhi, 1999; Hwa, 1999; Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006). All of these papers look at what happens to modern WSJ-trained statistical parsers (Ratnaparkhis, Collins, Gildeas and Roarks, respectively) as training data varies in size or usefulness (because we are testing on something other than WSJ). We concentrate particularly on the work of (Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006) as they provide results which are directly comparable to those presented in this paper. Looking at Table 1, the first line shows us the standard training and testing on WSJ both parsers perform in the 86-87% range. The next line shows what happens wh</context>
<context position="9066" citStr="Gildea (2001)" startWordPosition="1483" endWordPosition="1484">ing corpus to NANC for BROWN, we cannot perform the opposite scenario and adapt BROWN to WSJ. 3.1 Brown The BROWN corpus (Francis and Kucera, 1979) consists of many different genres of text, intended to approximate a balanced corpus. While the full corpus consists of fiction and nonfiction domains, the sections that have been annotated in Treebank II bracketing are primarily those containing fiction. Examples of the sections annotated include science fiction, humor, romance, mystery, adventure, and popular lore. We use the same divisions as Bacchiani et al. (2006), who base their divisions on Gildea (2001). Each division of the corpus consists of sentences from all available genres. The training division consists of approximately 80% of the data, while held-out development and testing divisions each make up 10% of the data. The treebanked sections contain approximately 25,000 sentences (458,000 words). 3.2 Wall Street Journal Our out-of-domain data is the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) portion of the Penn Treebank (Marcus et al., 1993) which consists of about 40,000 sentences (one million words) annotated with syntactic information. We use the standard divisions: Sections 2 through 21 are used for t</context>
<context position="15781" citStr="Gildea, 2001" startWordPosition="2612" endWordPosition="2613">tive in our case. While the self-trained BROWN data helps the parser, it adversely affects the performance of the reranking parser. When self-trained BROWN data is added to WSJ training, the reranking parsers performance drops from 86.6% to 86.1%. We see a similar degradation as NANC data is added to the training set as well. We are not yet able to explain this unusual behavior. We now turn to the scenario where we have some labeled in-domain data. The most obvious way to incorporate labeled in-domain data is to combine it with the labeled out-of-domain data. We have already seen the results (Gildea, 2001) and (Bacchiani et al., 2006) achieve in Table 1. We explore various combinations of BROWN, WSJ, and NANC corpora. Because we are mainly interested in exploring techniques with self-trained models rather than optimizing performance, we only consider weighting each corpus with a relative weight of one for this paper. The models generated are tuned on section 24 from WSJ. The results are summarized in Table 3. While both WSJ and BROWN models benefit from a small amount of NANC data, adding more than 250k NANC sentences to the BROWN or combined models causes their performance to drop. This is not</context>
<context position="22107" citStr="Gildea (2001)" startWordPosition="3670" endWordPosition="3671">ser model Parser alone Reranking parser WSJ alone 83.9 85.8 WSJ+2,500k NANC 86.4 87.7 BROWN alone 86.3 87.4 BROWN+50k NANC 86.8 88.0 BROWN+250k NANC 86.8 88.1 BROWN+500k NANC 86.7 87.8 WSJ+BROWN 86.5 88.1 WSJ+BROWN+50k NANC 86.8 88.1 WSJ+BROWN+250k NANC 86.8 88.1 WSJ+BROWN+500k NANC 86.6 87.7 Table 3: f-scores from various combinations of WSJ, NANC, and BROWN corpora on BROWN development. The reranking parser used the WSJ-trained reranker model. The BROWN parsing model is naturally better than the WSJ model for this task, but combining the two training corpora results in a better model (as in Gildea (2001)). Adding small amounts of NANC further improves the models. Parser model Parser alone WSJ-reranker BROWN-reranker WSJ 82.9 85.2 85.2 WSJ+NANC 87.1 87.8 87.9 BROWN 86.7 88.2 88.4 Table 5: Performance of various combinations of parser and reranker models when evaluated on BROWN test. The WSJ+NANC parser with the WSJ reranker comes close to the BROWN-trained reranking parser. The BROWN reranker provides only a small improvement over its WSJ counterpart, which is not statistically significant. 342 \x0cBracketing agreement f-score 88.03% Complete match 44.92% Average crossing brackets 0.94 POS Tag</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gildea, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Daniel Gildea. 2001. Corpus variation and parser performance. In Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), pages 167202.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Graff</author>
</authors>
<title>North American News Text Corpus. Linguistic Data Consortium.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<tech>LDC95T21.</tech>
<contexts>
<context position="9939" citStr="Graff, 1995" startWordPosition="1626" endWordPosition="1627">imately 25,000 sentences (458,000 words). 3.2 Wall Street Journal Our out-of-domain data is the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) portion of the Penn Treebank (Marcus et al., 1993) which consists of about 40,000 sentences (one million words) annotated with syntactic information. We use the standard divisions: Sections 2 through 21 are used for training, section 24 for held-out development, and section 23 for final testing. 3.3 North American News Corpus In addition to labeled news data, we make use of a large quantity of unlabeled news data. The unlabeled data is the North American News Corpus, NANC (Graff, 1995), which is approximately 24 million unlabeled sentences from various news sources. NANC contains no syntactic information and sentence boundaries are induced by a simple discriminative model. We also perform some basic cleanups on NANC to ease parsing. NANC contains news articles from various news sources including the Wall Street Journal, though for this paper, we only use articles from the LA Times portion. To use the data from NANC, we use self-training (McClosky et al., 2006). First, we take a WSJ trained reranking parser (i.e. both the parser and reranker are built from WSJ training data)</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Graff, 1995</marker>
<rawString>David Graff. 1995. North American News Text Corpus. Linguistic Data Consortium. LDC95T21.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Rebecca Hwa</author>
</authors>
<title>Supervised grammar induction using training data with limited constituent information.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>7280</pages>
<institution>University of Maryland.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="6582" citStr="Hwa, 1999" startWordPosition="1073" endWordPosition="1074">4.0 84.7 WSJ+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences. ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse selection can improve performance on biomedical data. Lease and Charniak (2005) use the Charniak parser for biomedical data and find that the use of out-of-domain trees and in-domain vocabulary information can considerably improve performance. However, the work which is most directly comparable to ours is that of (Ratnaparkhi, 1999; Hwa, 1999; Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006). All of these papers look at what happens to modern WSJ-trained statistical parsers (Ratnaparkhis, Collins, Gildeas and Roarks, respectively) as training data varies in size or usefulness (because we are testing on something other than WSJ). We concentrate particularly on the work of (Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006) as they provide results which are directly comparable to those presented in this paper. Looking at Table 1, the first line shows us the standard training and testing on WSJ both parsers perform in the 86-87% range. The next line shows w</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hwa, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Rebecca Hwa. 1999. Supervised grammar induction using training data with limited constituent information. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pages 7280, University of Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Matthew Lease</author>
<author>Eugene Charniak</author>
</authors>
<title>Parsing biomedical literature.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Second International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJCNLP05).</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="5684" citStr="Lease and Charniak, 2005" startWordPosition="930" endWordPosition="933"> a different class, and data from a different domain. He also notes that different domains have very different structures by looking at frequent grammar productions. For these reasons he takes the position that we should, instead, simply create treebanks for a large number of domains. While this is a coherent position, it is far from the majority view. There are many different approaches to parser adaptation. Steedman et al. (2003) apply cotraining to parser adaptation and find that cotraining can work across domains. The need to parse biomedical literature inspires (Clegg and Shepherd, 2005; Lease and Charniak, 2005). Clegg and Shepherd (2005) provide an extensive side-by-side performance analysis of several modern statistical parsers when faced with such data. They find that techniques which combine differTraining Testing f-measure Gildea Bacchiani WSJ WSJ 86.4 87.0 WSJ Brown 80.6 81.1 Brown Brown 84.0 84.7 WSJ+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences. ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse selection can improve performance on biomedica</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lease, Charniak, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Matthew Lease and Eugene Charniak. 2005. Parsing biomedical literature. In Second International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJCNLP05).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michell P Marcus</author>
<author>Beatrice Santorini</author>
<author>Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz</author>
</authors>
<title>Building a large annotated corpus of English: The Penn Treebank.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Comp. Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="2164" citStr="Marcus et al., 1993" startWordPosition="342" endWordPosition="345">require treebanks to train their parameters, but their performance declines when one parses genres more distant from the training datas domain. Furthermore, the treebanks required to train said parsers are expensive and difficult to produce. Naturally, one of the goals of statistical parsing is to produce a broad-coverage parser which is relatively insensitive to textual domain. But the lack of corpora has led to a situation where much of the current work on parsing is performed on a single domain using training data from that domain the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) section of the Penn Treebank (Marcus et al., 1993). Given the aforementioned costs, it is unlikely that many significant treebanks will be created for new genres. Thus, parser adaptation attempts to leverage existing labeled data from one domain and create a parser capable of parsing a different domain. Unfortunately, the state of the art in parser portability (i.e. using a parser trained on one domain to parse a different domain) is not good. The Charniak parser has a labeled precision-recall f-measure of 89.7% on WSJ but a lowly 82.9% on the test set from the Brown corpus treebank. Furthermore, the treebanked Brown data is mostly general no</context>
<context position="9499" citStr="Marcus et al., 1993" startWordPosition="1550" endWordPosition="1553">ns annotated include science fiction, humor, romance, mystery, adventure, and popular lore. We use the same divisions as Bacchiani et al. (2006), who base their divisions on Gildea (2001). Each division of the corpus consists of sentences from all available genres. The training division consists of approximately 80% of the data, while held-out development and testing divisions each make up 10% of the data. The treebanked sections contain approximately 25,000 sentences (458,000 words). 3.2 Wall Street Journal Our out-of-domain data is the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) portion of the Penn Treebank (Marcus et al., 1993) which consists of about 40,000 sentences (one million words) annotated with syntactic information. We use the standard divisions: Sections 2 through 21 are used for training, section 24 for held-out development, and section 23 for final testing. 3.3 North American News Corpus In addition to labeled news data, we make use of a large quantity of unlabeled news data. The unlabeled data is the North American News Corpus, NANC (Graff, 1995), which is approximately 24 million unlabeled sentences from various news sources. NANC contains no syntactic information and sentence boundaries are induced by</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcus, Santorini, Marcinkiewicz, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Michell P. Marcus, Beatrice Santorini, and Mary Ann Marcinkiewicz. 1993. Building a large annotated corpus of English: The Penn Treebank. Comp. Linguistics, 19(2):313330.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David McClosky</author>
<author>Eugene Charniak</author>
<author>Mark Johnson</author>
</authors>
<title>Effective self-training for parsing.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of HLT-NAACL</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="1307" citStr="McClosky et al., 2006" startWordPosition="198" endWordPosition="202">ly) the WSJ treebank data. This has led to concern that such parsers may be too finely tuned to this corpus at the expense of portability to other genres. Such worries have merit. The standard Charniak parser checks in at a labeled precisionrecall f-measure of 89.7% on the Penn WSJ test set, but only 82.9% on the test set from the Brown treebank corpus. This paper should allay these fears. In particular, we show that the reranking parser described in Charniak and Johnson (2005) improves performance of the parser on Brown to 85.2%. Furthermore, use of the self-training techniques described in (McClosky et al., 2006) raise this to 87.8% (an error reduction of 28%) again without any use of labeled Brown data. This is remarkable since training the parser and reranker on labeled Brown data achieves only 88.4%. 1 Introduction Modern statistical parsers require treebanks to train their parameters, but their performance declines when one parses genres more distant from the training datas domain. Furthermore, the treebanks required to train said parsers are expensive and difficult to produce. Naturally, one of the goals of statistical parsing is to produce a broad-coverage parser which is relatively insensitive </context>
<context position="3982" citStr="McClosky et al., 2006" startWordPosition="640" endWordPosition="643">r, but uses it to generate the n-best parses rather than a single parse. Then a reranking phase uses more detailed features, features which would (mostly) be impossible to incorporate in the initial phase, to reorder 337 \x0cthe list and pick a possibly different best parse. At first blush one might think that gathering even more fine-grained features from a WSJ treebank would not help adaptation. However, we find that reranking improves the parsers performance from 82.9% to 85.2%. The second technique is self-training parsing unlabeled data and adding it to the training corpus. Recent work, (McClosky et al., 2006), has shown that adding many millions of words of machine parsed and reranked LA Times articles does, in fact, improve performance of the parser on the closely related WSJ data. Here we show that it also helps the father-afield Brown data. Adding it improves performance yet-again, this time from 85.2% to 87.8%, for a net error reduction of 28%. It is interesting to compare this to our results for a completely Brown trained system (i.e. one in which the first-phase parser is trained on just Brown training data, and the second-phase reranker is trained on Brown 50-best lists). This system perfor</context>
<context position="10423" citStr="McClosky et al., 2006" startWordPosition="1700" endWordPosition="1703">ews data, we make use of a large quantity of unlabeled news data. The unlabeled data is the North American News Corpus, NANC (Graff, 1995), which is approximately 24 million unlabeled sentences from various news sources. NANC contains no syntactic information and sentence boundaries are induced by a simple discriminative model. We also perform some basic cleanups on NANC to ease parsing. NANC contains news articles from various news sources including the Wall Street Journal, though for this paper, we only use articles from the LA Times portion. To use the data from NANC, we use self-training (McClosky et al., 2006). First, we take a WSJ trained reranking parser (i.e. both the parser and reranker are built from WSJ training data) and parse the sentences from NANC with the 50-best (Charniak and Johnson, 2005) parser. Next, the 50-best parses are reordered by the reranker. Finally, the 1-best parses after reranking are combined with the WSJ training set to retrain the firststage parser.1 McClosky et al. (2006) find that the self-trained models help considerably when parsing WSJ. 4 Experiments We use the Charniak and Johnson (2005) reranking parser in our experiments. Unless mentioned otherwise, we use the </context>
<context position="11667" citStr="McClosky et al., 2006" startWordPosition="1902" endWordPosition="1905">as opposed to a BROWN-trained reranker). To evaluate, we report bracketing f-scores.2 Parser f-scores reported are for sentences up to 100 words long, while reranking parser f-scores are over all sentences. For simplicity and ease of comparison, most of our evaluations are performed on the development section of BROWN. 4.1 Adapting self-training Our first experiment examines the performance of the self-trained parsers. While the parsers are created entirely from labeled WSJ data and unlabeled NANC data, they perform extremely well on BROWN development (Table 2). The trends are the same as in (McClosky et al., 2006): Adding NANC data improves parsing performance on BROWN development considerably, improving the f-score from 83.9% to 86.4%. As more NANC data is added, the f-score appears to approach an asymptote. The NANC data appears to help reduce data sparsity and fill in some of the gaps in the WSJ model. Additionally, the reranker provides further benefit and adds an absolute 1-2% to the fscore. The improvements appear to be orthogonal, as our best performance is reached when we use the reranker and add 2,500k self-trained sentences from NANC. 1 We trained a new reranker from this data as well, but it</context>
<context position="13757" citStr="McClosky et al., 2006" startWordPosition="2255" endWordPosition="2258">he WSJ based parser is able to match the BROWN based parser. For the remainder of this paper, we will refer to the model trained on WSJ+2,500k sentences of NANC as our best WSJ+NANC model. We also note that this best parser is different from the best parser for parsing WSJ, which was trained on WSJ with a relative weight4 of 5 and 1,750k sentences from NANC. For parsing BROWN, the difference between these two parsers is not large, though. Increasing the relative weight of WSJ sentences versus NANC sentences when testing on BROWN development does not appear to have a significant effect. While (McClosky et al., 2006) showed that this technique was effective when testing on WSJ, the true distribution was closer to WSJ so it made sense to emphasize it. 4.2 Incorporating In-Domain Data Up to this point, we have only considered the situation where we have no in-domain data. We now 3 In this case, only the parser is trained on BROWN. In section 4.3, we compare against a fully BROWN-trained reranking parser as well. 4 A relative weight of n is equivalent to using n copies of the corpus, i.e. an event that occurred x times in the corpus would occur xn times in the weighted corpus. Thus, larger corpora will tend </context>
<context position="19927" citStr="McClosky et al., 2006" startWordPosition="3307" endWordPosition="3310">90.7 91.9 WSJ+NANC 86.4 92.1 93.5 94.3 BROWN 86.3 92.0 93.3 94.2 Table 6: Oracle f-scores of top n parses produced by baseline WSJ parser, a combined WSJ and NANC parser, and a baseline BROWN parser. Section 5.3). 5.1 Oracle Scores Table 6 shows the f-scores of an oracle reranker i.e. one which would always choose the parse with the highest f-score in the n-best list. While the WSJ parser has relatively low f-scores, adding NANC data results in a parser with comparable oracle scores as the parser trained from BROWN training. Thus, the WSJ+NANC model has better oracle rates than the WSJ model (McClosky et al., 2006) for both the WSJ and BROWN domains. 5.2 Parser Agreement In this section, we compare the output of the WSJ+NANC-trained and BROWN-trained reranking parsers. We use evalb to calculate how similar the two sets of output are on a bracket level. Table 7 shows various statistics. The two parsers achieved an 88.0% f-score between them. Additionally, the two parsers agreed on all brackets almost half the time. The part of speech tagging agreement is fairly high as well. Considering they were created from different corpora, this seems like a high level of agreement. 5.3 Statistical Analysis We conduc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>McClosky, Charniak, Johnson, 2006</marker>
<rawString>David McClosky, Eugene Charniak, and Mark Johnson. 2006. Effective self-training for parsing. In Proceedings of HLT-NAACL 2006.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Adwait Ratnaparkhi</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning to parse natural language with maximum entropy models.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Machine Learning,</booktitle>
<pages>34--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6571" citStr="Ratnaparkhi, 1999" startWordPosition="1071" endWordPosition="1072"> 81.1 Brown Brown 84.0 84.7 WSJ+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WSJ and Brown training sets. Gildea evaluates on sentences of length 40, Bacchiani on all sentences. ent parsers such as voting schemes and parse selection can improve performance on biomedical data. Lease and Charniak (2005) use the Charniak parser for biomedical data and find that the use of out-of-domain trees and in-domain vocabulary information can considerably improve performance. However, the work which is most directly comparable to ours is that of (Ratnaparkhi, 1999; Hwa, 1999; Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006). All of these papers look at what happens to modern WSJ-trained statistical parsers (Ratnaparkhis, Collins, Gildeas and Roarks, respectively) as training data varies in size or usefulness (because we are testing on something other than WSJ). We concentrate particularly on the work of (Gildea, 2001; Bacchiani et al., 2006) as they provide results which are directly comparable to those presented in this paper. Looking at Table 1, the first line shows us the standard training and testing on WSJ both parsers perform in the 86-87% range. The next l</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ratnaparkhi, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Adwait Ratnaparkhi. 1999. Learning to parse natural language with maximum entropy models. Machine Learning, 34(1-3):151175.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Satoshi Sekine</author>
</authors>
<title>The domain dependence of parsing.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. Applied Natural Language Processing (ANLP),</booktitle>
<pages>96102</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4924" citStr="Sekine (1997)" startWordPosition="807" endWordPosition="808">reduction of 28%. It is interesting to compare this to our results for a completely Brown trained system (i.e. one in which the first-phase parser is trained on just Brown training data, and the second-phase reranker is trained on Brown 50-best lists). This system performs at a 88.4% level only slightly higher than that achieved by our system with only WSJ data. 2 Related Work Work in parser adaptation is premised on the assumption that one wants a single parser that can handle a wide variety of domains. While this is the goal of the majority of parsing researchers, it is not quite universal. Sekine (1997) observes that for parsing a specific domain, data from that domain is most beneficial, followed by data from the same class, data from a different class, and data from a different domain. He also notes that different domains have very different structures by looking at frequent grammar productions. For these reasons he takes the position that we should, instead, simply create treebanks for a large number of domains. While this is a coherent position, it is far from the majority view. There are many different approaches to parser adaptation. Steedman et al. (2003) apply cotraining to parser ad</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sekine, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Satoshi Sekine. 1997. The domain dependence of parsing. In Proc. Applied Natural Language Processing (ANLP), pages 96102.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark Steedman</author>
<author>Miles Osborne</author>
<author>Anoop Sarkar</author>
<author>Stephen Clark</author>
<author>Rebecca Hwa</author>
<author>Julia Hockenmaier</author>
<author>Paul Ruhlen</author>
<author>Steven Baker</author>
<author>Jeremiah Crim</author>
</authors>
<title>Bootstrapping statistical parsers from small datasets.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of European ACL (EACL),</booktitle>
<pages>331338</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="5494" citStr="Steedman et al. (2003)" startWordPosition="900" endWordPosition="903">esearchers, it is not quite universal. Sekine (1997) observes that for parsing a specific domain, data from that domain is most beneficial, followed by data from the same class, data from a different class, and data from a different domain. He also notes that different domains have very different structures by looking at frequent grammar productions. For these reasons he takes the position that we should, instead, simply create treebanks for a large number of domains. While this is a coherent position, it is far from the majority view. There are many different approaches to parser adaptation. Steedman et al. (2003) apply cotraining to parser adaptation and find that cotraining can work across domains. The need to parse biomedical literature inspires (Clegg and Shepherd, 2005; Lease and Charniak, 2005). Clegg and Shepherd (2005) provide an extensive side-by-side performance analysis of several modern statistical parsers when faced with such data. They find that techniques which combine differTraining Testing f-measure Gildea Bacchiani WSJ WSJ 86.4 87.0 WSJ Brown 80.6 81.1 Brown Brown 84.0 84.7 WSJ+Brown Brown 84.3 85.6 Table 1: Gildea and Bacchiani results on WSJ and Brown test corpora using different WS</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Steedman, Osborne, Sarkar, Clark, Hwa, Hockenmaier, Ruhlen, Baker, Crim, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Mark Steedman, Miles Osborne, Anoop Sarkar, Stephen Clark, Rebecca Hwa, Julia Hockenmaier, Paul Ruhlen, Steven Baker, and Jeremiah Crim. 2003. Bootstrapping statistical parsers from small datasets. In Proc. of European ACL (EACL), pages 331338.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>