<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000225">
<title confidence="0.588231">
b&apos;A General Feature Space for Automatic Verb Classification
</title>
<author confidence="0.923191">
Eric Joanis and Suzanne Stevenson
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.996265">
Department of Computer Science
University of Toronto
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.996454">
fjoanis,suzannel@cs.toronto.edu
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990795" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999828095238095">
We develop a general feature space for
automatic classification of verbs into
lexical semantic classes. Previous work
was limited in scope by the need for
manual selection of discriminating fea-
tures, through a linguistic analysis of the
target verb classes (Merlo and Steven-
son, 2001). We instead analyze the
classification structure at a higher level,
using the possible defining characteris-
tics of classes as the basis for our fea-
ture space. The general feature space
achieves reductions in error rates of 42
69%, on a wider range of classes than
investigated previously, with compara-
ble performance to feature sets manu-
ally selected for the particular classifi-
cation tasks. Our results show that the
approach is generally applicable, and
avoids the need for resource-intensive
linguistic analysis for each new task.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997769" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99602954">
Wide-coverage language processing systems re-
quire large amounts of knowledge about individ-
ual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottle-
neck. Because verbs play a central role in the syn-
tactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence,
much research has focused on automatically learn-
ing properties of verbs from text corpora, such
as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe
and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and
Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002),
selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexi-
cal semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996;
Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000;
Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to ex-
tend the applicability of the latter, by developing a
general feature space for automatic verb classifi-
cation.
Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001)
showed that verbs could be automatically classi-
fied into one of three lexical semantic classes on
the basis of five simple statistical features. This
work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classifi-
cation from noisy, easily extractable corpus statis-
tics. However, the approach was limited in scope
by the need for manual determination of a discrim-
inating set of features, through a linguistic anal-
ysis of the target verb classes. Our work over-
comes this limitation by developing a general fea-
ture space that avoids the need for individual de-
velopment of features for specific classes.
The central idea of our approach is as follows.
We focus on lexical semantic classes as in Levin
(1993) (hereafter Levin), which group together
verbs sharing both a common semantics (such as
manner of motion or change of state), and a set of
syntactic alternations. An alternation refers to the
alternative mappings of the semantic arguments of
a verb to syntactic positions, as in:
la. I loaded the truck
b. I loaded hay onto the truck.
In Merlo and Stevenson (2001) (hereafter MS01),
the differences between the specific semantic ar-
guments and their possible alternations for the
three target classes were analyzed to determine a
small set of discriminating features. Here, we per-
form the linguistic analysis at a higher level, by
analyzing the range of possible alternations and
distinctions among arguments that verbs can ex-
hibit.
with hay
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998093">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998360071428572">
\x0cAs an illustrative example, MS01 determined
that an informative statistical feature is the propor-
tion of animate subjects used with a verb, since an-
imacy is correlated with agenthood, and their verb
classes differed in whether they have an agentive
subject. In our feature space, we generalize this
idea to yield a set of features that estimate animacy
for each possible syntactic argument slot (not just
subject, but direct and indirect object, and object
of prepositions). In this way, we capture the ob-
servation that, across verb classes in general, se-
mantic arguments in any slot (not just subject) may
differ in their proportion of animate entities.
Since we analyze verb class distinctions at this
more general level, we need only do the linguistic
analysis once, rather than having to do the individ-
ual analysis for every set of classes that we want to
distinguish. It is worth emphasizing that we do not
base our features directly on all the existing Levin
classes (cf. Don and Jones 1996)we instead an-
alyze possible alternations for verbs independent
of the actual classes. The result is a general classi-
fication feature space that in principle is useful for
any Levin-type verb classification task. 1
The generality of our feature space enables ex-
periments on a wider range of classes than has pre-
viously been attempted with the approach in MS01
and subsequent extensions (Merlo et al., 2002).
We demonstrate the applicability of the feature
space to distinctions among 14 classes, including
ten new classes in addition to the target classes
on which the method was originally developed.
To preview our results below, we achieve reduc-
tions in error rate ranging from 42% to 69%, av-
eraging more than 50% over all the tasks, demon-
strating the potential of the approach for a wide
range of classes. Furthermore, the performance
compares favourably with sets of features hand-
selected for the particular class distinctions, sup-
porting our claim that the general feature space
can replace the time-consuming expert linguistic
analysis previously needed for each new classifi-
cation task.
The remainder of the paper describes the anal-
!
And indeed, it may be useful for other approaches to
predicate classification as well, as long as their distinc-
tions have expression in syntactic behaviour (e.g., as in
the FrameNet project, http://www.icsi.berkeley.
edur framenet/).
ysis underlying the features in our general feature
space, the classes chosen for demonstrating its ef-
fectiveness, and our experimental procedures and
results. We conclude with a discussion of related
work, as well as limitations and planned exten-
sions of our approach.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990473" genericHeader="method">
2 The Feature Space
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999544482758621">
Recall that lexical semantic classes as in Levin
form a hierarchy of verb groupings with shared
meaning and syntax. The constraints on map-
ping semantic arguments to syntactic positions re-
flect underlying semantic properties of the verbs
(Pinker, 1989; Levin, 1993). Thus alternations,
such as those in (1) above, in which the same ar-
gument (hay or truck) is mapped to different po-
sitions, are particularly useful in distinguishing
verb classes. MS01 further note the importance
of the differing semantic (thematic) roles assigned
by verbs for distinguishing the classes.
The features in MS01, and those of our general
feature space, were designed to tap into the dif-
ferences between classes both in the alternations
they allow, and in the thematic roles assigned. To
this end, we generalized the features from MS01,
and extended them by considering the full set of
alternations from Levin, to capture similar distinc-
tions across a wider range of verb class variability.
Specifically, we drew on Part I of Levin, which
elaborates the alternations she uses to characterize
verb classes, in contrast to Part II, which enumer-
ates the classes themselves.
The feature space is summarized in Table 1, and
described in detail in the rest of this section. All
frequency counts are normalized by the total num-
ber of occurrences of the verb (or, in some cases,
a relevant subset).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.936749">
2.1 Features over Syntactic Slots
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999260555555556">
Syntactic alternations play a central role in defin-
ing classes, but are difficult to detect automatically
from a corpus (McCarthy, 2000). We have devised
several types of features that tap into different as-
pects of alternation behaviour. One set of features
encodes the frequency of the syntactic slots con-
taining verbal arguments in Levin\&apos;s classes (sub-
ject, direct and indirect object, and prepositional
phrases), thus approximating the allowable syntac-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999848">
164
</page>
<table confidence="0.94988625">
\x0c in Text Feature Category #Features
Syntactic slots 76
2.1 Slot overlap 40
&quot;Empty&quot; words 4
Passive 2
2.2 POS of the verb 6
Aux, modal, Adv 13
Derived forms 3
</table>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.633282">
2.3 Animacy of NPs 76
</subsectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.98692">
Table 1: Feature categories with number of fea-
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.966115161290323">
tures of each type.
tic frames for a verb.2 For prepositional phrases,
we have a separate feature for each of 51 high
frequency prepositions, as well as 19 groups of
closely related prepositions (e.g., between, in be-
tween, among, amongst, amid, and amidst form
one group). We also count verb uses where any
prepositional phrase occurs.
Using syntactic frame information alone misses
critical properties of alternations, since two verbs
may occur in the same frames but undergo differ-
ent mappings of their arguments to the positions.
Earlier work has used a measure of overlap over
nouns in syntactic slots as a noisy indicator of par-
ticipation in an alternation (Stevenson and Merlo,
1999; McCarthy, 2000). The idea is that since the
same semantic argument may occur in two differ-
ent slots in a pair of alternating frames, the degree
to which those two slots contain the same entities
is an indication of the verb\&apos;s participation in the
alternation.
In our feature space, we consider the overlap be-
tween each pair of slots that corresponds to an al-
ternation in Part I of Levin (i.e., 1-8). For each
alternation in which a semantic argument occurs
in one slot in one usage of the verb (such as sub-
ject in The sky cleared), and in a different slot in
the alternant usage (such as object of from in The
clouds cleared from the sky), we add a feature with
the measure of overlap in noun (lemma) usage be-
tween those two slots (in this case, subject of verb
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.7073095">
and object of from, Levin 2.3.5). When appropri-
2 Counts of separate slots are less informative than counts
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.987777333333333">
of entire syntactic frames, but also easier to extract, and there-
fore less noisy.
ate, we considered prepositions as a group, e.g.,
when the alternation refers to a general locative or
directional specification, rather than to a specific
preposition.
Levin also includes a number of alternations
in which semantically empty constituents (it and
there) alternate with a contentful subject or ob-
ject (e.g., A problem developed/There developed a
problem, Levin 6.1). We added features to count
it in the subject and direct object positions, and
there in the subject position. Given our extrac-
tion tools, the relevant semantically empty uses of
these words are indistinguishable from their con-
tentful usages. However, as with all our features,
we assume that the features will be useful even
given a certain level of noise, as found by MS01.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.91675">
2.2 Tense, Voice, and Aspect Features
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999179095238095">
Verb meaning and alternations also interact in in-
teresting ways with voice, tense, and aspect. For
example, MS01 used counts of passive and VBN
(past participle) usage as redundant indicators of
the transitive alternation. Levin notes several alter-
nations that depend on the passive use (5), so we
adopt this as a general feature. Some alternations
in Levin indirectly depend on tense of the verb
(e.g., the middle voice is usually in the present
tense), so we include a set of features that encode
the proportion of occurrence of the six POS tags
that verbs can take in the Penn tagset: VB, VBP,
VBZ, VBG, VBD, and VBN. We also further aug-
ment the feature space to count verb uses which
include each auxiliary or modal (or any modal),
or an adverb, whose use also interacts with voice
and aspect. In addition, there are alternations that
involve derived forms of the verb (Levin 5.4,
7.1,2), hence we include a set of features that
measure the frequency of a verb used as a noun
or adjective.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.995003">
2.3 The Animacy Feature
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99906525">
Another feature used by MS01 tapped into proper-
ties of the verbal arguments themselves. The ani-
macy feature measured the proportion of subjects
that were animate entities (estimated by pronoun
use) to capture the distinction between Agent and
Theme subjects across their target classes. Here
we consider the animacy of each of our syntactic
slots. In addition to personal pronouns, we count
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996753">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997947">
\x0cas animate proper NPs labelled as &quot;person&quot; by
our chunker (Abney\&apos;s (1991) SCOL). Other gen-
eral feature differences across thematic roles are
more challenging to detect automatically (e.g., vo-
litionality or independent existence, from Dowty,
1991). We leave further generalization of the idea
of distinctive features among thematic roles to fu-
ture work.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988696" genericHeader="method">
3 Experimental Verb Classes
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990157864197531">
For the experimental investigation of our feature
space, we selected a number of verb classes that
would be non-trivial test cases for evaluating the
method. Both for practical reasons and to make
the results of general interest, the classes could
neither be too small nor contain mostly infrequent
verbs. Pairs or triples of verb classes were se-
lected to form the test pairs/triples for each of a
number of separate classification tasks. To illus-
trate the range of applicability of the feature space,
we picked some pairs/triples of classes that were
closely related and some that were more dissim-
ilar. Table 2 at the end of this section lists the
classes, with their Levin class numbers; their prop-
erties are summarized here with examples of each.
Benefactive versus Recipient verbs.
Mary baked... a cake for Joan/Joan a cake.
Mary gave.., a cake to Joan/Joan a cake.
These dative alternation verbs differ in the prepo-
sition and the semantic role of its object.
Admire versus Amuse verbs.
I admire Jane. Jane amuses me.
These psychological state verbs differ in that the
Experiencer argument is the subject of Admire
verbs, and the object of Amuse verbs.
Run versus Sound Emission verbs.
The kids ran in the room./*The room ran with kids.
Birds sang in the trees./The trees sang with birds.
These intransitive activity verbs differ in the
prepositional alternations they allow.
Cheat versus Steal and Remove verbs.
I cheated... Jane of her money/*the money from Jane.
I stole... *Jane of her money/the money from Jane.
These semantically related classes differ in the
prepositional alternants they allow.
Wipe versus Steal and Remove verbs.
Wipe... the dust/the dust from the table/the table.
Steal... the money/the money from the bank/*the bank.
These classes generally allow the same syntactic
frames, but differ in the possible semantic role as-
signment. (Location can be the direct object of
Wipe verbs but not of Steal and Remove verbs, as
shown.)
Spray/Load versus Fill versus Other Verbs of
Putting (several related Levin classes).
/ loaded.., hay on the wagon/the wagon with hay.
I filled... *hay on the wagon/the wagon with hay.
I put... hay on the wagon/*the wagon with hay.
These three classes also differ in prepositional
altemants. Note, however, that the options for
Spray/Load verbs overlap with both of the other
two types of verbs.
Optionally Intransitive: Run versus Change
of State versus &quot;Object Drop&quot;.
These are the three classes of MS01, which we in-
vestigate here for comparison to their results. All
are optionally intransitive but assign different se-
mantic roles to their arguments. (Note that the Ob-
ject Drop verbs are a superset of the Benefactives
above.)
The classification tasks we chose vary in dif-
ficulty. For many tasks, knowing exactly what
PP arguments each verb takes may be sufficient
to perform the classification (cf. Don and Jones
1996). However, we do not have access to such
perfect knowledge, since PP arguments and ad-
juncts cannot be distinguished with high accuracy.
Using our simple extraction tools, for example, the
PP/or argument in I admired Jane for her honesty
is not distinguished from the for adjunct in I
amused Jane for the money. Furthermore, PP ar-
guments differ in frequency, so that a highly distin-
guishing but rarely used alternant will likely not be
useful. Differences in PP usage are thus noisy in-
dicators that we expect to be useful but not defini-
tive.
Finally, one of the pairs, Wipe versus Steal and
Remove verbs, are not distinguishable by even per-
fect information about syntactic frames: there is
no frame or slot which is allowed by all verbs in
one class and no verbs in the other. One might
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995903">
166
</page>
<table confidence="0.961468411764706">
\x0ctherefore expect this task to be one of the hardest
we consider.
Verb Class Levin Cl. # verbs
B enefactive 26.1, 26.3 35
Recipient 13.1, 13.3 27
Admire 31.2 35
Amuse 31.1 134
Run 51.3.2 79
Sound Emission 43.2 56
Cheat 10.6 29
Steal and Remove 10.5, 10.1 45
Wipe 10.4.1,2 35
Spray/Load 9.7 36
Fill 9.8 63
Other V. of Putting 9.1-6 48
Change of State 45.1-4 169
Object Drop 26.1,3,7 50
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.992701">
Table 2: Verb classes (see Section 3), their Levin
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.8332555">
class numbers, and the number of experimental
verbs in each (see Section 4.2).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.917899" genericHeader="method">
4 Materials and Method
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.988878">
4.1 Corpus
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998477444444445">
We use the British National Corpus (BNC) to es-
timate all features (Burnard, 2000), a 100M word
corpus tagged with the CLAWS POS tagset, which
we map to the Penn tagset. It consists of text sam-
ples of recent British English ranging over a wide
spectrum of domains, including both fiction and
non-fiction. Since it is a general corpus, we do
not expect any strong domain-specific bias in verb
usage.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.996965">
4.2 Verb Selection
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991020827586207">
We selected our experimental verbs as follows.
We started with a list of all the verbs in the given
classes from Levin, removing any verb that did not
occur at least 100 times in the BNC.3 Because we
assign a single classification to each verb, we also
removed any verb: that was deemed excessively
polysemous; that belonged to another class under
consideration in this study; or for which the class
3 Due to mistakes in our original counts, twelve verbs with
frequency between 88 and 99 were retained, as well as one
with frequency 44, singe, and one with frequency 19, idolize.
did not correspond to the main sense. (For exam-
ple, the Recipient-verb sense of extendin the us-
age &quot;extending a loan&quot;is far less common than
the &quot;stretching&quot; sense.) In on-going work, we are
exploring an iterative approach to token- and type-
based classification that would address this current
limitation of a single class per verb.
Table 2 above shows the number of verbs in
each class at the end of this process. Of these
verbs, 20 from each class were randomly selected
to use as training data. (For two classes, the se-
lection process was not completely random, since
some of the verbs were ones used previously in
MS01. We used those as training verbs since they
did not qualify as unseen test verbs.) Our unseen
test verbs then consist of all verbs remaining after
the selection of training data, except those that had
been used in the previous studies we build on.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998064">
4.3 Feature Extraction
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99949025">
We use an existing tool to extract the verb group
and syntactic slots on which our features are
based. The partial (or chunking) parser of Abney
(1991), called SCOL, allows us to extract subjects
and direct objects with reasonable confidence, and
to extract potential prepositional phrases associ-
ated with the verb. SCOL does not identify in-
direct objects, which we also require. We use
TGrep2 (Rohde, 2002) to identify potential indi-
rect objects by assuming that an object followed
by a noun phrase which SCOL has left unattached
is a double-object frame.4 From these extracted
slots, we calculate all the features described in
Section 2, yielding a vector of 220 normalized
counts for each verb, which forms the input to the
machine learning system.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998701">
4.4 Machine Learning Approach
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955493">
For all our experiments, we use the decision-
tree induction system C5.0, release 1.16 (www..
rulequest . com), the successor of C4.5 (Quin-
lan, 1993), as our machine learning software. On
our training sets, we use 10-fold cross-validation
repeated 50 times to estimate classification accu-
racy. For these, we report the average accuracy
4 This method of indirect object extraction had very low
precision (.22 on a random sample), but produced useful fea-
tures despite the high level of noise.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.946276">
167
</page>
<figure confidence="0.949745375">
\x0cExperiment
Base-
line
Acc
N
Test
Verbs
All features Levin-derived subsets
Train
Acc SE
Test
Acc\t (#)
Train
Ace SE
Test
Ace\t (#)
</figure>
<table confidence="0.9974627">
Benefactive/Recipient 50.0 22 74.1 0.6 72.7 (16) 79.5 0.6 86.4 (19)
Admire/Amuse 50.0 129 79.6 0.6 82.2 (106) 80.8 0.5 90.7 (117)
Run/Sound Emission 50.0 79 79.9 0.7 78.5 (62) 71.9 0.8 77.2 (61)
Cheat/Steal-Remove 50.0 33 88.9 0.4 72.7 (24) 83.0 0.5 72.7 (24)
Wipe/Steal-Remove 50.0 39 79.4 0.8 84.6 (33) 85.8 0.6 84.6 (33)
Spray/Fill/Putting 33.3 85 78.3 0.5 65.9 (56) 79.2 0.5 64.7 (55)
Optionally Intrans. 33.3 204 68.3 0.7 72.1 (147) 68.7 0.5 77.0 (157)
6 Locative Classes 16.7 133 69.0 0.3 56.4 (75) 72.8 0.4 54.9 (73)
8 Locative Classes 12.5 212 69.3 0.4 59.9 (127) 64.7 0.3 59.0 (125)
All 13 Classes 7.7 507 58.6 0.3 46.4 (235) 58.7 0.2 43.6 (221)
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999506">
Table 3: Experimental Results. Acc is % accuracy; SE is % standard error; # is number of test items
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.930256285714286">
correctly classified.
(number of verbs correctly classified over the total
number of verbs) and standard error calculated by
C5.0. To measure performance on our unseen test
data, we train a classifier on the training data, and
then measure its accuracy on the test verbs. In all
cases, we use the boosting option in C5.0.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997322" genericHeader="method">
5 Experimental Results
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997854134615385">
We performed ten classification tasks, shown in
the first column of Table 3. The 2- and 3-way
tasks, and their motivation, were described ear-
lier in Section 3. We added three multiway tasks
to explore how much we can expect our feature
space to scale to multiple class distinctions: The 6-
way task involves the Cheat, Steal-Remove, Wipe,
Spray/Load, Fill, and &quot;Other Verbs of Putting&quot;
classes, all of which undergo similar alternations
of locative arguments. To these 6, the 8-way task
adds the Run and Sound Emission verbs, which
also undergo locative alternations. The 13-way
task includes all our classes (except Benefactive,
which is a subset of Object Drop).
Note that we do not create one classifier which
is applied to different test data sets; rather, a sepa-
rate classifier is defined for each task using only
the training data for the verb classes under in-
vestigation. In all cases, the training data is bal-
anced, with 20 verbs in each class, so the baseline
(chance) performance is 1/k for a task discrim-
inating k classes. This baseline is shown in the
second column of Table 3, while the third column
gives the number of test verbs for each task.
Our first set of experiments uses all our fea-
tures (as listed in Table 1); the results are shown
in columns 4 and 5 of Table 3. In all cases, test
performance shows a substantial increase of 22-
47 percentage points above the baseline, with a
reduction in error rate ranging from 42-69%. In-
deed, it is worth noting that what we predicted to
be the most difficult task (the Wipe/Steal-Remove
case) had the best overall performance, of 84.6%
(line 5 of the table). In only two of our 2- and 3-
way tasks did test performance decrease by more
than 5% compared to training performance, in-
dicating good generalizability of the classifiers.
The 6- and 8-way tasks had very good perfor-
mance, and even the 13-way task far exceeded the
baseline, although in each case, test performance
was substantially less than results on training data.
For these complex multiway tasks, it seems, more
training verbs would be desirable.
Ideally, we would also like to compare our re-
sults to features developed by linguistic experts,
such as those in MS01. On our new test verbs
in the optionally intransitive task of MS01, our
feature space outperformed their hand-crafted fea-
tures, 72.1% (line 7 of the table) versus 64.2%.5
5 We set out to show that our general feature space could
perform comparably to a manually devised one. This result
reveals a potential advantage of the general feature set, which
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993787">
168
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999381045454545">
\x0cFor the other tasks, however, no manually de-
rived feature space exists. We instead compare the
general feature space to subsets of our own fea-
tures (called the Levin-derived subsets) which are
hand-selected through an analysis of the classes in
Levin.6 For each class, we have systematically
identified the subset of features indicated by the
class description given in Levin. For each task,
then, the Levin-derived subset is the union of these
subsets for all the classes in the task. The results
for these feature sets are given in columns 6 and
7 of Table 3. Comparing columns 5 and 7, we
see that the general feature space performs as well
as or better than the Levin-derived subset on most
tasks. For only 3 of the 10 tasks does the subset of
features outperform the full feature space by 5%
or more.
These results taken together support the hypoth-
esis that our general feature space can be used
successfully for automatic verb classification, and
can eliminate the need for time-consuming expert
analysis for each new task.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999738" genericHeader="method">
6 Related Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99676227118644">
Don and Jones (1996) showed that perfect knowl-
edge of the allowable syntactic frames for a verb
enabled an accuracy of 98% in assigning verbs
to Levin classes. We adopt the approach of
MS01, which instead approximates such knowl-
edge through statistical corpus analysis, allowing
for easier extensibility to new classes. Further-
more, rather than using a class-by-class analysis
as in Dorr and Jones (1996), our features are de-
termined through an analysis of the possible alter-
nations for verbs independent of their class assign-
ment, leading to a more general set of features.
Our study generalizes the slot overlap feature
of MS01 as an indicator of membership in a verb
class, on the assumption that slot overlap is cor-
related with alternation behaviour. Indeed, Mc-
Carthy (2000) confirmed this relation, showing
includes a broad range of indicators of syntactic behaviours.
These indicators may help to discriminate classes even if they
are not conceived of as core distinctions between the classes.
6This approach recognizes the important challenge faced
by our method in having to automatically select the best fea-
tures for a task from our large feature space. Admittedly, it
does not address the possibility that a linguist may devise a
feature for which we have no analogue.
that a slot overlap feature similar to ours could be a
useful indicator for a given alternation. McCarthy
achieved an increase in performance on her task
by using an alternative similarity measure over the
selectional preference of a verb for two slots that
alternate, indicating that other formulations of slot
similarity may be useful to pursue in future work.
Schulte im Walde (2000) and Schulte im Walde
and Brew (2002) achieved promising results us-
ing unsupervised clustering of verbs in English
and German, respectively, according to syntactic
frame statistics. Our feature space is more gen-
eral because it uses a combination of types of fea-
tures; we have features intended to indicate par-
ticipation in alternations, and not just subcatego-
rization. While our method used supervised learn-
ing, Stevenson and Merlo (1999) found little dif-
ference in performance between unsupervised and
supervised approaches on the original MS01 task.
However, since unsupervised methods are more
sensitive to irrelevant features, additional care will
be required to determine useful subsets of features
from our (larger) general feature space.
Also using unsupervised learning, Oishi and
Matsumoto (1997) clustered Japanese verbs auto-
matically into hundreds of semantic classes, which
they then combined into a network of 38 classes
using linguistic knowledge and semi-automated
processing. Their approach, like ours, used a com-
bination of syntactic frame and aspectual features,
but a limited set. Our work aims to extend this type
of hand-picked feature space to achieve a general-
ity that will limit the need for human expert input
in the classification process.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99723" genericHeader="conclusions">
7 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99968425">
We achieve very good accuracies across a range
of class distinctions, strongly supporting our ap-
proach of devising a general feature space for au-
tomatic verb classification based on a high-level
analysis of verb class distinctions. By basing our
features on possible alternations, rather than spe-
cific classes, we aim our feature space to be useful
not only for those verb classes already developed
in Levin, but for any additional classes not yet cov-
ered there, that allow for the same alternations. We
also believe it will be straightforward to extend
the feature space to cover additional alternations
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987685">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999548375">
\x0cnot in the scope of Levin (such as those involving
sentential arguments), through the same process of
generalizing the existing features to new slots.
Still, our investigation has been limited to En-
glish verb classes, and our feature space is lim-
ited in being motivated by alternations in English.
It thus lacks grammatical features (e.g., Case or
other rich morphological properties) used in other
languages to mark arguments or indicate the re-
lation between them. Interestingly, Merlo et al.
(2002) showed that some of the hand-crafted fea-
tures of MS01 were useful in Italian for classify-
ing the same verb classes in that language. We
think a more general feature space such as ours
will have even more potential for crosslinguis-
tic applicability: We have devised a mapping of
Levin\&apos;s analysis of the variation in expression of
arguments across classes in English to a general
set of features. To the extent that Levin\&apos;s anal-
ysis is grounded in general principles concerning
the linking of semantic arguments to their syntac-
tic expression, our feature space is an initial step in
capturing variation in the expression of arguments
across languages.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962806" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957567666666667">
We gratefully acknowledge the financial support
of NSERC of Canada, Bell University Labs, and
the University of Toronto.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971708" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999054902777778">
Steven Abney. 1991. Parsing by chunks. In Robert
Berwick, Steven Abney, and Carol Tenny, editors,
Principle-Based Parsing. Kluwer Academic Pub-
lishers.
Michael Brent. 1993. From grammar to lexicon: Unsu-
pervised learning of lexical syntax. Computational
Linguistics, 19(3):243-262.
Ted Briscoe and John Carroll. 1997. Automatic extrac-
tion of subcategorization from corpora. In Proceed-
ings of the Fifth ACL Conference on Applied Natural
Language Processing (ANLP-97), pages 356-363.
Lou Burnard, editor. 2000. British National Corpus
User Reference Guide.
Bonnie J. Dorr and Doug Jones. 1996. Role of word
sense disambiguation in lexical acquisition: Predict-
ing semantics from syntactic cues. pages 322-327.
David R. Dowty. 1991. Thematic proto-roles and argu-
ment selection. Language, 67(3):547-619.
Daniel Gildea and Daniel Jurafsky. 2002. Automatic
labeling of semantic roles. Computational Linguis-
tics, 28(3):245-288.
Maria Lapata and Chris Brew. 1999. Using subcatego-
rization to resolve verb class ambiguity. In P. Fung
and J. Zhou, editors, Joint SIGDAT Conference on
Empirical Methods in NLP and Very Large Corpora
(EMNLP/VLC-99), pages 266-274.
Beth Levin. 1993. English verb classes and alterna-
tions: A preliminary investigation. Chicago UP.
Diana McCarthy. 2000. Using semantic preferences to
identify verbal participation in role switching alter-
nations. In Proceedings of the First Conference of
the North American Ch. of the ACL (NAACL-2000).
Paola Merlo and Suzanne Stevenson. 2001. Automatic
verb classification based on statistical distributions
of argument structure. Computational Linguistics,
27(3):373-408.
Paola Merlo, Suzanne Stevenson, Vivian Tsang, and
Gianluca Allaria. 2002. A multilingual paradigm for
automatic verb classification. In Proceedings of the
40th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 207-214.
Akira Oishi and Yuji Matsumoto. 1997. Detecting
the organization of semantic subclasses of japanese
verbs. International Journal of Corpus Linguistics,
2(1):65-89.
Steven Pinker. 1989. Learnability and cognition: the
acquisition of argument structure. MIT Press.
J. R. Quinlan. 1993. C4.5: Programs for Machine
Learning. Morgan Kaufmann, CA.
Philip Resnik. 1996. Selectional constraints: an
information-theoretic model and its computational
realization. Cognition, 61(1-2):127-159.
Ellen Riloff and Mark Schmelzenbach. 1998. An em-
pirical approach to conceptual case frame acquisi-
tion. In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very
Large Corpora (WVLC-98).
Douglas L. T. Rohde. 2002. TGrep2 user manual ver-
sion 1.3. Available with the TGrep2 package at
http://tedlab.mit.edu/ - dr/Tgrep2/.
Sabine Schulte im Walde. 2000. Clustering verbs se-
mantically according to their alternation behaviour.
In Proceedings of the 18th International Con-
ference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-
2000), pages 747-753.
Sabine Schulte im Walde and Chris Brew. 2002. Induc-
ing German semantic verb classes from purely syn-
tactic subcategorisation information. In Proceed-
ings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages
223-230.
Suzanne Stevenson and Paola Merlo. 1999. Automatic
verb classification using grammatical features. In
Proceedings of the Ninth Conference of the Euro-
pean Chapter of the ACL (EACL-99), pages 45-52.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.849782">
170
</page>
<figure confidence="0.337959">
\x0c&apos;
</figure>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.994780">
<title confidence="0.999237">b&apos;A General Feature Space for Automatic Verb Classification</title>
<author confidence="0.999888">Eric Joanis</author>
<author confidence="0.999888">Suzanne Stevenson</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9999785">Department of Computer Science University of Toronto</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.999892">fjoanis,suzannel@cs.toronto.edu</email>
<abstract confidence="0.999804545454545">We develop a general feature space for automatic classification of verbs into lexical semantic classes. Previous work was limited in scope by the need for manual selection of discriminating features, through a linguistic analysis of the target verb classes (Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). We instead analyze the classification structure at a higher level, using the possible defining characteristics of classes as the basis for our feature space. The general feature space achieves reductions in error rates of 42 69%, on a wider range of classes than investigated previously, with comparable performance to feature sets manually selected for the particular classification tasks. Our results show that the approach is generally applicable, and avoids the need for resource-intensive linguistic analysis for each new task.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Steven Abney</author>
</authors>
<title>Parsing by chunks.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<editor>In Robert Berwick, Steven Abney, and Carol Tenny, editors, Principle-Based Parsing.</editor>
<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="18538" citStr="Abney (1991)" startWordPosition="3070" endWordPosition="3071"> from each class were randomly selected to use as training data. (For two classes, the selection process was not completely random, since some of the verbs were ones used previously in MS01. We used those as training verbs since they did not qualify as unseen test verbs.) Our unseen test verbs then consist of all verbs remaining after the selection of training data, except those that had been used in the previous studies we build on. 4.3 Feature Extraction We use an existing tool to extract the verb group and syntactic slots on which our features are based. The partial (or chunking) parser of Abney (1991), called SCOL, allows us to extract subjects and direct objects with reasonable confidence, and to extract potential prepositional phrases associated with the verb. SCOL does not identify indirect objects, which we also require. We use TGrep2 (Rohde, 2002) to identify potential indirect objects by assuming that an object followed by a noun phrase which SCOL has left unattached is a double-object frame.4 From these extracted slots, we calculate all the features described in Section 2, yielding a vector of 220 normalized counts for each verb, which forms the input to the machine learning system.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Abney, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Steven Abney. 1991. Parsing by chunks. In Robert Berwick, Steven Abney, and Carol Tenny, editors, Principle-Based Parsing. Kluwer Academic Publishers.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Brent</author>
</authors>
<title>From grammar to lexicon: Unsupervised learning of lexical syntax.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>19--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1397" citStr="Brent, 1993" startWordPosition="208" endWordPosition="209">nce to feature sets manually selected for the particular classification tasks. Our results show that the approach is generally applicable, and avoids the need for resource-intensive linguistic analysis for each new task. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Brent, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Michael Brent. 1993. From grammar to lexicon: Unsupervised learning of lexical syntax. Computational Linguistics, 19(3):243-262.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ted Briscoe</author>
<author>John Carroll</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic extraction of subcategorization from corpora.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fifth ACL Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ANLP-97),</booktitle>
<pages>356--363</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1425" citStr="Briscoe and Carroll, 1997" startWordPosition="210" endWordPosition="213">e sets manually selected for the particular classification tasks. Our results show that the approach is generally applicable, and avoids the need for resource-intensive linguistic analysis for each new task. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Briscoe, Carroll, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Ted Briscoe and John Carroll. 1997. Automatic extraction of subcategorization from corpora. In Proceedings of the Fifth ACL Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ANLP-97), pages 356-363.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>British National Corpus User Reference Guide.</booktitle>
<editor>Lou Burnard, editor.</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="25268" citStr="(2000)" startWordPosition="4217" endWordPosition="4217"> approach of MS01, which instead approximates such knowledge through statistical corpus analysis, allowing for easier extensibility to new classes. Furthermore, rather than using a class-by-class analysis as in Dorr and Jones (1996), our features are determined through an analysis of the possible alternations for verbs independent of their class assignment, leading to a more general set of features. Our study generalizes the slot overlap feature of MS01 as an indicator of membership in a verb class, on the assumption that slot overlap is correlated with alternation behaviour. Indeed, McCarthy (2000) confirmed this relation, showing includes a broad range of indicators of syntactic behaviours. These indicators may help to discriminate classes even if they are not conceived of as core distinctions between the classes. 6This approach recognizes the important challenge faced by our method in having to automatically select the best features for a task from our large feature space. Admittedly, it does not address the possibility that a linguist may devise a feature for which we have no analogue. that a slot overlap feature similar to ours could be a useful indicator for a given alternation. Mc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>2000</marker>
<rawString>Lou Burnard, editor. 2000. British National Corpus User Reference Guide.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bonnie J Dorr</author>
<author>Doug Jones</author>
</authors>
<title>Role of word sense disambiguation in lexical acquisition: Predicting semantics from syntactic cues.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<pages>322--327</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1600" citStr="Dorr and Jones, 1996" startWordPosition="233" endWordPosition="236">nalysis for each new task. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statistics. However, the approach was limited in scope by the need for manual determination of a discrimina</context>
<context position="24894" citStr="Dorr and Jones (1996)" startWordPosition="4151" endWordPosition="4154">gether support the hypothesis that our general feature space can be used successfully for automatic verb classification, and can eliminate the need for time-consuming expert analysis for each new task. 6 Related Work Don and Jones (1996) showed that perfect knowledge of the allowable syntactic frames for a verb enabled an accuracy of 98% in assigning verbs to Levin classes. We adopt the approach of MS01, which instead approximates such knowledge through statistical corpus analysis, allowing for easier extensibility to new classes. Furthermore, rather than using a class-by-class analysis as in Dorr and Jones (1996), our features are determined through an analysis of the possible alternations for verbs independent of their class assignment, leading to a more general set of features. Our study generalizes the slot overlap feature of MS01 as an indicator of membership in a verb class, on the assumption that slot overlap is correlated with alternation behaviour. Indeed, McCarthy (2000) confirmed this relation, showing includes a broad range of indicators of syntactic behaviours. These indicators may help to discriminate classes even if they are not conceived of as core distinctions between the classes. 6Thi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dorr, Jones, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Bonnie J. Dorr and Doug Jones. 1996. Role of word sense disambiguation in lexical acquisition: Predicting semantics from syntactic cues. pages 322-327.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David R Dowty</author>
</authors>
<title>Thematic proto-roles and argument selection.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<journal>Language,</journal>
<pages>67--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="12143" citStr="Dowty, 1991" startWordPosition="1978" endWordPosition="1979">d into properties of the verbal arguments themselves. The animacy feature measured the proportion of subjects that were animate entities (estimated by pronoun use) to capture the distinction between Agent and Theme subjects across their target classes. Here we consider the animacy of each of our syntactic slots. In addition to personal pronouns, we count 165 \x0cas animate proper NPs labelled as &quot;person&quot; by our chunker (Abney\&apos;s (1991) SCOL). Other general feature differences across thematic roles are more challenging to detect automatically (e.g., volitionality or independent existence, from Dowty, 1991). We leave further generalization of the idea of distinctive features among thematic roles to future work. 3 Experimental Verb Classes For the experimental investigation of our feature space, we selected a number of verb classes that would be non-trivial test cases for evaluating the method. Both for practical reasons and to make the results of general interest, the classes could neither be too small nor contain mostly infrequent verbs. Pairs or triples of verb classes were selected to form the test pairs/triples for each of a number of separate classification tasks. To illustrate the range of</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dowty, 1991</marker>
<rawString>David R. Dowty. 1991. Thematic proto-roles and argument selection. Language, 67(3):547-619.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
<author>Daniel Jurafsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic labeling of semantic roles.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>28--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1501" citStr="Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002" startWordPosition="220" endWordPosition="223">s show that the approach is generally applicable, and avoids the need for resource-intensive linguistic analysis for each new task. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statisti</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gildea, Jurafsky, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Daniel Gildea and Daniel Jurafsky. 2002. Automatic labeling of semantic roles. Computational Linguistics, 28(3):245-288.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maria Lapata</author>
<author>Chris Brew</author>
</authors>
<title>Using subcategorization to resolve verb class ambiguity.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in NLP and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-99),</booktitle>
<pages>266--274</pages>
<editor>In P. Fung and J. Zhou, editors,</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="1623" citStr="Lapata and Brew, 1999" startWordPosition="237" endWordPosition="240">ask. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statistics. However, the approach was limited in scope by the need for manual determination of a discriminating set of features, t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lapata, Brew, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Maria Lapata and Chris Brew. 1999. Using subcategorization to resolve verb class ambiguity. In P. Fung and J. Zhou, editors, Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in NLP and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-99), pages 266-274.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Beth Levin</author>
</authors>
<title>English verb classes and alternations: A preliminary investigation. Chicago UP.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<contexts>
<context position="2538" citStr="Levin (1993)" startWordPosition="388" endWordPosition="389">semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statistics. However, the approach was limited in scope by the need for manual determination of a discriminating set of features, through a linguistic analysis of the target verb classes. Our work overcomes this limitation by developing a general feature space that avoids the need for individual development of features for specific classes. The central idea of our approach is as follows. We focus on lexical semantic classes as in Levin (1993) (hereafter Levin), which group together verbs sharing both a common semantics (such as manner of motion or change of state), and a set of syntactic alternations. An alternation refers to the alternative mappings of the semantic arguments of a verb to syntactic positions, as in: la. I loaded the truck b. I loaded hay onto the truck. In Merlo and Stevenson (2001) (hereafter MS01), the differences between the specific semantic arguments and their possible alternations for the three target classes were analyzed to determine a small set of discriminating features. Here, we perform the linguistic a</context>
<context position="6213" citStr="Levin, 1993" startWordPosition="982" endWordPosition="983">meNet project, http://www.icsi.berkeley. edur framenet/). ysis underlying the features in our general feature space, the classes chosen for demonstrating its effectiveness, and our experimental procedures and results. We conclude with a discussion of related work, as well as limitations and planned extensions of our approach. 2 The Feature Space Recall that lexical semantic classes as in Levin form a hierarchy of verb groupings with shared meaning and syntax. The constraints on mapping semantic arguments to syntactic positions reflect underlying semantic properties of the verbs (Pinker, 1989; Levin, 1993). Thus alternations, such as those in (1) above, in which the same argument (hay or truck) is mapped to different positions, are particularly useful in distinguishing verb classes. MS01 further note the importance of the differing semantic (thematic) roles assigned by verbs for distinguishing the classes. The features in MS01, and those of our general feature space, were designed to tap into the differences between classes both in the alternations they allow, and in the thematic roles assigned. To this end, we generalized the features from MS01, and extended them by considering the full set of</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Levin, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Beth Levin. 1993. English verb classes and alternations: A preliminary investigation. Chicago UP.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Diana McCarthy</author>
</authors>
<title>Using semantic preferences to identify verbal participation in role switching alternations.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First Conference of the North American Ch. of the ACL (NAACL-2000).</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="7489" citStr="McCarthy, 2000" startWordPosition="1192" endWordPosition="1193">oss a wider range of verb class variability. Specifically, we drew on Part I of Levin, which elaborates the alternations she uses to characterize verb classes, in contrast to Part II, which enumerates the classes themselves. The feature space is summarized in Table 1, and described in detail in the rest of this section. All frequency counts are normalized by the total number of occurrences of the verb (or, in some cases, a relevant subset). 2.1 Features over Syntactic Slots Syntactic alternations play a central role in defining classes, but are difficult to detect automatically from a corpus (McCarthy, 2000). We have devised several types of features that tap into different aspects of alternation behaviour. One set of features encodes the frequency of the syntactic slots containing verbal arguments in Levin\&apos;s classes (subject, direct and indirect object, and prepositional phrases), thus approximating the allowable syntac164 \x0c in Text Feature Category #Features Syntactic slots 76 2.1 Slot overlap 40 &quot;Empty&quot; words 4 Passive 2 2.2 POS of the verb 6 Aux, modal, Adv 13 Derived forms 3 2.3 Animacy of NPs 76 Table 1: Feature categories with number of features of each type. tic frames for a verb.2 Fo</context>
<context position="8748" citStr="McCarthy, 2000" startWordPosition="1400" endWordPosition="1401">feature for each of 51 high frequency prepositions, as well as 19 groups of closely related prepositions (e.g., between, in between, among, amongst, amid, and amidst form one group). We also count verb uses where any prepositional phrase occurs. Using syntactic frame information alone misses critical properties of alternations, since two verbs may occur in the same frames but undergo different mappings of their arguments to the positions. Earlier work has used a measure of overlap over nouns in syntactic slots as a noisy indicator of participation in an alternation (Stevenson and Merlo, 1999; McCarthy, 2000). The idea is that since the same semantic argument may occur in two different slots in a pair of alternating frames, the degree to which those two slots contain the same entities is an indication of the verb\&apos;s participation in the alternation. In our feature space, we consider the overlap between each pair of slots that corresponds to an alternation in Part I of Levin (i.e., 1-8). For each alternation in which a semantic argument occurs in one slot in one usage of the verb (such as subject in The sky cleared), and in a different slot in the alternant usage (such as object of from in The clou</context>
<context position="25268" citStr="McCarthy (2000)" startWordPosition="4215" endWordPosition="4217">adopt the approach of MS01, which instead approximates such knowledge through statistical corpus analysis, allowing for easier extensibility to new classes. Furthermore, rather than using a class-by-class analysis as in Dorr and Jones (1996), our features are determined through an analysis of the possible alternations for verbs independent of their class assignment, leading to a more general set of features. Our study generalizes the slot overlap feature of MS01 as an indicator of membership in a verb class, on the assumption that slot overlap is correlated with alternation behaviour. Indeed, McCarthy (2000) confirmed this relation, showing includes a broad range of indicators of syntactic behaviours. These indicators may help to discriminate classes even if they are not conceived of as core distinctions between the classes. 6This approach recognizes the important challenge faced by our method in having to automatically select the best features for a task from our large feature space. Admittedly, it does not address the possibility that a linguist may devise a feature for which we have no analogue. that a slot overlap feature similar to ours could be a useful indicator for a given alternation. Mc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>McCarthy, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Diana McCarthy. 2000. Using semantic preferences to identify verbal participation in role switching alternations. In Proceedings of the First Conference of the North American Ch. of the ACL (NAACL-2000).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Paola Merlo</author>
<author>Suzanne Stevenson</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic verb classification based on statistical distributions of argument structure.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>27--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1675" citStr="Merlo and Stevenson, 2001" startWordPosition="245" endWordPosition="248">essing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statistics. However, the approach was limited in scope by the need for manual determination of a discriminating set of features, through a linguistic analysis of the target verb clas</context>
<context position="2902" citStr="Merlo and Stevenson (2001)" startWordPosition="448" endWordPosition="451">es. Our work overcomes this limitation by developing a general feature space that avoids the need for individual development of features for specific classes. The central idea of our approach is as follows. We focus on lexical semantic classes as in Levin (1993) (hereafter Levin), which group together verbs sharing both a common semantics (such as manner of motion or change of state), and a set of syntactic alternations. An alternation refers to the alternative mappings of the semantic arguments of a verb to syntactic positions, as in: la. I loaded the truck b. I loaded hay onto the truck. In Merlo and Stevenson (2001) (hereafter MS01), the differences between the specific semantic arguments and their possible alternations for the three target classes were analyzed to determine a small set of discriminating features. Here, we perform the linguistic analysis at a higher level, by analyzing the range of possible alternations and distinctions among arguments that verbs can exhibit. with hay 163 \x0cAs an illustrative example, MS01 determined that an informative statistical feature is the proportion of animate subjects used with a verb, since animacy is correlated with agenthood, and their verb classes differed</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Merlo, Stevenson, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Paola Merlo and Suzanne Stevenson. 2001. Automatic verb classification based on statistical distributions of argument structure. Computational Linguistics, 27(3):373-408.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Paola Merlo</author>
<author>Suzanne Stevenson</author>
<author>Vivian Tsang</author>
<author>Gianluca Allaria</author>
</authors>
<title>A multilingual paradigm for automatic verb classification.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>207--214</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4689" citStr="Merlo et al., 2002" startWordPosition="741" endWordPosition="744">aving to do the individual analysis for every set of classes that we want to distinguish. It is worth emphasizing that we do not base our features directly on all the existing Levin classes (cf. Don and Jones 1996)we instead analyze possible alternations for verbs independent of the actual classes. The result is a general classification feature space that in principle is useful for any Levin-type verb classification task. 1 The generality of our feature space enables experiments on a wider range of classes than has previously been attempted with the approach in MS01 and subsequent extensions (Merlo et al., 2002). We demonstrate the applicability of the feature space to distinctions among 14 classes, including ten new classes in addition to the target classes on which the method was originally developed. To preview our results below, we achieve reductions in error rate ranging from 42% to 69%, averaging more than 50% over all the tasks, demonstrating the potential of the approach for a wide range of classes. Furthermore, the performance compares favourably with sets of features handselected for the particular class distinctions, supporting our claim that the general feature space can replace the time-</context>
<context position="28547" citStr="Merlo et al. (2002)" startWordPosition="4731" endWordPosition="4734">tions. We also believe it will be straightforward to extend the feature space to cover additional alternations 169 \x0cnot in the scope of Levin (such as those involving sentential arguments), through the same process of generalizing the existing features to new slots. Still, our investigation has been limited to English verb classes, and our feature space is limited in being motivated by alternations in English. It thus lacks grammatical features (e.g., Case or other rich morphological properties) used in other languages to mark arguments or indicate the relation between them. Interestingly, Merlo et al. (2002) showed that some of the hand-crafted features of MS01 were useful in Italian for classifying the same verb classes in that language. We think a more general feature space such as ours will have even more potential for crosslinguistic applicability: We have devised a mapping of Levin\&apos;s analysis of the variation in expression of arguments across classes in English to a general set of features. To the extent that Levin\&apos;s analysis is grounded in general principles concerning the linking of semantic arguments to their syntactic expression, our feature space is an initial step in capturing variat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Merlo, Stevenson, Tsang, Allaria, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Paola Merlo, Suzanne Stevenson, Vivian Tsang, and Gianluca Allaria. 2002. A multilingual paradigm for automatic verb classification. In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 207-214.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Akira Oishi</author>
<author>Yuji Matsumoto</author>
</authors>
<title>Detecting the organization of semantic subclasses of japanese verbs.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<journal>International Journal of Corpus Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>2--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="26960" citStr="Oishi and Matsumoto (1997)" startWordPosition="4477" endWordPosition="4480">s. Our feature space is more general because it uses a combination of types of features; we have features intended to indicate participation in alternations, and not just subcategorization. While our method used supervised learning, Stevenson and Merlo (1999) found little difference in performance between unsupervised and supervised approaches on the original MS01 task. However, since unsupervised methods are more sensitive to irrelevant features, additional care will be required to determine useful subsets of features from our (larger) general feature space. Also using unsupervised learning, Oishi and Matsumoto (1997) clustered Japanese verbs automatically into hundreds of semantic classes, which they then combined into a network of 38 classes using linguistic knowledge and semi-automated processing. Their approach, like ours, used a combination of syntactic frame and aspectual features, but a limited set. Our work aims to extend this type of hand-picked feature space to achieve a generality that will limit the need for human expert input in the classification process. 7 Conclusion We achieve very good accuracies across a range of class distinctions, strongly supporting our approach of devising a general f</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Oishi, Matsumoto, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Akira Oishi and Yuji Matsumoto. 1997. Detecting the organization of semantic subclasses of japanese verbs. International Journal of Corpus Linguistics, 2(1):65-89.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Steven Pinker</author>
</authors>
<title>Learnability and cognition: the acquisition of argument structure.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="6199" citStr="Pinker, 1989" startWordPosition="980" endWordPosition="981"> as in the FrameNet project, http://www.icsi.berkeley. edur framenet/). ysis underlying the features in our general feature space, the classes chosen for demonstrating its effectiveness, and our experimental procedures and results. We conclude with a discussion of related work, as well as limitations and planned extensions of our approach. 2 The Feature Space Recall that lexical semantic classes as in Levin form a hierarchy of verb groupings with shared meaning and syntax. The constraints on mapping semantic arguments to syntactic positions reflect underlying semantic properties of the verbs (Pinker, 1989; Levin, 1993). Thus alternations, such as those in (1) above, in which the same argument (hay or truck) is mapped to different positions, are particularly useful in distinguishing verb classes. MS01 further note the importance of the differing semantic (thematic) roles assigned by verbs for distinguishing the classes. The features in MS01, and those of our general feature space, were designed to tap into the differences between classes both in the alternations they allow, and in the thematic roles assigned. To this end, we generalized the features from MS01, and extended them by considering t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pinker, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Steven Pinker. 1989. Learnability and cognition: the acquisition of argument structure. MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J R Quinlan</author>
</authors>
<title>C4.5: Programs for Machine Learning.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann, CA.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="19316" citStr="Quinlan, 1993" startWordPosition="3195" endWordPosition="3197"> SCOL does not identify indirect objects, which we also require. We use TGrep2 (Rohde, 2002) to identify potential indirect objects by assuming that an object followed by a noun phrase which SCOL has left unattached is a double-object frame.4 From these extracted slots, we calculate all the features described in Section 2, yielding a vector of 220 normalized counts for each verb, which forms the input to the machine learning system. 4.4 Machine Learning Approach For all our experiments, we use the decisiontree induction system C5.0, release 1.16 (www.. rulequest . com), the successor of C4.5 (Quinlan, 1993), as our machine learning software. On our training sets, we use 10-fold cross-validation repeated 50 times to estimate classification accuracy. For these, we report the average accuracy 4 This method of indirect object extraction had very low precision (.22 on a random sample), but produced useful features despite the high level of noise. 167 \x0cExperiment Baseline Acc N Test Verbs All features Levin-derived subsets Train Acc SE Test Acc\t (#) Train Ace SE Test Ace\t (#) Benefactive/Recipient 50.0 22 74.1 0.6 72.7 (16) 79.5 0.6 86.4 (19) Admire/Amuse 50.0 129 79.6 0.6 82.2 (106) 80.8 0.5 90.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Quinlan, 1993</marker>
<rawString>J. R. Quinlan. 1993. C4.5: Programs for Machine Learning. Morgan Kaufmann, CA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Philip Resnik</author>
</authors>
<title>Selectional constraints: an information-theoretic model and its computational realization.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<journal>Cognition,</journal>
<pages>61--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1541" citStr="Resnik, 1996" startWordPosition="226" endWordPosition="227"> avoids the need for resource-intensive linguistic analysis for each new task. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statistics. However, the approach was limited in</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Resnik, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Philip Resnik. 1996. Selectional constraints: an information-theoretic model and its computational realization. Cognition, 61(1-2):127-159.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ellen Riloff</author>
<author>Mark Schmelzenbach</author>
</authors>
<title>An empirical approach to conceptual case frame acquisition.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora (WVLC-98).</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="1473" citStr="Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998" startWordPosition="216" endWordPosition="219">classification tasks. Our results show that the approach is generally applicable, and avoids the need for resource-intensive linguistic analysis for each new task. 1 Introduction Wide-coverage language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Riloff, Schmelzenbach, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Ellen Riloff and Mark Schmelzenbach. 1998. An empirical approach to conceptual case frame acquisition. In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora (WVLC-98).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Douglas L T Rohde</author>
</authors>
<title>TGrep2 user manual version 1.3. Available with the TGrep2 package at http://tedlab.mit.edu/ -</title>
<date>2002</date>
<pages>2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="18794" citStr="Rohde, 2002" startWordPosition="3110" endWordPosition="3111">een test verbs.) Our unseen test verbs then consist of all verbs remaining after the selection of training data, except those that had been used in the previous studies we build on. 4.3 Feature Extraction We use an existing tool to extract the verb group and syntactic slots on which our features are based. The partial (or chunking) parser of Abney (1991), called SCOL, allows us to extract subjects and direct objects with reasonable confidence, and to extract potential prepositional phrases associated with the verb. SCOL does not identify indirect objects, which we also require. We use TGrep2 (Rohde, 2002) to identify potential indirect objects by assuming that an object followed by a noun phrase which SCOL has left unattached is a double-object frame.4 From these extracted slots, we calculate all the features described in Section 2, yielding a vector of 220 normalized counts for each verb, which forms the input to the machine learning system. 4.4 Machine Learning Approach For all our experiments, we use the decisiontree induction system C5.0, release 1.16 (www.. rulequest . com), the successor of C4.5 (Quinlan, 1993), as our machine learning software. On our training sets, we use 10-fold cross</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rohde, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Douglas L. T. Rohde. 2002. TGrep2 user manual version 1.3. Available with the TGrep2 package at http://tedlab.mit.edu/ - dr/Tgrep2/.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sabine Schulte im Walde</author>
</authors>
<title>Clustering verbs semantically according to their alternation behaviour.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<contexts>
<context position="1647" citStr="Walde, 2000" startWordPosition="243" endWordPosition="244">language processing systems require large amounts of knowledge about individual words, leading to a lexical acquisition bottleneck. Because verbs play a central role in the syntactic and semantic interpretation of a sentence, much research has focused on automatically learning properties of verbs from text corpora, such as their subcategorization (Brent, 1993; Briscoe and Carroll, 1997), argument roles (Riloff and Schmelzenbach, 1998; Gildea and Jurafsky, 2002), selectional preferences (Resnik, 1996), and lexical semantic classification (Dorr and Jones, 1996; Lapata and Brew, 1999; Schulte im Walde, 2000; Merlo and Stevenson, 2001). Our work aims to extend the applicability of the latter, by developing a general feature space for automatic verb classification. Specifically, Merlo and Stevenson (2001) showed that verbs could be automatically classified into one of three lexical semantic classes on the basis of five simple statistical features. This work demonstrated the feasibility of verb classification from noisy, easily extractable corpus statistics. However, the approach was limited in scope by the need for manual determination of a discriminating set of features, through a linguistic anal</context>
<context position="26155" citStr="Walde (2000)" startWordPosition="4359" endWordPosition="4360">ed by our method in having to automatically select the best features for a task from our large feature space. Admittedly, it does not address the possibility that a linguist may devise a feature for which we have no analogue. that a slot overlap feature similar to ours could be a useful indicator for a given alternation. McCarthy achieved an increase in performance on her task by using an alternative similarity measure over the selectional preference of a verb for two slots that alternate, indicating that other formulations of slot similarity may be useful to pursue in future work. Schulte im Walde (2000) and Schulte im Walde and Brew (2002) achieved promising results using unsupervised clustering of verbs in English and German, respectively, according to syntactic frame statistics. Our feature space is more general because it uses a combination of types of features; we have features intended to indicate participation in alternations, and not just subcategorization. While our method used supervised learning, Stevenson and Merlo (1999) found little difference in performance between unsupervised and supervised approaches on the original MS01 task. However, since unsupervised methods are more sen</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Walde, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Sabine Schulte im Walde. 2000. Clustering verbs semantically according to their alternation behaviour.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING2000),</booktitle>
<pages>747--753</pages>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>In Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING2000), pages 747-753.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sabine Schulte im Walde</author>
<author>Chris Brew</author>
</authors>
<title>Inducing German semantic verb classes from purely syntactic subcategorisation information.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>223--230</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="26192" citStr="Walde and Brew (2002)" startWordPosition="4364" endWordPosition="4367">o automatically select the best features for a task from our large feature space. Admittedly, it does not address the possibility that a linguist may devise a feature for which we have no analogue. that a slot overlap feature similar to ours could be a useful indicator for a given alternation. McCarthy achieved an increase in performance on her task by using an alternative similarity measure over the selectional preference of a verb for two slots that alternate, indicating that other formulations of slot similarity may be useful to pursue in future work. Schulte im Walde (2000) and Schulte im Walde and Brew (2002) achieved promising results using unsupervised clustering of verbs in English and German, respectively, according to syntactic frame statistics. Our feature space is more general because it uses a combination of types of features; we have features intended to indicate participation in alternations, and not just subcategorization. While our method used supervised learning, Stevenson and Merlo (1999) found little difference in performance between unsupervised and supervised approaches on the original MS01 task. However, since unsupervised methods are more sensitive to irrelevant features, additi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Walde, Brew, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Sabine Schulte im Walde and Chris Brew. 2002. Inducing German semantic verb classes from purely syntactic subcategorisation information. In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 223-230.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Suzanne Stevenson</author>
<author>Paola Merlo</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic verb classification using grammatical features.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Ninth Conference of the European Chapter of the ACL (EACL-99),</booktitle>
<pages>45--52</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8731" citStr="Stevenson and Merlo, 1999" startWordPosition="1396" endWordPosition="1399">hrases, we have a separate feature for each of 51 high frequency prepositions, as well as 19 groups of closely related prepositions (e.g., between, in between, among, amongst, amid, and amidst form one group). We also count verb uses where any prepositional phrase occurs. Using syntactic frame information alone misses critical properties of alternations, since two verbs may occur in the same frames but undergo different mappings of their arguments to the positions. Earlier work has used a measure of overlap over nouns in syntactic slots as a noisy indicator of participation in an alternation (Stevenson and Merlo, 1999; McCarthy, 2000). The idea is that since the same semantic argument may occur in two different slots in a pair of alternating frames, the degree to which those two slots contain the same entities is an indication of the verb\&apos;s participation in the alternation. In our feature space, we consider the overlap between each pair of slots that corresponds to an alternation in Part I of Levin (i.e., 1-8). For each alternation in which a semantic argument occurs in one slot in one usage of the verb (such as subject in The sky cleared), and in a different slot in the alternant usage (such as object of</context>
<context position="26593" citStr="Stevenson and Merlo (1999)" startWordPosition="4426" endWordPosition="4429">ver the selectional preference of a verb for two slots that alternate, indicating that other formulations of slot similarity may be useful to pursue in future work. Schulte im Walde (2000) and Schulte im Walde and Brew (2002) achieved promising results using unsupervised clustering of verbs in English and German, respectively, according to syntactic frame statistics. Our feature space is more general because it uses a combination of types of features; we have features intended to indicate participation in alternations, and not just subcategorization. While our method used supervised learning, Stevenson and Merlo (1999) found little difference in performance between unsupervised and supervised approaches on the original MS01 task. However, since unsupervised methods are more sensitive to irrelevant features, additional care will be required to determine useful subsets of features from our (larger) general feature space. Also using unsupervised learning, Oishi and Matsumoto (1997) clustered Japanese verbs automatically into hundreds of semantic classes, which they then combined into a network of 38 classes using linguistic knowledge and semi-automated processing. Their approach, like ours, used a combination </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Stevenson, Merlo, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Suzanne Stevenson and Paola Merlo. 1999. Automatic verb classification using grammatical features. In Proceedings of the Ninth Conference of the European Chapter of the ACL (EACL-99), pages 45-52.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>