<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<figure confidence="0.534854">
b&apos;Proceedings of NAACL-HLT 2013, pages 534539,
Atlanta, Georgia, 914 June 2013. c
2013 Association for Computational Linguistics
Predicative Adjectives: An Unsupervised Criterion to Extract Subjective
Adjectives
Michael Wiegand
Spoken Language Systems
</figure>
<affiliation confidence="0.821399">
Saarland University
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.851623">
michael.wiegand@lsv.uni-saarland.de
</email>
<author confidence="0.840595">
Josef Ruppenhofer
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.764733666666667">
Dept. of Information Science
and Language Technology
Hildesheim University
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.314898">
ruppenho@uni-hildesheim.de
</email>
<author confidence="0.353211">
Dietrich Klakow
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.6317065">
Spoken Language Systems
Saarland University
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.971565">
dietrich.klakow@lsv.uni-saarland.de
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988454" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999339090909091">
We examine predicative adjectives as an unsu-
pervised criterion to extract subjective adjec-
tives. We do not only compare this criterion
with a weakly supervised extraction method
but also with gradable adjectives, i.e. another
highly subjective subset of adjectives that can
be extracted in an unsupervised fashion. In or-
der to prove the robustness of this extraction
method, we will evaluate the extraction with
the help of two different state-of-the-art senti-
ment lexicons (as a gold standard).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99795" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9065426">
Since the early work on sentiment analysis, it has
been established that the part of speech with the
highest proportion of subjective words are adjec-
tives (Wiebe et al., 2004) (see Sentence (1)). How-
ever, not all adjectives are subjective (2).
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.624153">
(1) A grumpy guest made some impolite remarks
to the insecure and inexperienced waitress.
(2) The old man wearing a yellow pullover sat on a
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.907267363636364">
plastic chair.
This justifies the exploration of criteria to automati-
cally separate the subjective adjectives from the non-
subjective adjectives.
In this work, we are interested in an out-of-
context assessment of adjectives and therefore eval-
uate them with the help of sentiment lexicons. We
examine the property of being a predicative adjec-
tive as an extraction criterion. Predicative adjectives
are adjectives that do not modify the head of a noun
phrase, but which predicate a property of the refer-
ent of a noun phrase to which they are linked via a
copula or a control predicate (3).
We show that adjectives that frequently occur as
predicative adjectives are more likely to convey sub-
jectivity (in general) than adjectives that occur non-
predicatively, such as the pre-nominal (attributive)
adjectives (4). A subjective adjective may occur
both as a predicative (3) and a non-predicative (5)
adjective and also convey subjectivity in both con-
texts. However, a large fraction of non-subjective
adjectives do not occur as predicative adjectives (6).
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9997435">
(3) Her idea was brilliant.
(4) This is a financial problem.
(5) She came up with a brilliant idea.
(6) ?The problem is financial.
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99667" genericHeader="related work">
2 Related Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9995898">
The extraction of subjective adjectives has already
attracted some considerable attention in previous re-
search. Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997) ex-
tract polar adjectives by a weakly supervised method
in which subjective adjectives are found by search-
ing for adjectives that are conjuncts of a pre-defined
set of polar seed adjectives. Wiebe (2000) in-
duces subjective adjectives with the help of distribu-
tional similarity. Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe (2000)
examine the properties of dynamic, gradable and
polar adjectives as a means to detect subjectivity.
Vegnaduzzo (2004) presents another bootstrapping
method of extracting subjective adjectives with the
help of head nouns of the subjective candidates and
distributional similarity. Baroni and Vegnaduzzo
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99795">
534
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.476809333333333">
\x0c(2004) employ Web-based Mutual information for
this task and largely outperform the results produced
by Vegnaduzzo (2004).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993257" genericHeader="method">
3 Method
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998178">
In the following, we present different features with
the help of which subjective adjectives can be ex-
tracted. For all resulting lists, the adjectives will be
ranked according to their frequency of co-occurring
with a particular feature.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999873">
3.1 Extracting Predicative Adjectives (PRD)
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.896343571428571">
For the extraction of predicative adjectives, we ex-
clusively rely on the output of a dependency parser.
Predicative adjectives are usually connected to the
subject of the sentence via the dependency label
nsubj (Example (7) would correspond to Sen-
tence (3)).
(7) nsubj(brilliant, idea)
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999754">
3.2 Extracting Gradable Adjectives (GRD)
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982790454545454">
As an alternative extraction method, we consider
morpho-syntactically gradable adjectives. Gradable
adjectives, such as nice or small, are adjectives that
can be inflected to specify the degree or grade of
something (Wiktionary1). It has been stated in pre-
vious work that if some adjective can build a com-
parative (e.g. nicer) or a superlative (e.g. nicest),
then this adjective tends to be subjective (Hatzivas-
siloglou and Wiebe, 2000).
We employ the property of gradability, since,
firstly, it is very predictive towards subjectivity and,
secondly, it is the only other unsupervised criterion
currently known to extract subjective adjectives. For
the extraction of gradable adjectives, we rely, on the
one hand, on the part-of-speech labels JJR (com-
parative) and JJS (superlative). On the other hand,
we also consider adjectives being modified by ei-
ther more or most. For the former case, we need
to normalize the comparative (e.g. nicer) or superla-
tive (e.g. nicest) word form to the canonical positive
word form (e.g. nice) that is commonly used in sen-
timent lexicons.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.6211915">
1
http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/gradable
</footnote>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.94317">
3.3 Weakly-Supervised Extraction (WKS)
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985270166666667">
We also consider a weakly supervised extraction
method in this paper, even though it is not strictly
fair to compare such a method with our two pre-
vious extraction methods which are completely un-
supervised. WKS considers an adjective subjective,
if it co-occurs as a conjunct of a previously defined
highly subjective (seed) adjective (8). In order to de-
tect such conjunctions, we employ the dependency
relation conj. By just relying on surface patterns,
we would not be able to exclude spurious conjunc-
tions in which other constituents than the two adjec-
tives are coordinated, such as Sentence (10).
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.98892375">
(8) This approach is ill-conceived and ineffective.
(9) conj(ill-conceived,
ineffective)
(10) [Evil witches are stereotypically dressed in
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.953428285714286">
black] and [good fairies in white].
We also experimented with other related weakly-
supervised extraction methods, such as mutual in-
formation of two adjectives at the sentence level (or
even smaller window sizes). However, using con-
junctions largely outperformed these alternative ap-
proaches so we only pursue conjunctions here.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999464" genericHeader="evaluation">
4 Experiments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996658315789474">
As a large unlabeled (training) corpus, we chose the
North American News Text Corpus (LDC95T21)
comprising approximately 350 million words of
news text. For syntactic analysis we use the Stan-
ford Parser (Finkel et al., 2005). In order to decide
whether an extracted adjective is subjective or not,
we employ two sentiment lexicons, namely the Sub-
jectivity Lexicon (SUB) (Wilson et al., 2005) and
SO-CAL (SOC) (Taboada et al., 2011). According to
the recent in-depth evaluation presented in Taboada
et al. (2011), these two sentiment lexicons are the
most effective resources for English sentiment anal-
ysis. By taking into account two different lexicons,
which have also been built independently of each
other, we want to provide evidence that our pro-
posed criterion to extract subjective adjectives is not
sensitive towards a particular gold standard (which
would challenge the general validity of the proposed
method).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991956">
535
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.942099777777778">
\x0cALL other new last many first such next political federal own sev-
eral few good former same economic public major recent
American second big foreign high small local military fi-
nancial little national
PRD able likely available clear difficult important ready
willing hard good due possible sure interested un-
likely necessary high responsible easy strong unable
different enough open aware happy impossible right
wrong confident
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.91495">
Table 2: The 30 most frequent adjectives (ALL) and pred-
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.965501428571429">
icative adjectives (PRD);
marks matches with both sen-
timent lexicons SUB and SOC.
In order to produce the subjective seed adjec-
tives for the weakly supervised extraction, we col-
lect from the sentiment lexicon that we evaluate the
n most frequent subjective adjectives according to
our corpus. In order to further improve the quality
of the seed set, we only consider strong subjective
expressions from SUB and expressions with the in-
tensity strength 5 from SOC.
Table 1 lists the size of the different sentiment lex-
icons and the rankings produced by the different ex-
traction methods. Of course, the list of all adjectives
from the corpus (ALL) is the largest list2 while PRD
is the second largest and GRD the third largest. The
rankings produced by WKS are fairly sparse, in par-
ticular the ones induced with the help of SOC; ap-
parently there are more frequently occurring strong
subjective adjectives in SUB than there are high in-
tensity adjectives in SOC.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9792925">
4.1 Frequent Adjectives vs. Frequent
Predicative Adjectives
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989047818181818">
Table 2 compares the 30 most frequent adjectives
(ALL) and predicative adjectives (PRD). Not only
does this table show that the proportion of subjective
adjectives is much larger among the predicative ad-
jectives but we may also gain some insight into what
non-subjective adjectives are excluded. Among the
high frequent adjectives are many quantifiers (many,
few and several) and ordinal expressions (first, next
and last). In principle, most of these expressions
are not subjective. One may argue that these adjec-
tives behave like function words. Since they occur
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.933723">
2
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998708111111111">
It will also contain many words erroneously tagged as ad-
jectives, however, this is unlikely to affect our experiments since
we only focus on the highly ranked (i.e. most frequent) words.
The misclassifications rather concern infrequent words.
very frequently, one might exclude some of them
by just ignoring the most frequent adjectives. How-
ever, there are also other types of adjectives, espe-
cially pertainyms (political, federal, economic, pub-
lic, American, foreign, local, military, financial and
national) that appear on this list which could not be
excluded by that heuristic. We found that these non-
subjective content adjectives are present throughout
the entire ranking and they are fairly frequent (on
the ranking). On the list of predicative adjectives all
these previous types of adjectives are much less fre-
quent. Many of them only occur on lower ranks (and
we assume that several of them only got on the list
due to parsing errors).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9905945">
4.2 Comparison of the Different Extraction
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998215838709677">
Table 3 compares the precision of the different ex-
traction methods at different cut-off values. It is in-
teresting to see that for ALL in particular the higher
ranks are worse than the lower ranks (e.g. rank
1000). We assume that this is due to the high-
frequency adjectives which are similar to function
words (see Section 4.1). At all cut-off values, how-
ever, this baseline is beaten by every other method,
including our proposed method PRD. The two unsu-
pervised methods PRD and GRD perform on a par
with each other. On SUB, PRD even mostly out-
performs GRD. The precision achieved by WKS is
quite good. However, the coverage of this method
is low. It would require more seed expressions to
increase it, however, this would also mean consider-
ably more manual guidance.
Table 3 also shows that the precision of all ex-
traction methods largely drops on the lower ranks.
However, one should not conclude from that the ex-
traction methods proposed only work well for highly
frequent words. The drop can be mostly explained
by the fact that the two sentiment lexicons we use
for evaluation are finite (i.e. SUB: 4396 words/SOC:
2827 words (Table 1)), and that neither of these lexi-
cons (nor their union) represents the complete set of
all English subjective adjectives. Both lexicons will
have a bias towards frequently occurring subjective
expressions.
Inspecting the ranks 3001-3020 produced by PRD
as displayed in Table 4, for example, actually reveals
that there are still many more subjective adjectives
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998876">
536
</page>
<table confidence="0.9957395">
\x0cLexicons Extraction Methods
WKS-5 WKS-10 WKS-25 WKS-50
SUB SOC ALL PRD GRD SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC
4396 2827 212287 20793 7942 292 81 440 131 772 319 1035 385
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.962896142857143">
Table 1: Statistics regarding the size (i.e. number of adjectives) of the different sentiment lexicons and rankings.
artistic appealable airtight adjustable activist accommodat-
ing acclimated well-meaning weakest upsetting unsurpassed
unsatisfying unopposed unobtrusive unobjectionable unem-
ployable understanding uncharacteristic submerged speechless
Table 4: A set of entries PRD produces on lower ranks
(ranks 3001-3020);
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.975533620689655">
marks matches with either of the
sentiment lexicons SUB or SOC.
than the matches with our sentiment lexicons sug-
gest (e.g. appealable, accomodating, well-meaning,
weakest, unsurpassed, unopposed, unobjectionable,
unemployable, uncharacteristic or speechless). In
other words, these are less frequent words; many
of them are actually subjective even though they are
not listed in the sentiment lexicons. Moreover, irre-
spective of the drop in precision on the lower ranks,
PRD and GRD still outperform ALL on both senti-
ment lexicons (Table 3). Despite the sparseness of
our two gold standards on the lower ranks, we thus
have some indication that PRD and GRD are more
effective than ALL.
The problem of the evaluation of less-frequent
words could not be solved by an extrinsic evaluation,
either, e.g. by using the extracted lists for some text
classification task (at the sentence/document level).
The evaluation on contextual classification on cor-
pora would also be biased towards high-frequency
words (as the word distribution is typically Zipfian).
For instance, on the MPQA-corpus (Wiebe et al.,
2005), i.e. the standard dataset for (fine-grained)
sentiment analysis, there is not a single mention of
the subjective words appealable, accommodating,
unsurpassed, unopposed, unobtrusive or speechless,
which were found among the lower ranks 3001-
3020.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.984946">
4.3 How Different Are Gradable and
Predicative Adjectives?
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999497875">
Since in the previous experiments the proportion of
subjective adjectives was similar among the grad-
able adjectives and the predicative adjectives, we
may wonder whether these two extraction methods
produce the same adjectives. In principle, the set of
gradable adjectives extracted is much smaller than
the list of extracted predicative adjectives (see Ta-
ble 1). We found that the gradable adjectives are
a proper subset of predicative adjectives, which is
in line with the observation by (Bolinger, 1972,
21) that gradable adjectives (which he calls degree
words) readily occur predicatively whereas non-
gradable ones tend not to.
However, while gradability implies compatibility
with predicative use, the reverse is not true. Ac-
cordingly, we found adjectives that are definitely not
gradable among the predicative adjectives that are
subjective, for instance endless, insolvent, nonexis-
tent, stagnant, unavailable or untrue. This means
that with the criterion of predicative adjectives one
is able to extract relevant subjective adjectives that
cannot be caught by the gradability criterion alone,
namely complementary adjectives that refer to a sim-
ple binary opposition (Cruse, 1986, 198-99).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9023985">
4.4 Intersecting the Different Unsupervised
Criteria
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999179">
In this section, we want to find out whether we can
increase the precision by considering intersections
of the two different unsupervised extraction crite-
ria. (Due to the sparsity of WKS, it does not make
sense to include that method in this experiment.) In
our previous experiments it turned out that as far as
precision is concerned, our new proposed extraction
criterion was similar to the gradability criterion. If,
however, the intersection of these two criteria pro-
duces better results, then we have provided some
further proof of the effectiveness of our proposed
criterion (even though we may sacrifice some exclu-
sive subjective adjectives in PRD as pointed out in
Section 4.3). It would mean that this criterion is also
beneficial in the presence of the gradability criterion.
Figure 1 shows the corresponding results. We
computed the intersection of PRD and GRD at var-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996528">
537
</page>
<table confidence="0.982065461538462">
\x0cALL PRD GRD WKS-5 WKS-10 WKS-25 WKS-50
Rank n SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC SUB SOC
10 10.00 30.00 90.00 90.00 80.00 60.00 80.00 90.00 80.00 90.00 90.00 70.00 90.00 70.00
25 20.00 32.00 88.00 60.00 64.00 60.00 92.00 80.00 91.00 80.00 92.00 80.00 92.00 84.00
50 30.00 34.00 88.00 64.00 70.00 68.00 82.00 78.00 92.00 78.00 92.00 84.00 90.00 86.00
100 37.00 38.00 81.00 68.00 79.00 75.00 80.00 N/A 82.00 72.00 89.00 78.00 92.00 77.00
250 45.60 43.20 79.60 75.60 84.80 76.00 70.80 N/A 74.40 N/A 80.40 67.50 82.04 67.20
500 48.00 49.20 77.20 70.00 82.20 74.00 N/A N/A N/A N/A 72.60 N/A 75.20 N/A
1000 48.70 48.10 75.50 65.60 72.60 65.00 N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A 64.30 N/A
1500 49.07 46.53 68.60 59.07 66.27 58.60 N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A
2000 48.00 43.85 64.55 55.40 61.55 54.25 N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A
2500 46.08 40.96 59.52 51.28 56.36 50.00 N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A
3000 44.20 39.17 54.63 47.13 51.47 46.03 N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A N/A
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999262">
Table 3: Precision at rank n of the different extraction methods; WKS-m denotes that for the extraction the m most
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.995399888888889">
frequent subjective adjectives from the respective sentiment lexicon were considered as seed expressions.
ious cut-off values of n. The resulting intersection
comprises m ranks with m &lt; n. The precision of
the intersection was consequently compared against
the precision of PRD and GRD at rank m. The figure
shows that with the exception of the higher ranks on
SUB (&lt; 200) there is indeed a systematic increase
in precision when the intersection of PRD and GRD
is considered.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998347" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999948272727273">
We examined predicative adjectives as a criterion
to extract subjective adjectives. As this extraction
method is completely unsupervised, it is preferable
to weakly supervised extraction methods since we
are not dependent on a manually designed high qual-
ity seed set and we obtain a much larger set of ad-
jectives. This extraction method is competitive if
not slightly better than gradable adjectives. In ad-
dition, combining these two unsupervised methods
by assessing their intersection results mostly in an
increase in precision.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943987" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998681571428572">
This work was performed in the context of the Software-
Cluster project EMERGENT. Michael Wiegand was
funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education and
Research (BMBF) under grant no. 01IC10S01. The
authors would like to thank Maite Taboada for providing
her sentiment lexicon (SO-CAL) to be used for the exper-
iments presented in this paper.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.967571">
55
60
65
70
75
80
85
500 1000 1500 2000 2500
Precision
Top N Ranked Adjectives
Predicative Adjectives (PRD)
Gradable Adjectives (GRD)
Intersection of PRD and GRD
(a) Evaluation on SUB lexicon
50
55
60
65
70
75
80
500 1000 1500 2000 2500
Precision
Top N Ranked Adjectives
Predicative Adjectives (PRD)
Gradable Adjectives (GRD)
Intersection of PRD and GRD
(b) Evaluation on SOC lexicon
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.997138">
Figure 1: Comparison of the individual rankings of GRD
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.470888">
and PRD with their intersection.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.983304">
538
</page>
<reference confidence="0.997227647058823">
\x0cReferences
Marco Baroni and Stefano Vegnaduzzo. 2004. Identify-
ing Subjective Adjectives through Web-based Mutual
Information. In Proceedings of KONVENS, pages 17
24, Vienna, Austria.
Dwight Bolinger. 1972. Degree words. Mouton, The
Hague.
David Alan Cruse. 1986. Lexical Semantics. Cambridge
University Press, Cambridge, UK.
Jenny Rose Finkel, Trond Grenager, and Christopher
Manning. 2005. Incorporating Non-local Information
into Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sam-
pling. In Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the As-
sociation for Computational Linguistics (ACL), pages
363370, Ann Arbor, MI, USA.
Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou and Kathleen R. McKeown.
1997. Predicting the Semantic Orientation of Adjec-
tives. In Proceedings of the Conference on European
Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguis-
tics (EACL), pages 174181, Madrid, Spain.
Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou and Janyce Wiebe. 2000. Ef-
fects of Adjective Orientation and Gradability on Sen-
tence Subjectivity. In Proceedings of the International
Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING),
pages 299305, Saarbrucken, Germany.
Maite Taboada, Julian Brooke, Milan Tofiloski, Kimberly
Voll, and Manfred Stede. 2011. Lexicon-Based Meth-
ods for Sentiment Analysis. Computational Linguis-
tics, 37(2):267 307.
Stefano Vegnaduzzo. 2004. Acquisition of Subjective
Adjectives with Limited Resources. In Proceedings of
the AAAI Spring Symposium on Exploring Attitude and
Affect in Text: Theories and Applications, Stanford,
CA, USA.
Janyce Wiebe, Theresa Wilson, Rebecca Bruce, Matthew
Bell, and Melanie Martin. 2004. Learning Subjective
Language. Computational Linguistics, 30(3).
Janyce Wiebe, Theresa Wilson, and Claire Cardie. 2005.
Annotating Expressions of Opinions and Emotions
in Language. Language Resources and Evaluation,
39(2/3):164210.
Janyce M. Wiebe. 2000. Learning Subjective Adjectives
from Corpora. In Proceedings of the National Confer-
ence on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), pages 735740,
Austin, TX, USA.
Theresa Wilson, Janyce Wiebe, and Paul Hoffmann.
2005. Recognizing Contextual Polarity in Phrase-level
Sentiment Analysis. In Proceedings of the Conference
on Human Language Technology and Empirical Meth-
ods in Natural Language Processing (HLT/EMNLP),
pages 347354, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.978068">
539
</page>
<figure confidence="0.252847">
\x0c&apos;
</figure>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.497142">
<note confidence="0.880262666666667">b&apos;Proceedings of NAACL-HLT 2013, pages 534539, Atlanta, Georgia, 914 June 2013. c 2013 Association for Computational Linguistics</note>
<title confidence="0.931306">Predicative Adjectives: An Unsupervised Criterion to Extract Subjective Adjectives</title>
<author confidence="0.999313">Michael Wiegand</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9585585">Spoken Language Systems Saarland University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.953038">michael.wiegand@lsv.uni-saarland.de</email>
<author confidence="0.993224">Josef Ruppenhofer</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.999176333333333">Dept. of Information Science and Language Technology Hildesheim University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.975752">ruppenho@uni-hildesheim.de</email>
<author confidence="0.993185">Dietrich Klakow</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9730685">Spoken Language Systems Saarland University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.983666">dietrich.klakow@lsv.uni-saarland.de</email>
<abstract confidence="0.99843325">We examine predicative adjectives as an unsupervised criterion to extract subjective adjectives. We do not only compare this criterion with a weakly supervised extraction method but also with gradable adjectives, i.e. another highly subjective subset of adjectives that can be extracted in an unsupervised fashion. In order to prove the robustness of this extraction method, we will evaluate the extraction with the help of two different state-of-the-art sentiment lexicons (as a gold standard).</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>\x0cReferences Marco Baroni</author>
<author>Stefano Vegnaduzzo</author>
</authors>
<title>Identifying Subjective Adjectives through Web-based Mutual Information.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of KONVENS,</booktitle>
<pages>17--24</pages>
<location>Vienna, Austria.</location>
<marker>Baroni, Vegnaduzzo, 2004</marker>
<rawString>\x0cReferences Marco Baroni and Stefano Vegnaduzzo. 2004. Identifying Subjective Adjectives through Web-based Mutual Information. In Proceedings of KONVENS, pages 17 24, Vienna, Austria.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dwight Bolinger</author>
</authors>
<title>Degree words.</title>
<date>1972</date>
<location>Mouton, The Hague.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="14376" citStr="Bolinger, 1972" startWordPosition="2222" endWordPosition="2223">hich were found among the lower ranks 3001- 3020. 4.3 How Different Are Gradable and Predicative Adjectives? Since in the previous experiments the proportion of subjective adjectives was similar among the gradable adjectives and the predicative adjectives, we may wonder whether these two extraction methods produce the same adjectives. In principle, the set of gradable adjectives extracted is much smaller than the list of extracted predicative adjectives (see Table 1). We found that the gradable adjectives are a proper subset of predicative adjectives, which is in line with the observation by (Bolinger, 1972, 21) that gradable adjectives (which he calls degree words) readily occur predicatively whereas nongradable ones tend not to. However, while gradability implies compatibility with predicative use, the reverse is not true. Accordingly, we found adjectives that are definitely not gradable among the predicative adjectives that are subjective, for instance endless, insolvent, nonexistent, stagnant, unavailable or untrue. This means that with the criterion of predicative adjectives one is able to extract relevant subjective adjectives that cannot be caught by the gradability criterion alone, namel</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bolinger, 1972</marker>
<rawString>Dwight Bolinger. 1972. Degree words. Mouton, The Hague.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Alan Cruse</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical Semantics.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, UK.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="15056" citStr="Cruse, 1986" startWordPosition="2320" endWordPosition="2321">occur predicatively whereas nongradable ones tend not to. However, while gradability implies compatibility with predicative use, the reverse is not true. Accordingly, we found adjectives that are definitely not gradable among the predicative adjectives that are subjective, for instance endless, insolvent, nonexistent, stagnant, unavailable or untrue. This means that with the criterion of predicative adjectives one is able to extract relevant subjective adjectives that cannot be caught by the gradability criterion alone, namely complementary adjectives that refer to a simple binary opposition (Cruse, 1986, 198-99). 4.4 Intersecting the Different Unsupervised Criteria In this section, we want to find out whether we can increase the precision by considering intersections of the two different unsupervised extraction criteria. (Due to the sparsity of WKS, it does not make sense to include that method in this experiment.) In our previous experiments it turned out that as far as precision is concerned, our new proposed extraction criterion was similar to the gradability criterion. If, however, the intersection of these two criteria produces better results, then we have provided some further proof of</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cruse, 1986</marker>
<rawString>David Alan Cruse. 1986. Lexical Semantics. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jenny Rose Finkel</author>
<author>Trond Grenager</author>
<author>Christopher Manning</author>
</authors>
<title>Incorporating Non-local Information into Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sampling.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL),</booktitle>
<pages>363370</pages>
<location>Ann Arbor, MI, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6593" citStr="Finkel et al., 2005" startWordPosition="988" endWordPosition="991">ive) (10) [Evil witches are stereotypically dressed in black] and [good fairies in white]. We also experimented with other related weaklysupervised extraction methods, such as mutual information of two adjectives at the sentence level (or even smaller window sizes). However, using conjunctions largely outperformed these alternative approaches so we only pursue conjunctions here. 4 Experiments As a large unlabeled (training) corpus, we chose the North American News Text Corpus (LDC95T21) comprising approximately 350 million words of news text. For syntactic analysis we use the Stanford Parser (Finkel et al., 2005). In order to decide whether an extracted adjective is subjective or not, we employ two sentiment lexicons, namely the Subjectivity Lexicon (SUB) (Wilson et al., 2005) and SO-CAL (SOC) (Taboada et al., 2011). According to the recent in-depth evaluation presented in Taboada et al. (2011), these two sentiment lexicons are the most effective resources for English sentiment analysis. By taking into account two different lexicons, which have also been built independently of each other, we want to provide evidence that our proposed criterion to extract subjective adjectives is not sensitive towards </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Finkel, Grenager, Manning, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Jenny Rose Finkel, Trond Grenager, and Christopher Manning. 2005. Incorporating Non-local Information into Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sampling. In Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), pages 363370, Ann Arbor, MI, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou</author>
<author>Kathleen R McKeown</author>
</authors>
<title>Predicting the Semantic Orientation of Adjectives.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference on European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL),</booktitle>
<pages>174181</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2772" citStr="Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997)" startWordPosition="409" endWordPosition="412">) than adjectives that occur nonpredicatively, such as the pre-nominal (attributive) adjectives (4). A subjective adjective may occur both as a predicative (3) and a non-predicative (5) adjective and also convey subjectivity in both contexts. However, a large fraction of non-subjective adjectives do not occur as predicative adjectives (6). (3) Her idea was brilliant. (4) This is a financial problem. (5) She came up with a brilliant idea. (6) ?The problem is financial. 2 Related Work The extraction of subjective adjectives has already attracted some considerable attention in previous research. Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997) extract polar adjectives by a weakly supervised method in which subjective adjectives are found by searching for adjectives that are conjuncts of a pre-defined set of polar seed adjectives. Wiebe (2000) induces subjective adjectives with the help of distributional similarity. Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe (2000) examine the properties of dynamic, gradable and polar adjectives as a means to detect subjectivity. Vegnaduzzo (2004) presents another bootstrapping method of extracting subjective adjectives with the help of head nouns of the subjective candidates and distributional similarity. Baroni a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hatzivassiloglou, McKeown, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou and Kathleen R. McKeown. 1997. Predicting the Semantic Orientation of Adjectives. In Proceedings of the Conference on European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL), pages 174181, Madrid, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou</author>
<author>Janyce Wiebe</author>
</authors>
<title>Effects of Adjective Orientation and Gradability on Sentence Subjectivity.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING),</booktitle>
<pages>299305</pages>
<location>Saarbrucken, Germany.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3083" citStr="Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe (2000)" startWordPosition="457" endWordPosition="460"> predicative adjectives (6). (3) Her idea was brilliant. (4) This is a financial problem. (5) She came up with a brilliant idea. (6) ?The problem is financial. 2 Related Work The extraction of subjective adjectives has already attracted some considerable attention in previous research. Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997) extract polar adjectives by a weakly supervised method in which subjective adjectives are found by searching for adjectives that are conjuncts of a pre-defined set of polar seed adjectives. Wiebe (2000) induces subjective adjectives with the help of distributional similarity. Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe (2000) examine the properties of dynamic, gradable and polar adjectives as a means to detect subjectivity. Vegnaduzzo (2004) presents another bootstrapping method of extracting subjective adjectives with the help of head nouns of the subjective candidates and distributional similarity. Baroni and Vegnaduzzo 534 \x0c(2004) employ Web-based Mutual information for this task and largely outperform the results produced by Vegnaduzzo (2004). 3 Method In the following, we present different features with the help of which subjective adjectives can be extracted. For all resulting lists, the adjectives will b</context>
<context position="4571" citStr="Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe, 2000" startWordPosition="676" endWordPosition="680"> usually connected to the subject of the sentence via the dependency label nsubj (Example (7) would correspond to Sentence (3)). (7) nsubj(brilliant, idea) 3.2 Extracting Gradable Adjectives (GRD) As an alternative extraction method, we consider morpho-syntactically gradable adjectives. Gradable adjectives, such as nice or small, are adjectives that can be inflected to specify the degree or grade of something (Wiktionary1). It has been stated in previous work that if some adjective can build a comparative (e.g. nicer) or a superlative (e.g. nicest), then this adjective tends to be subjective (Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe, 2000). We employ the property of gradability, since, firstly, it is very predictive towards subjectivity and, secondly, it is the only other unsupervised criterion currently known to extract subjective adjectives. For the extraction of gradable adjectives, we rely, on the one hand, on the part-of-speech labels JJR (comparative) and JJS (superlative). On the other hand, we also consider adjectives being modified by either more or most. For the former case, we need to normalize the comparative (e.g. nicer) or superlative (e.g. nicest) word form to the canonical positive word form (e.g. nice) that is </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hatzivassiloglou, Wiebe, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou and Janyce Wiebe. 2000. Effects of Adjective Orientation and Gradability on Sentence Subjectivity. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), pages 299305, Saarbrucken, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maite Taboada</author>
<author>Julian Brooke</author>
<author>Milan Tofiloski</author>
<author>Kimberly Voll</author>
<author>Manfred Stede</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexicon-Based Methods for Sentiment Analysis.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>307</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6800" citStr="Taboada et al., 2011" startWordPosition="1022" endWordPosition="1025">ctives at the sentence level (or even smaller window sizes). However, using conjunctions largely outperformed these alternative approaches so we only pursue conjunctions here. 4 Experiments As a large unlabeled (training) corpus, we chose the North American News Text Corpus (LDC95T21) comprising approximately 350 million words of news text. For syntactic analysis we use the Stanford Parser (Finkel et al., 2005). In order to decide whether an extracted adjective is subjective or not, we employ two sentiment lexicons, namely the Subjectivity Lexicon (SUB) (Wilson et al., 2005) and SO-CAL (SOC) (Taboada et al., 2011). According to the recent in-depth evaluation presented in Taboada et al. (2011), these two sentiment lexicons are the most effective resources for English sentiment analysis. By taking into account two different lexicons, which have also been built independently of each other, we want to provide evidence that our proposed criterion to extract subjective adjectives is not sensitive towards a particular gold standard (which would challenge the general validity of the proposed method). 535 \x0cALL other new last many first such next political federal own several few good former same economic pub</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Taboada, Brooke, Tofiloski, Voll, Stede, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Maite Taboada, Julian Brooke, Milan Tofiloski, Kimberly Voll, and Manfred Stede. 2011. Lexicon-Based Methods for Sentiment Analysis. Computational Linguistics, 37(2):267 307.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Stefano Vegnaduzzo</author>
</authors>
<title>Acquisition of Subjective Adjectives with Limited Resources.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the AAAI Spring Symposium on Exploring Attitude and Affect in Text: Theories and Applications,</booktitle>
<location>Stanford, CA, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3201" citStr="Vegnaduzzo (2004)" startWordPosition="476" endWordPosition="477">The problem is financial. 2 Related Work The extraction of subjective adjectives has already attracted some considerable attention in previous research. Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997) extract polar adjectives by a weakly supervised method in which subjective adjectives are found by searching for adjectives that are conjuncts of a pre-defined set of polar seed adjectives. Wiebe (2000) induces subjective adjectives with the help of distributional similarity. Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe (2000) examine the properties of dynamic, gradable and polar adjectives as a means to detect subjectivity. Vegnaduzzo (2004) presents another bootstrapping method of extracting subjective adjectives with the help of head nouns of the subjective candidates and distributional similarity. Baroni and Vegnaduzzo 534 \x0c(2004) employ Web-based Mutual information for this task and largely outperform the results produced by Vegnaduzzo (2004). 3 Method In the following, we present different features with the help of which subjective adjectives can be extracted. For all resulting lists, the adjectives will be ranked according to their frequency of co-occurring with a particular feature. 3.1 Extracting Predicative Adjectives</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vegnaduzzo, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Stefano Vegnaduzzo. 2004. Acquisition of Subjective Adjectives with Limited Resources. In Proceedings of the AAAI Spring Symposium on Exploring Attitude and Affect in Text: Theories and Applications, Stanford, CA, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Janyce Wiebe</author>
<author>Theresa Wilson</author>
<author>Rebecca Bruce</author>
<author>Matthew Bell</author>
<author>Melanie Martin</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Subjective Language.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="1219" citStr="Wiebe et al., 2004" startWordPosition="160" endWordPosition="163">xtract subjective adjectives. We do not only compare this criterion with a weakly supervised extraction method but also with gradable adjectives, i.e. another highly subjective subset of adjectives that can be extracted in an unsupervised fashion. In order to prove the robustness of this extraction method, we will evaluate the extraction with the help of two different state-of-the-art sentiment lexicons (as a gold standard). 1 Introduction Since the early work on sentiment analysis, it has been established that the part of speech with the highest proportion of subjective words are adjectives (Wiebe et al., 2004) (see Sentence (1)). However, not all adjectives are subjective (2). (1) A grumpy guest made some impolite remarks to the insecure and inexperienced waitress. (2) The old man wearing a yellow pullover sat on a plastic chair. This justifies the exploration of criteria to automatically separate the subjective adjectives from the nonsubjective adjectives. In this work, we are interested in an out-ofcontext assessment of adjectives and therefore evaluate them with the help of sentiment lexicons. We examine the property of being a predicative adjective as an extraction criterion. Predicative adject</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wiebe, Wilson, Bruce, Bell, Martin, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Janyce Wiebe, Theresa Wilson, Rebecca Bruce, Matthew Bell, and Melanie Martin. 2004. Learning Subjective Language. Computational Linguistics, 30(3).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Janyce Wiebe</author>
<author>Theresa Wilson</author>
<author>Claire Cardie</author>
</authors>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Annotating Expressions of Opinions and Emotions in Language. Language Resources and Evaluation,</booktitle>
<pages>39--2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="13562" citStr="Wiebe et al., 2005" startWordPosition="2100" endWordPosition="2103">ill outperform ALL on both sentiment lexicons (Table 3). Despite the sparseness of our two gold standards on the lower ranks, we thus have some indication that PRD and GRD are more effective than ALL. The problem of the evaluation of less-frequent words could not be solved by an extrinsic evaluation, either, e.g. by using the extracted lists for some text classification task (at the sentence/document level). The evaluation on contextual classification on corpora would also be biased towards high-frequency words (as the word distribution is typically Zipfian). For instance, on the MPQA-corpus (Wiebe et al., 2005), i.e. the standard dataset for (fine-grained) sentiment analysis, there is not a single mention of the subjective words appealable, accommodating, unsurpassed, unopposed, unobtrusive or speechless, which were found among the lower ranks 3001- 3020. 4.3 How Different Are Gradable and Predicative Adjectives? Since in the previous experiments the proportion of subjective adjectives was similar among the gradable adjectives and the predicative adjectives, we may wonder whether these two extraction methods produce the same adjectives. In principle, the set of gradable adjectives extracted is much </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wiebe, Wilson, Cardie, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Janyce Wiebe, Theresa Wilson, and Claire Cardie. 2005. Annotating Expressions of Opinions and Emotions in Language. Language Resources and Evaluation, 39(2/3):164210.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Janyce M Wiebe</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Subjective Adjectives from Corpora.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI),</booktitle>
<pages>735740</pages>
<location>Austin, TX, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2975" citStr="Wiebe (2000)" startWordPosition="444" endWordPosition="445">n both contexts. However, a large fraction of non-subjective adjectives do not occur as predicative adjectives (6). (3) Her idea was brilliant. (4) This is a financial problem. (5) She came up with a brilliant idea. (6) ?The problem is financial. 2 Related Work The extraction of subjective adjectives has already attracted some considerable attention in previous research. Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997) extract polar adjectives by a weakly supervised method in which subjective adjectives are found by searching for adjectives that are conjuncts of a pre-defined set of polar seed adjectives. Wiebe (2000) induces subjective adjectives with the help of distributional similarity. Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe (2000) examine the properties of dynamic, gradable and polar adjectives as a means to detect subjectivity. Vegnaduzzo (2004) presents another bootstrapping method of extracting subjective adjectives with the help of head nouns of the subjective candidates and distributional similarity. Baroni and Vegnaduzzo 534 \x0c(2004) employ Web-based Mutual information for this task and largely outperform the results produced by Vegnaduzzo (2004). 3 Method In the following, we present different features w</context>
<context position="4571" citStr="Wiebe, 2000" startWordPosition="679" endWordPosition="680"> the subject of the sentence via the dependency label nsubj (Example (7) would correspond to Sentence (3)). (7) nsubj(brilliant, idea) 3.2 Extracting Gradable Adjectives (GRD) As an alternative extraction method, we consider morpho-syntactically gradable adjectives. Gradable adjectives, such as nice or small, are adjectives that can be inflected to specify the degree or grade of something (Wiktionary1). It has been stated in previous work that if some adjective can build a comparative (e.g. nicer) or a superlative (e.g. nicest), then this adjective tends to be subjective (Hatzivassiloglou and Wiebe, 2000). We employ the property of gradability, since, firstly, it is very predictive towards subjectivity and, secondly, it is the only other unsupervised criterion currently known to extract subjective adjectives. For the extraction of gradable adjectives, we rely, on the one hand, on the part-of-speech labels JJR (comparative) and JJS (superlative). On the other hand, we also consider adjectives being modified by either more or most. For the former case, we need to normalize the comparative (e.g. nicer) or superlative (e.g. nicest) word form to the canonical positive word form (e.g. nice) that is </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wiebe, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Janyce M. Wiebe. 2000. Learning Subjective Adjectives from Corpora. In Proceedings of the National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), pages 735740, Austin, TX, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Theresa Wilson</author>
<author>Janyce Wiebe</author>
<author>Paul Hoffmann</author>
</authors>
<title>Recognizing Contextual Polarity in Phrase-level Sentiment Analysis.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference on Human Language Technology and Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (HLT/EMNLP),</booktitle>
<pages>347354</pages>
<location>Vancouver, BC,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6760" citStr="Wilson et al., 2005" startWordPosition="1015" endWordPosition="1018"> such as mutual information of two adjectives at the sentence level (or even smaller window sizes). However, using conjunctions largely outperformed these alternative approaches so we only pursue conjunctions here. 4 Experiments As a large unlabeled (training) corpus, we chose the North American News Text Corpus (LDC95T21) comprising approximately 350 million words of news text. For syntactic analysis we use the Stanford Parser (Finkel et al., 2005). In order to decide whether an extracted adjective is subjective or not, we employ two sentiment lexicons, namely the Subjectivity Lexicon (SUB) (Wilson et al., 2005) and SO-CAL (SOC) (Taboada et al., 2011). According to the recent in-depth evaluation presented in Taboada et al. (2011), these two sentiment lexicons are the most effective resources for English sentiment analysis. By taking into account two different lexicons, which have also been built independently of each other, we want to provide evidence that our proposed criterion to extract subjective adjectives is not sensitive towards a particular gold standard (which would challenge the general validity of the proposed method). 535 \x0cALL other new last many first such next political federal own s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wilson, Wiebe, Hoffmann, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Theresa Wilson, Janyce Wiebe, and Paul Hoffmann. 2005. Recognizing Contextual Polarity in Phrase-level Sentiment Analysis. In Proceedings of the Conference on Human Language Technology and Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (HLT/EMNLP), pages 347354, Vancouver, BC, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>